<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Killing is murder, and no murder, or, An exercitation concerning a scurrilous pamphlet of one William Allen, a Jesuitical impostor, intituled, Killing no murder wherein His Highness honor is vindicated and Allens impostors discovered : and wherein the true grounds of government are stated, and his fallacious principles detected and rejected : as also his calumnious scoffs are perstringed and cramb'd down his own throat / by Mich. Hawke, of the Middle-Temple, Gentl.</title>
            <author>Hawke, Michael.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 229 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43095</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1171</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12455</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12844447</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12844447</idno>
            <idno type="VID">94414</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43095)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94414)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 383:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Killing is murder, and no murder, or, An exercitation concerning a scurrilous pamphlet of one William Allen, a Jesuitical impostor, intituled, Killing no murder wherein His Highness honor is vindicated and Allens impostors discovered : and wherein the true grounds of government are stated, and his fallacious principles detected and rejected : as also his calumnious scoffs are perstringed and cramb'd down his own throat / by Mich. Hawke, of the Middle-Temple, Gentl.</title>
                  <author>Hawke, Michael.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[9], 56 p. : port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Edward Sexby and Silius Titus were joint authors of "Killing no murder"; William Allen, under whose name this work appeared, was, like Sexby, a trooper in Cromwell's own regiment.  Cf.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: portrait is lacking in filmed copy.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sexby, Edward, d. 1658. --  Killing no murder.</term>
               <term>Titus, Silius, 1623?-1704. --  Killing no murder.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94414:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:94414:1"/>
            <p>KILLING IS MURDER, AND NO MURDER: <hi>OR</hi> An Exercitation concerning a Scurrilous PAMPHLET, OF ONE <hi>WILLIAM ALLEN, A Jeſuitical Impoſtor;</hi> Intituled KILLING no MURDER: Wherein his <hi>Highneſs</hi> honor is vindicated and <hi>Allens</hi> Impoſtors diſcovered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And wherein the true Grounds of Government are Stated, and his fallacious Principles detected and rejected.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As alſo his Calumnious Scoffs are perſtringed and cramb'd down his own Throat.</p>
            <q>
               <p>An ſiquis atro dente me petiverit,</p>
               <p>In ultus flebo ut puer.</p> 
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Horac. Epod. 6.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Scurror ego ipſe mihi, populo tu. <bibl>
                  <hi>Hor. l. 1. Ep. 19.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>By MICH. HAWKE, of the Middle-Temple Gentl.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for the <hi>Author;</hi> and are to be Sold by the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of <hi>Stationers.</hi> 1657.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="continuation_of_title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94414:2"/>
            <p>ANd firſt of his Title, <hi>Killing no Murder:</hi> Wherein by his Jeſuiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal fallacy he ſhewes himſelf to be of that Faction; for Killing is Murder, and no Murder: And it is no Murder in the Supream, or Subordinate Magiſtrate, for any Capital Crime to condemn one to death, and Execute him: But it is Murder in any private Perſon upon precogitated malice to kill any private Man. And that, if any pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Perſon compaſſe the death of the Supream Magiſtrate,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Coll. comm. f.</hi> 1. 133. <hi>b.</hi>
               </note> and declare it by any overt Fact, though he be a Mad Man (as I ſuppoſe therein <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Allen</hi> is) the very intent is high Treaſon, and Superlative Murder by the Law of God and Nations, though it be not effected; which he in <hi>facto</hi> will be inforced to acknowledge, if once apprehended; notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Jeſuitical Inſtitutions of his Ghoſtly Father <hi>Mariana.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which alſo the taking upon him the ſpurious name of <hi>William Allen</hi> ſeems to ſignify; wherein no man of that name and his condition is to be found within the Latitude of our territories; a faſhion followed by the Jeſuitres,
<note place="margin">Contra Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchi. com.</note> as by <hi>Eudaemon Johannes,</hi> and <hi>Junius Brutus,</hi> whom <hi>Beza</hi> ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to be <hi>Parſons</hi> the Jeſuit; and not without reaſon, ſaith <hi>Barclai,</hi> in that they bluſh to own that opinion, which they in conſcience know to be erroneous: Which is allowable to the Jeſuitical Doctors, to teach o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that which they really know to be erroneous,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See the Preface to the Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cialls. Watſons Quod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libet. f.</hi> 238.</note> as <hi>Layman</hi> the Jeſuit affirmeth, <hi>quamvis ipſe Doctor ejuſmodi ſententiam ſpeculative falfam eſſe ſibi perſuadeat.</hi> Neither doth his bearing of Armes free him from that ſuſpicion; for <hi>Parſon</hi> the Jeſuit is checked by Maſter <hi>Watſon,</hi> for Acting in <hi>Campo Martio,</hi> with <hi>Bellonas</hi> Banners; and if Fame ſpeaks truth, he is not the onely Jeſuit hath under the ſhape of a Souldier lurked, and done miſchief in our Army.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Put them in mind to be ſubject to principalities and powers ready to obey Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, and to every good work.</hi> 
               <bibl>Tit. 3.1.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>Neither murmure, as ſome of them have alſo murmured, and were deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the Deſtroyer.</hi> 
               <bibl>1 Corin. 10.8.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>Curſe not the King, no not in thy thoughts; for a Bird of the Aire ſhall car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the voice, and that which hath Wings ſhall tell the matter.</hi> 
               <bibl>Eccleſ. 10.20.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>Falſa maledicta in privatum quidem non licet jacere, in Regem vero veris abſtinendum.</hi> 
               <bibl>Grot. de bel. l. 1. c. 4.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>Remove from me reproach and contempt; for I have kept thy Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> 
               <bibl>Pſal. 119.221.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>Non eſt ulla res tanti, aut commodum ullum expetendum, ut viri boni &amp; ſplendorem &amp; nomen omittas.</hi> 
               <bibl>Cicer. 3. Offic.</bibl>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:94414:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the Moſt Puiſſant and Prudent PRINCE,</hi> OLIVER CROMWEL, By the Grace of God <hi>LORD PROTECTOR Of the Commonwealth of England, Scotland, and Ireland,</hi> And the Dominions and Territories thereunto belonging.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Renowned PRINCE,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Ardon me, if I preſume to preſent theſe Papers to Your Princely View, as <hi>Juſtine</hi> did his Annals, to the Emperor <hi>Antoninus; Non tam cognoſcendi, quam emendandi
<pb facs="tcp:94414:3"/>cauſa;</hi> not ſo much to inſtruct you as to be Inſtructed of You, who are beſt able to Judge of the Hiſtorical Paſſages re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated in them; in which You have been a Continual and Honorable Actor: Which, if it ſhall pleaſe Your <hi>Highneſs,</hi> to peruſe and examine by the quadrant and ſquare of Your exact Judgement, and peircing Intellect, You ſhall highly Honor him, whoſe ambitious and ulti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate ſcope is to vindicate Your <hi>High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> Honor; which hath alwayes, and ever ſhall be divulged and defended by the Pen, and Hand of Your,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nworthy Servant, and obſervant Subject,</hi> MICH. HAWKE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:94414:3"/>
            <head>To the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pright and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbiaſs'd <hi>READER.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not unknown to ſome great Perſonages, that the Author had compleated this Exercitation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Anſwer to <hi>Killing no Murder</hi> ſaw the light; and had been made pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick ſooner, but that he doubted to divulge it without the ſurveigh of ſome of the Higher Powers: their being therein ſpecified many particular paſſages concerning the State. Neither is it a Novelty, or an inutility for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe Books of the ſame ſubject to paſſe the Preſſe, as St.
<note place="margin">Lib. 1. de Trinit. c. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Auguſtine</hi> upon the ſame occaſion averreth. <hi>Utile eſt</hi> (ſaith he,) <hi>plures libros, a pluribus fieri diverſo ſtilo etiam de quaeſtionibus iiſdem, ut ad plurimos res per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniat ad alios ſic, ad alios autem ſic:</hi> It is profitable to have many Books compoſed of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in a divers ſtile, even of the ſame que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, that the knowledge of the thing may be conveyed to many, to ſome after this manner, to others after another. Which alſo may be very requiſite, and conducent to the ſuffocating of this
<pb facs="tcp:94414:4"/>ſerpentine pamphlet; for a ſingle eye may clearly diſcern by the therein inſerted ſecret and ſeveral relations, that it cannot proceed from one brain, but that it is <hi>Hydra multorum Capitum</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by many virulent Heads, and therefore had need of more Heads then one to incounter it: Beſides many material paſſages are untouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the other, which in this are punctually handled, and not by skippes, but litterally, and orderly decided: And alſo have retorted in his teeth the filth of his ſcurrilous and bitter taunts, and thrown them in his own face, which for the moſt part work more powerfully on cavalier and nimble wits then a Logical Argument; for as <hi>Horatius</hi> one of the Secretaries of <hi>Auguſtus,</hi>
               <q>Ridiculum acri Fortius,
<note place="margin">Horat. l. 2. Sp. 1</note> &amp; melius magnam plerum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſecat rem.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Which are generally by him pretermitted. My intention is not to diſparrage the Author; for in many things he hath done very well; <hi>Sed plus vident oculi, quam oculus:</hi> Two eys ſee more then one.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:94414:4"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>IT hath been deemed prudence in Princes, to ſleight calumnies; for which</hi> Tacitus <hi>gives theſe Reaſons,</hi> Quia ſpreta exoleſcunt, ſi iraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care, agnita videautur; <hi>becauſe, they being ſlighted vaniſh and come to naught; but if you be angry at them you ſeem to acknowledge them; and in another place by condemning them,</hi> Nil niſi dedecus ſibi, atque illis gloriam peperere,
<note place="margin">View of the Civil Law, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> fo. 31.</note> 
               <hi>They have purchaſed nothing but diſgrace to themſelves, and glory to the Authors: which are to be underſtood of defamations, proceeding from the lubricity of the tongue, or weakneſs of the brain as Sir</hi> Thomas Ridley <hi>diſtinguiſheth, according to the ſaying of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror,</hi> Siquis Imperatori maledixerit ſi id ex levitate proceſſerit, contemnen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum eſt; ſi ex inſania, miſeratione digniſſimum. <hi>If any ſhall ſpeak evil of the Emperor, if it proceed from lightneſs, it is to be contemned, if from madneſs, it is worthy of commiſeration, but if they be</hi> Vulnifici ſales &amp; cruenta verba, <hi>Wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and bloody words, full of rancour and malice;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Curt. l. 6.</note> 
               <hi>which as</hi> Alexander <hi>in</hi> Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius, perveniunt ad gladios, <hi>Produce quarrels and ſeditions: Such Calumnia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors according to the conſtitution of</hi> Theodoſius, <hi>ought to be ſecured, by Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and according to other Princes, by Death,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tac. l. 6.</note> 
               <hi>as</hi> Tiberius <hi>the ſageſt of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, who otherwiſe, was merciful to</hi> Male-dicants, <hi>cauſed</hi> Panconianus <hi>for compoſing Verſes in diſgrace of him to be condemned</hi> Laeſae Majeſtatis, <hi>Of High Treaſon, and to be ſtrangled in Priſon; which moved</hi> Henry <hi>the Seventh, whom Sir</hi> Francis Bacon <hi>adorneth with the Elegy of awiſe Prince,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bacon His H. 7</note> 
               <hi>to hang and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute five perſons, for contriving and ſpreading of ſwarms and volleyes of Libels againſt his Majeſty.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Clapm. l. 6. nuper.</note> 
               <hi>And ſo ſevere and ſtrict was the great Turk in puniſhing this crime, who in moral policy by dilating his Empire ſeemeth ſecond to none, that he commanded fifty Scholaſtiques whom they called Totti, to be put to death, becauſe they made certain ſignes and ſignification of a ſiniſter conceit they had of him, which might be conceived to be a very cruel cenſure; but that the Wiſeman intimateth the ſame</hi> Eccleſ. 10.20. <hi>Curſe not the King no not in thy thoughts; and that the diſparagement of Princes are the fomentaries,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem. H. 7.</note> 
               <hi>and as Sir</hi> Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Bacon <hi>the Females of Sedition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And though the words of a malitious Detractor as the Wiſe-man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plut. Apotheg.</note> 
               <hi>are ſharper then Swords, or as Heracides, then whetted Swords, and penetrate into the Bowels of the Belly, yet the diffamations of a Libeller, are more pernicious eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially Printed Libels, becauſe more permanent;</hi> Littera Scripta manet, <hi>and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually read &amp; carried from one malevolent hand to another, and will not</hi> exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſcere <hi>as</hi> Tacitus <hi>ſaith, but</hi> gliſcere, <hi>not decay but increaſe; for moſt men are tranſported with a philauty or ſelf-reſpect, and have envious and itching ears, to hear ill reports of others, and are eaſily induced to beleeve them. So as the more dangerous they are, the greater care ſhould be taken, to cancel, and vacuate them, which may be according to the practice of other Princes, either</hi> Creman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do,
<pb facs="tcp:94414:5"/>
               <hi>by apprehending them in</hi> Ovo <hi>when they ſweat under the Preſſe; And to fire them as</hi> Tiberius <hi>did thoſe of</hi> Liberius, <hi>who wrote the Elegy of</hi> Brutus <hi>and</hi> Caſſius: <hi>or elſe</hi> refutando, <hi>by Reaſons, which work moſt on a man, to refute them: as the moſt learned Doctor</hi> Andrew <hi>handled and tortured</hi> Tortus, <hi>who by his Pen, as this Libeller attempted to ſeduce the Princes Subjects from their allegiance; Theſe are the thoughts which have inſtigated the Author, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel, and confute, this peſtilent and perilous Libel, which punctually levelleth at the ruin, and fate of his</hi> Highneſs; <hi>and alſo by collection of other Princes, for under the pretence and colour of Tyranny, he concludeth it lawfull for any obſcure or ſordid perſon to kill or murder his Sovereign Prince, pronouncing it to be a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and magnanimous Act ſo to do. And for ſo much that this Paſquil is covertly diſperſed among diſcontented and ſeditious perſons, which they embrace as their Apoſtles Creed, and communicate and extol it to others, as an indubitable, and ſacred Truth, whereby many well diſpoſed people may be debauched, corrupted, and withdrawn from their due obedience to their Prince. The Author, thought it his duty to the Prince, and Publique, to prevent ſuch imminent and future miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs, by making it manifeſt, that every</hi> page <hi>of this Paſquiller is full fraught with venemous errors,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Oſeand. Cent.</note> 
               <hi>and ſeditions falſities. And that their Apoſtle is</hi> Os Diaboli <hi>as</hi> Irenaeus <hi>ſtiled</hi> Marcion, <hi>the Mouth of the Devil; and that this</hi> Creed <hi>is the Devils Creed, forged in the Infernal Shop of</hi> King Killing Jeſuits <hi>his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected Apoſtles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein if the Author ſhall ſeem Superficially Prolix</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Utque oblita modi milleſima pagina ſurgat.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>Yet hopeth he well that the Serious Obſervator will mark,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Juv. Sav. 7.</note> 
               <hi>and conſider the various, curt and cloſe couched Historical Paſſages, with his Suſpence and involved Queſtions, which could not be clearly conceived, and fully refelled in conciſer and fewer Lines.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:94414:5"/>
            <p>ANd firſt in general to tax him for his Calumnies,
<note place="margin">Invidia ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniae mater. Lip. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ont.</note> the brood of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy and malice, wherein he followeth the ſteps of <hi>Satan,</hi> who for calumniating and accuſing his Brethren is ſirnamed <hi>Diabolus,</hi> which in the Original ſignifieth a <hi>Calumniator;</hi> and practiſeth the precept of <hi>Medius,</hi> whom <hi>Plutarche</hi> ſtileth <hi>Dux Calumniatorum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plutarche de diff. &amp; ad</note> the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of Calumniators, which is <hi>Audacter calumniis mordere, inquiens, ſi is qui morſus eſt, vulneri medeatur, cicatricem tamen relinqui;</hi> boldly to bite with Calumnies, ſaying, that if he that is ſo bitten be cured, yet a ſcarre will remain; for as <hi>Machiavel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Machiavel. l.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 8.</note> though Calumnies be grounded on ſlight ſuſpitions, yet they being once divulged and entertained will hardly be removed. And this is generally this Impoſtors breviary, or practiſe of piety in all the paſſages of this <hi>Paſquil,</hi> to interlace, and interweave here and there divers contumelious opprobries againſt his <hi>Highneſs,</hi> which though they be univerſally fictitious, yet hopeth he that ſome ſcarre or filth will adheare to his ſkin; but he is vaniely deceived, for the Magnanimity and integrity of his <hi>Highneſs</hi> will with ſcorn and contempt caſt off the dirt, and filth of his contumelies, as a Lion doth dirty water paſſing through a miry ſlough, without any blemiſh remaining, ſaying, <hi>Ille didicit maledice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, ego maledicta contemnere;</hi> he hath learned to revile, and I to contemne revilings.</p>
            <p>And then in particular to purſue him cloſe,
<note place="margin">Terent.</note> and to pay him in his own coyne: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t quod ab ipſo allatum eſt, id ſibi illatum putet;</hi> that what ſcoffes are caſt from him, he may find retorted on him.</p>
            <p>In the front he placeth his ſupplication to his <hi>Highneſs,</hi> which is as full of jeeres as words, wherein he endeavoureth with <hi>Archilochus</hi> by his ſnar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſcoffes, to jeere his <hi>Highneſs</hi> out of his life, as he did <hi>Lycambes</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Verſe,
<q>Tincta Lycambaeo ſanguine tela gerunt:</q>
            </p>
            <p>And would fain perſwade his <hi>Highneſs</hi> to his <hi>happy expiration, whereby he might ſhew himſelf a true Father and Deliverer of his Countrey, and free it from a bondage little inferior to that from which</hi> Moſes <hi>delivered his</hi> — (A Simile, which by his often repetition ſeemeth much to pleaſe his fancy, though no more like then this Impoſtor is to a true <hi>Iſraelite) and that then he will be a true Reformer of Religion, and till then we can call nothing our own; and that by his death we hope for our Inheritance, with ſome other Ironys</hi> tending to that purpoſe, which becomes the Kings <hi>Jeſter</hi> better then a States man, as he would ſeem to be: but his <hi>Highneſs</hi> may truely and juſtly ſay with <hi>Titus</hi> the beſt of the <hi>Roman Emperors,</hi> who by ſuch De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractors was reproached in the like kind; Seeing I have done nothing worthy of reproach, <hi>Mendacia non curo;</hi> I weigh not lyes: and that by all
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:94414:6"/>peaceable and prudent people and their Repreſentative; he is acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to be a true Father of his Countrey, and a Deliverer of his people, from the <hi>Aegyptian</hi> bondage of Popery and Tyranny, and that by his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal and Princely care; our Inheritances are ſetled and protected againſt forreine invaſions; and domeſtique ſeditions, unleſſe theirs who through inteſtine inſurrections, or publique Rebellions have juſtly forfeited the ſame, ſuch as this Impoſtor and his Confederates are, or have been.</p>
            <p>And that contrary to this <hi>Impoſtors</hi> contumelions ſuggeſtion, juſtice is not defined by the will and pleaſure of the ſtrongeſt; but other Laws take place as well as thoſe of the Sword, which all the ſubordinate Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciaries to his <hi>Highneſs</hi> will averre; that it hath been his principal and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emptory charge to them to adminiſter Juſtice to all impartially, without any reſpect of perſons, according to the Laws of the Land; and that his <hi>Highneſs</hi> upon particular complaints of divers of his people, pretending that they have not received Juſtice, by the hands of his Juſticiaries hath called them before him, and according to Law, equity, and good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience heard and determined the ſame. And as <hi>St. Paul</hi> did, ſo doth his <hi>Highneſs</hi> exerciſe himſelf to have alwayes a good conſcience, void of all offence, towards God and man; where is then the terror of conſcience this Impoſtor would faſten on his <hi>Highneſs?</hi> is it not fixed in his own heart?
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.2.</note> is not he one of them the Apoſtle mentioneth, who ſpeaking lyes with Hypocriſy, having his conſcience ſeared with an hot Iron, giveth heed to ſeducing Spirits, and the Doctrine of Devils? For who can deny but it is the Doctrine of the Devil, who was an Homicide from the beginning, to give the Reins of Authority to diſſolute perſons, to wound and ſlaughter the ſupream Magiſtrate, to whom they ought not onely to be ſubject for wrath but for conſcience ſake?</p>
            <p>And therefore it behooveth <hi>William Allen</hi> to conſider in his own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, in what a ſad and deſperate condition he ſtandeth through his Diabolical murderous intention, whereby he cannot onely eſcape the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain doom of Gods vengeance, but alſo incurre the Capital cenſure of his Vicegerent; which to avoid, I will not adviſe him as he did his <hi>Highneſs,</hi> though it may be ſuppoſed, that to eſcape a ſhameful death like <hi>Brutus</hi> and <hi>Caſſius,</hi> he will periſh on his own Sword, or rather with <hi>Judas</hi> frighted with the terror of conſcience will be his own Hangman, or elſe with his renowned <hi>Sindercombe</hi> ſwallow a Spaniſh Figge to ſhun the Triple Tree; but why ſhould he be ſuppoſed to be ſo Valiant, whoſe valour, like <hi>Therſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res,</hi> conſiſteth onely in braving, railing, and encouraging others to fight, and aſſault one he dares not himſelf encounter; and what man of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſence will give ear and credit to his exhortations, by which he would incite others to Act that horrid Homicide he himſelf feareth to attempt? Howſoever this Impoſtor may aſſure himſelf, that his <hi>Highneſs</hi> hath his heart and conſcience ſo armed, and fortified with Religious fortitude, and Pious conſtancy, that no Scuril or popular conceits can deterre him from laying faſt hold on his Scepter.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Virtus repulſae neſcia ſordidae,</l>
               <l>Intaminatis fulget honoribus,</l>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:94414:6"/>
               <l>Nec ſumit aut ponit ſecures</l>
               <l>— Arbitrio popularis aurae.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Next followeth his Dedication, which is as full of ſhifts, as his ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was of ſcoffs,
<q>Aſtutam vapido ſervans ſub pectore vulpem:</q>
               <q>Shrowding two faces under one ſubtile hood.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein he ſtraineth all the nerves of his conceit to corrupt and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch the Army, and either to withdraw it from his <hi>Highneſs,</hi> or to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide it to its and his <hi>Highneſs</hi> deſtruction, which is apparent in the Title; it being directed to all <hi>thoſe Officers and Souldiers of the Army that remember their engagements, and dare be honeſt (hoping at the leaſt to gain the honeſt party to his Devotion.)</hi> But I wonder much that he ſhould have ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in the honeſt party, having ſo little honeſty himſelf; for what ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt man would attempt to divide but unite, and eſpecially the Army, whereby it might be decayed or ruined, which under God was the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal meanes of procuring our Liberty, and of preſerving the ſame? but what cares <hi>William Allen</hi> if with <hi>Phaeton</hi> he fires the world, ſo he may have his will; to wit the ruine of his <hi>Highneſs,</hi> which is the fatal cloſe of his Dedicatory Epiſtle? This the Levellers aimed at in the year 1649. and the fifth Monarchy men in the year 1654.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See the Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Parliament of England, dated</hi> 27. <hi>September</hi> 1649. <hi>And the Caſe of the Commonwealth &amp;c. Dated</hi> 1654. <hi>See the true Caſe of the Commonwealth &amp;c. Dated</hi> 1654.</note> by the diviſion and alteration of the Army, to ſuppreſſe the Generals; but his <hi>Highneſs</hi> and the Army are in one Body ſo naturally and affectionately incorporated, that no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand or divice can diſſipate and ſeparate them, no more then the device of <hi>Pompy,</hi> and the Commande of the Senate could <hi>Caeſar</hi> and his Army at <hi>Rubicon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to weigh his wily Arguments, by which he cunningly goeth about to ſeduce the Army from his <hi>Highneſs;</hi> the one, and the Prime one, is, that <hi>the Officers and Souldiers of the Army, which were raiſed to defend the Priviledges of Parliament, his</hi> Highneſs <hi>hath made to diſſolve Parliaments.</hi> This is a fallacy from the cauſe, <hi>a non cauſa ut cauſa;</hi> for the raiſing of the Army was not to defend the Priviledges of Parliament, but to bring De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents to condigne puniſhment, the maintenance of the Laws, and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of the Land, and of due ſucceſſions of Parliament, which did not intend to quarrel with the Kingly Government, but to regulate the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders, and exceſſes in the Government. And the Army never took up Armes againſt any particular form of Government, nor ever fought againſt the King as a King, nor for the Parliament meerly as a Parliament, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares by all the Papers and Declarations have been publiſhed in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of theſe Warres; and therefore was the long Parliament juſtly diſſolved by the Army, becauſe it exceeded the due time of ſucceſſions of Parliaments, which ſhould have been but triennial, &amp; not perpetual as they would have had it; beſides many other enormities did concurre to its diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, which in the true State of the Commonwealth Stated, Dated 1654. Fo. 11.12. are amply declared, ſo as when that was diſſolved, there was not ſo much heard as the barking of ſuch a Dog as the Impoſtor is, or any general or viſible repining at that; and the Souldiers therein were not made the Inſtruments of ſlavery, and eſtabliſhers of Tyranny as he
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:94414:7"/>ſaith, but the Reſtorers of our Liberty, and Inſtruments of Juſtice. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Parliament I know of, but that it did continue out the fixt period of time, according to the firſt Inſtitution.</p>
            <p>And as concerning their engagements; the Parliament being juſtly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, the engagements concerning the Priviledges of the ſame, are alſo juſtly diſſolved; for all promiſſory Oaths as engagements are but Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal ties, grounded upon Political conſiderations for Politique ends, and binde no longer then the particular Politei and State ſtandeth; for as the <hi>Civilians</hi> diſtinguiſh in ſuch Oaths,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tholoſa Syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tag.</hi> 49. <hi>c.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>appoſita clauſula cenſeatur, promiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem valere rebus ſic ut tunc erant extantibus &amp; in eodem ſtatu permanentibus;</hi> an annexed clauſe or condition is to be ſuppoſed, that promiſe to be of force, things ſtanding as they then were, and remaining in the ſame State; ſo as if that State be changed and ended, ſuch engagements as reflect on it are determined; which diſtinction this Impoſtor might have learned of his Maſter <hi>Suares,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Suares reſp. ad apologiam pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure fidelit.</hi> 409.</note> 
               <hi>Quod ſublata materia Juramenti, conſequenter obligatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem auferri neceſſe eſt;</hi> that the matter of the Oath being taken away, by conſequence the Obligation of neceſſity muſt be taken away; as if a King, ſaith he, be depoſed, he ceaſeth to be a King; and in that reſpect no obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience is due unto him, and forthwith the Oath doth not binde; <hi>à fortiori,</hi> if the Government be determined, and the matter of the Oath diſſolved, the Obligation of the Oath is <hi>ipſo facto</hi> exſtinct; for as Maſter <hi>Askham,</hi> poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion is the great condition for our obedience and allegiance; how unjuſtly therefore doth this Impoſtor call theſe diſtinctions prevarications to piece up contrary Oaths, which are grounded on approved Authority, and his own Maſters opinion. The other reaſon on which he groundeth his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious deſgne, is, that the Officers and <hi>Souldiers of the Army are employed to force Elections,</hi> that is, as may be conceived to ſeculde ſuch as are tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulent and factious from being Elected, and admitted members of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, wherein we are to diſtinguiſh between a quiet and ſetled State, and a Commonwealth which is diſtracted with factions. In the firſt a free E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of Knights, Burgeſſes, and Citizens in Parliament, is requiſite, and ought to be, as <hi>Plato</hi> ſaith, <hi>Libere &amp; incorrupte;</hi> in the ſecond a free Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is altogether inconvenient and dangerous; for otherwiſe that great Council may be diſtracted, and overruled by turbulent Spirits, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by it reſolved for the publique good: A pregnant Example, of which we lately had in the proceedings of the late Precedent Parliament,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See his High.</hi> 22. <hi>Jan.</hi> 1654.</note> which as his <hi>Highneſs</hi> ſaith, wholy ſpent their time, and did nothing. And in ſuch caſes of extremity where there is no courſe of prevention otherwiſe provided by Parliament, <hi>Expedit principi omnium diſſentionum cauſas in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pub. dirimere;</hi> it appertaineth to the Prince to prevent all cauſes of diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Commonwealth, for he is the ſupreame <hi>Conſervator pacis;</hi> and by the advice of his Council may bar, and fruſtrate the Election of thoſe of whoſe malignancy and diſaffection to the State; he hath received cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and infallible intelligence, and that by way of preventing future diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord and diſtraction; and accordingly in the turbulent times of <hi>Henry</hi> the third, when the Kingdom was divided into two mighty Parties, That wiſe King called the beſt affected onely to Parliament, as Maſter <hi>Cambden</hi> in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:94414:7"/>his <hi>Britannia</hi> relateth; <hi>Ad ſummum honorem pertinet,</hi> ſaith he,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>F.</hi> 122.</note> 
               <hi>Ex quo</hi> Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricus <hi>tertius ex tanta multitudine quae ſeditioſa, &amp; turbulenta fuit, optimos quoſque ad Parlementaria comitia evocaverit.</hi> It was an highly honoured Act in <hi>Henry</hi> the third, that out of ſo great a multitude, which was ſeditious and turbalent, he had called every one of the beſt affected to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by whoſe prudence and moderation the torn Eſtate of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom was cemented and ſetled in an uniformity of peace and tranquillity. In like manner did his <hi>Highneſs</hi> this Parliament out of a multitude of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant and diſcontented perſons, by the advice of his Council, according to the Inſtrument of Government, call and admit thoſe onely who were beſt affected, and well diſpoſed, into the Parliament Houſe; by whoſe wiſdom and advice with little diſturbance and contradiction the three main Pillars of the State, which were then tottering, were firmly fixed and eſtabliſhed by Act of Parliament; to wit, the ſupreame Magiſtracy was confirmed in his <hi>Highneſs,</hi> the ſucceſſion ſetled, and the Liberties of the people were Ratified, and ſecured by his <hi>Highneſs,</hi> according to the advice and Requeſt of the Members of Parliament; and were not as he impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently ſaith, Pimps of Tyranny, onely imployed to draw the people to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute their Liberty.</p>
            <p>How unworthily and injuriouſly therefore doth this Impoſtor brand that pacifique and prudent Parliament in divers paſſages of his Paſquil with the ſtrange name of a <hi>Junto</hi> (with whoſe ſound he is as much plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed as children are with the ſtrange noiſe of a Rattle) becauſe it was pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and cleanſed of ſuch malignant and factious ſpirits, and not virtuous, as this Impoſtor ſaith, who would have fomented diſcord and diſſentions among them: By which means the diſtracted State of theſe Nations is hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily united to the content of his Highneſs, and ſatisfaction of the People: And that with the approbation and applauſe of the Religious, Zealous, Faithfull, and Couragious Officers and Souldiers of the Army, as he ſtileth them, notwithſtanding his conjuring imprecations, who for their fidelity upon occaſions, are deſervedly advanced &amp; exalted by their magnificent &amp; victorious Prince &amp; General; &amp; <hi>not ruined by him whom they raiſed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>F.</hi> 15.</note> according to this Impoſtors <hi>Machiavilian</hi> rule, <hi>which,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>Princes obſerve, when they are in power, never to make uſe of thoſe that help'd them to it;</hi> unleſs they be ſuch as this Impoſtor is, Seducing Mutineers, who are juſtly purged, and caſt out of the Army like dung, and like cudgeled hounds lye lurk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their kennel, bawling, barking, and catching at flies, and are not like to riſe, or be exalted, unleſs it be as <hi>Haman</hi> was, and as he divineth, be hanged up like bottles.</p>
            <q>Qui male dixerit pejus audiet.</q>
            <p>His Preface now enſueth, wherein, like the Fox, though he ſeems to change his hair and outſide, yet ſtill retains his nature and manners, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Proverb, <hi>Vulpem pilum mutare, non mores;</hi> and pretendeth, <hi>that it was not inſtigations of private revenge and malice</hi> (though it may be conceived, <hi>manet alta mente repoſtum,</hi> that his publique diſgrace doth ſtill ſtick in his ſtomack) <hi>but indignation did make him break that ſilence pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence would perswade him to uſe.</hi> But indignation and anger, ſaith the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:94414:8"/>Royal Preacher,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.9.</note> reſteth in the boſom of fools: And, <hi>Ira furor brevis eſt,</hi> Anger is a mad Pen-man, which makes him uſe ſuch frantick and wild ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions. But what is he angry at? <hi>but that he ſhall employ his time and pains to little purpoſe</hi> (which he truly divines) <hi>or to think that any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of his, or convictions of theirs, ſhall draw men from any thing wherein they ſhall ſee profit, or ſecurity; or to any thing wherein they ſhall ſee loſs, and fear of danger</hi> (which alſo is true) for, by the dictate of reaſon, every one is taught and convicted to purſue his own profit, and to ſhun danger; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will any one of ſound ſenſe hearken to his unprofitable and unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable deluſions.</p>
            <p>And, <hi>that we court our bondage, and place it among the requeſts we put up to him</hi> (which is <hi>illi cordolium,</hi> and ſtrikes to his heart to ſee the ſincere affection of the Parliament, and their reſpective obſervance) And, <hi>that he expecteth not onely danger from ill men, but diſallowance from many which are good, that have a zeal, but not according to knowledge</hi> (neither of which he hath, which therefore he muſt expect.) All his hopes is, <hi>in honeſt and wiſe men, which,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>are but few,</hi> or indeed none at all; for what ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt or wiſe man will give ear to his projects, which as he confeſſeth, <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear ſo bloody, and ſo cruel,</hi> unleſs ſuch diſcontented and forlorn perſons as himſelf, whoſe life is a death to them, and for whom <hi>Timon Miſanthro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos</hi> hath prepared a new Gibbet in his Garden, expecting daily their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired hanſel.</p>
            <p>But his ſoul Pen beſpatters not onely his Highneſs, but his accomplices, as he terms them, and eſpecially Mr. Speaker by name, for giving Mr. <hi>Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dercombes traiterous deſigne the epithites of bloody, wicked, and proceeding from the prince of darkneſs, fearing that the people judging of things accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their outward appearances, without penetrating at all into their cauſes and natures, when they ſhall read the Pamphlet of Mr. Speaker, they will certainly think he gives thoſe plotters the right Titles;</hi> and not without good reaſon; for though the vulgar do not ordinarily dive into the cauſes of things, are not wiſe enough to apprehend them, yet moſt of them are ſo wiſe, as to hearken unto the advice and reports of thoſe whom they know to be wiſe, and able to judge of them (whom <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in that reſpect adjudgeth to be wiſe men) And therefore without doubt, they will ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er believe what is declared by Mr. Speaker, who is a man of Authority, and who hath alwayes been reputed <hi>vir bonus, &amp; ſapiens,</hi> a wiſe, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt man, then that what is feigned and foyſted in the Pamphlet of this Impoſtor, an obſcure, ſcurril and lying Paſquiller, which for it in divers places of the City of <hi>London</hi> was burnt by the people, for want of an Hangman, which is notoriouſly manifeſt, in that he ſeemeth to doubt of <hi>Sindercombes</hi> traiterous deſign, and ſuſpitiouſly to aſcribe it to his Highneſs invention, whereas the contrary is made clear by the confeſſion of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates, and upon ſufficient evidence, at a publique Trial, ſo adjudged. Which is not unlike to his lying proteſtation, to wit, <hi>that his principal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent in this paper is not to declaim againſt my Lord Protector, or his Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices; and that were it not more to juſtifie others then to accuſe them, he ſhould think their own actions ſhould juſtifie them ſufficiently;</hi> which, as <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:94414:8"/>is <hi>magnum &amp; impudens mendacium,</hi> a great and impudent lye: For in his Supplication he perſwadeth his Highneſs to his <hi>happy expiration, and that his death ſhall ſomething ballance the evils of his life.</hi> And in his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication he inciteth the Officers of the Army againſt him, <hi>that they can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver redeem their honour untill they ſee their revenge upon his faithleſs head.</hi> And herein in his Preface he juſtifieth it lawfull for <hi>Sindercomb</hi> to have killed him, as a <hi>Tyrant,</hi> and by conſequence for any other private man. If then to perſwade his Highneſs to his expiration, or to incite the Army to take away his life, or to allow it lawfull for any private perſon to kill him, and that as it is probably ſaid, <hi>tribus bolis,</hi> he would have him forthwith devoured one way or other, be not principally to declaim againſt his Highneſs, then fools cannot ſpeak nonſence.</p>
            <p>But what will <hi>William Allen</hi> gain by his lying, but that when he ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth truth, no man will beleeve him, but ſay to him as it is ſaid in the Comedy, <hi>Si dixeris mendacium ſolens tuo more feceris?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plaut. Amph.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But to paſs by his other ſenſleſs and ſuperfluous paſſages, and to diſcuſs and examin his three ſerious queſtions, which contain in them the conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and venom of this peſtilent Pamphlet.</p>
            <p>The firſt is, <hi>Whether my Lord Protector be a Tyrant or no?</hi> which he ſaith is <hi>no queſtion,</hi> and would <hi>diſputare ex non conceſſis;</hi> but he ſhall neither find it granted of us, nor proved by him.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is, <hi>If he be, whether it it is lawfull to do juſtice upon him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſolemnity, that is, to kill him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third is, <hi>If it be lawfull, whether it is likely to prove profitable, or noxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the Common-wealth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt queſtion: <hi>Bartolus</hi> makes Tyrants of two ſorts, <hi>In titulo,</hi> or <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercitio;</hi> the one is called a Tyrant, becauſe he hath no Right to govern; and the other, becauſe he governeth not rightly, or as he Phraſeth it, Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannically; and at laſt inferreth that the <hi>Protector may with great Juſtice put in this claime to both Titles, but how unjuſtly, the concluſion will manifeſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And then ſaith, that <hi>we ſhall ſufficiently demonſtrate who they are that have not right to govern, if we ſhew who they are that have:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ariſt. Polit. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> And firſt he premiſeth truely that the ſupreame Power was firſt placed in Fathers of Families, as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> tells us from <hi>Homer,</hi> that every one gives Laws to his Wife and Children; ſo <hi>Adam</hi> was the King and Lord of his Family; and a Son a ſubject, and a Servant was then one and the ſame thing; and this power was exerciſed everywhere where Families were diſperſed, and ſome ſmall time in ſome places after Commonwealths were conſtituted; but whereas <hi>William Allen</hi> aſſumeth, that after, of many Houſes and Families a Society was made, the ſupreame Power was deſigned and ſetled in one man, by the conſent and Election of the people, where the immediate ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of God himſelf did not interpoſe; <hi>William Allen</hi> muſt give me leave to leave him; for after the fall of our firſt Parents the natural State of men, before they were ſetled in a Society, as Maſter <hi>Hobbs</hi> truely ſaith, was a meer Warre; and as <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rules concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. F.</hi> 14.</note> 
               <hi>tantum haberent quantum manu ac viri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus per caedem &amp; vulnera eripere, &amp; retinere potuiſſent:</hi> had ſo much as by force and might through wounds and ſlaughters they could obtain and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:94414:9"/>and as his Maſter <hi>Mariana</hi> in thoſe times, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bique latrocinia, direptio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, caedeſque graſſabantur;</hi> everywhere Robbery, Rapine, and Slaughter did rage,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Regis Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tut. Fo.</hi> 16. <hi>Gen.</hi> 6. <hi>Lib.</hi> 1.</note> which abhorreth not much from the Sacred Scriptures, as is plain by the Tragedy of <hi>Abel</hi> and the Murtherous minde of <hi>Lamech:</hi> And what may be meant by the Giants who were mighty men, and in the old time men of renown, but ſuch as <hi>Thucydides</hi> writes of, who by force and rapine did ſnatch and catch what they could from others, holding it an honour, and no diſgrace, ſo it was Valiantly done; all which continually happened be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſetlement of a Society by a Supreame Governor; how then was it poſſible for ſuch a diſcordant multitude of people ſolemnly to concurre, or unanimouſly to conſent in the Election and approbation of a Supreame Magiſtrate, which indeed at that time was <hi>bellua multorum Capitum?</hi> and though God for the ſpecial care he had of the People of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> did ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time after a ſpecial manner chooſe their King, whom the people afterwards did accept and approve, yet cannot this Impoſtor find any Place or Text in the Scripture, where any Power or Commiſſion is given to the people to govern themſelves, or chooſe themſelves a Governor, or to alter the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of Governement at their pleaſure; though this Impoſtor would <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortâ gula</hi> wreſt the Text of <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.14, 15. to that purpoſe; <hi>If thou ſay I will ſet a King over me, like as all the Nations are about me;</hi> Thou <hi>ſhalt make a King over thee, ſuch as the Lord thy God ſhal chooſe;</hi> ſo as notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their ſaying, the choiſe and nomination of their King was to proceed from God; and therefore according to that prediction, when the people did aſk a King;
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.5.</note> and that <hi>Samuel</hi> would make them a King to Judge them like other Nations, he ſhewed them <hi>Saul,</hi> ſaying, See you him whom the Lord hath choſen,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.5.</note> which the people acknowledged, ſhowting and ſaying, God ſave the King.</p>
            <p>And in that he ſaith, <hi>it is plain in that place that God gives the people the choiſe of their King,</hi> for there <hi>he inſtructs them whom they ſhall chooſe, one of the midſt of their Brethren:</hi> This is otherwiſe; for he there ſaith not they ſhall chooſe a King <hi>from among their Brethren;</hi> but they ſhall make a King over them;
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.1.</note> from among thy Brethren, whom the Lord God ſhall chooſe; that is to ſay, ſhall approve and confirme Gods choiſe: So <hi>Saul</hi> was choſen by God, and anointed by <hi>Samuel,</hi> but was made, that is, confirmed King by all the people in Gilgal; ſo <hi>David</hi> was choſen by God, and anointed by the ſame Prophet, but was afterwards confirmed by the people of <hi>Juda</hi> and the Elders of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.2.14.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And if the peoples conſent were alone ſufficient, then was Gods choice in vain; but I hope this Impoſtor will not be ſo vain in this as in other things he is, to make Gods Election and choice vain, to pleaſe the people; for <hi>Deus &amp; natura nil faciunt fruſtra,</hi> God and nature do nothing in vain: Much more he ſaith he could ſay if it were a leſſe Manifeſt truth, to wit for the Election of the people; but how can it be a Manifeſt truth is ſo abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant from reaſon? for it is averſe from reaſon, that men who are free by nature, ſhould by free Elections expoſe themſelves to imperious ſubjection, without fear or force;
<note place="margin">Oratio ad Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarem.</note> for by nature every one <hi>aſperrime Rectorem patitur,</hi> un willingly and ſtubbornly endureth a Ruler; eſpecially to have the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:94414:9"/>Power of life and death over him, as every Ruler hath; whereupon <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricius</hi> inferreth this concluſion, <hi>Nulla gens ſine aliquo metu,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De rep. F.</hi> 6.</note> 
               <hi>vel vi ſupremo Magiſtratui ſe ſubjecit;</hi> and therefore as <hi>Bodin</hi> ſaith, <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> is deceived in ſuppoſing that Kings where choſen by the ſuffrages of the people; <hi>fallit enim</hi> Ariſtoteles, ſaith he,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bodin. de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pub. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>qui aureum illud genus hominum Fabalis Poetarum quam ipſa re illuſtrius, Reges Heroas ſuffragio creaſſe prodidit; Ariſtotle</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth in that he ſheweth that the people who lived in the Golden Age, did create their Heroique Kings by ſuffrages, which is more Illuſtrious by Poetical Figments then by real truths; for it is perſpicuous that the firſt Kingdom and Royalty was conſtituted by <hi>Nimrod,</hi> whom the Sacred Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters call a mighty Hunter, becauſe by force he gained his Kingdom; for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his age, Liberty was equal to all; and he was the firſt that compelled Free men to ſubjection, and therefore is called <hi>Nimrodus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>In. Gen.</hi> 10.</note> that is <hi>Dominus metuendus,</hi> a terrible Lord, and as <hi>Toſtatus,</hi> was the firſt King and Monarch, becauſe we read of none in Holy Scriptures Reigned before him.</p>
            <p>But againſt this I ſurmiſe this Impoſtor will object who goeth about to make all Princes Tyrants in <hi>Titulo,</hi> whoſe Power is not founded on popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Election or conſent; that <hi>Nimrod</hi> was a Tyrant, becauſe he was a mighty Hunter, <hi>Populoſque vi &amp; armis Sceptro ſubjecit,</hi> and ſubjected the people by force, and Armes to his Scepter; but on the contrary he is ſaid to be a mighty Hunter before the Lord, becauſe as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cajus in Ariſt. Fo.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 10. <hi>Cornelius de lapide Melchior Canus, Aben Ezra in</hi> 10. <hi>Gen. Barcl. contrae Monarch</hi> F. 281. <hi>Acq. ſum. pa.</hi> 1. <hi>q.</hi> 63. <hi>Ar.</hi> 4. <hi>Syntag. Ic. l.</hi> 18. <hi>c.</hi> 18. <hi>c.</hi> 12.</note> 
               <hi>robur accepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat à Domino;</hi> he had received his ſtrength from the Lord, by which he ſubdued the people that lived in that age; and that he <hi>nutu &amp; beneplacito Dei,</hi> by the impulſe &amp; good pleaſure of God had forced the barbarous and rude people unto a Civil life, and ſtoutly ruled them by the Power of the Sword, as many Commentators on that place obſerve; ſo as if this Impoſtor will make <hi>Nimrod</hi> a Tyrant, he muſt make the will and power of God Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, by which he obtained his Royalty; for as <hi>Aquinas, effectus ſemper con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertitur in ſuum principium;</hi> the effect is alwayes converted into his princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: It is clear therefore, that if we reſpect the foundation of Governement, it is not Election or conſent of the people, as this Impoſtor would have it, but force and Armes which firſt raiſed and eſtabliſhed it; which is alſo confirmed by Judicions <hi>Tholoſanus, primus vi conſtituit imperium; alii par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim ſucceſſione, alii Electione facti ſunt reges:</hi> The firſt by force conſtituted a Kingdom; others were partly by ſucceſſion, and partly by Election made Kings. Election then hath no priviledge in a Commonwealth, which was firſt conſtituted by force; neither in a ſetled Commonwealth hath it any power where ſucceſſion reigneth, which is almoſt univerſal; and where it hath any vigor, it is but little and in part; for many Princes are and have been choſen by ſome part of the people, but by the whole or major part none at all; but moſt have been by the nobility, Gentlemen, and Princes of the blood, as in <hi>Poland, Denmark, Swethland,</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> and not by any collective or repreſentative body of a Nation, whence this Impoſtor may learn, if he ſcorn not inſtruction, that all juſt Power of Government is not founded upon thoſe two baſes of Gods immediate appointment, or the peoples conſent, as he would have it; but <hi>datur tertium,</hi> to wit Warre and Victory, which he might have learned of the ancient Father <hi>Tertullian, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peria
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:94414:10"/>armis quaeri,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoll. Reſp. ad Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo. Jur. F.</hi> 124.</note> 
               <hi>Victoriis propagari;</hi> that Empires are purthaſed by Armes, and pronagated by Victories; or elſe of his new Maſter <hi>Suares, Solent i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum provinciae ſeu populi liberi involuntarie ſubjici regibus per bellum;</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces and free people are unwillingly ſometimes made ſubject by Warre; but this hapneth to be done juſtly or injuſtly; when therefore Warre hath a juſt Title, the people is juſtly deprived of the power they had, and the Victor that prevaileth againſt them, hath true Right and Dominion over them: For <hi>jus eſt in Armis;</hi> there is Right in Armes, and it is the moſt po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Right, which the <hi>Roman Civilian Cicero</hi> was at the laſt forced to confeſſe,
<note place="margin">Ep. ad Atti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</note> 
               <hi>Nullum Jus plus poteſt quam arma; ut enim quiſque potentiſſimus eſt, it a juſtiſſime dicere, &amp; facere omnia videtur;</hi> no Law hath more power then Armes; for as every one is more potent, ſo doth he ſeem to ſay and do all things moſt juſtly. By this it is perſpicuous that there are three baſes of all juſt power of Government, the immediate appointment of God, Warre and Victory, and the Election and conſent of the people. And therefore this Impoſtor ſhall give me leave to inferre his concluſion, that whoſoever doth arrogate to himſelf that power, or any part of it, and cannot produce any of theſe three Titles, is not a Ruler but a Tyrant. And now let this Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtor dare to aſk his <hi>Highneſs, Quis te conſtituit Principem &amp; Judicem ſuper nos?</hi> who made the Prince and Judge over us? and he ſhall be fully anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, to wit, that he was made a Prince and Judge over us by the imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate appointment of God, by the Right of Warre, and by the conſent of the people, which two Titles dimane alſo from the Divine providence, as ſhall be in the ſequel ſhowed; but firſt of the immediate appointment of God.</p>
            <p>The power of all Kings, Princes, and Rulers, immediately proceeds from God, though not by his ſpecial revelation, which was onely incident to ſome of the Kings of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1.</note> yet by particular deſignation, which is common to all, and is a matter of Faith, if we will believe St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who ſaith, There is no power but of God; which he uſeth as a reaſon to perſwade due obedience to the Prince; and that God is the immediate Diſpenſator of that power he proveth by the Authority God hath given to a Prince to revenge and execute wrath upon him that doth evil,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ib.</hi> 2.4.</note> by depriving him of life, if it be requiſite as he ſaith, that he beareth not the Sword in vain, which is onely in the gift and power of God, who is <hi>Dominus vitae &amp; necis,</hi> the Lord of life and death; for no man hath power to take away his own life without the guilt of being a Murderer; and therefore are Princes called by the Prince of Poets <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Gods Son, and Schollers; and by a more Divine Poet,
<note place="margin">Homer.</note> Gods, <hi>Dixi quod dii eſtis;</hi> I have ſaid you are Gods, becauſe they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately have their power from God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Solomon</hi> the Wiſeſt of Kings acknowledged this, By me Kings Raign, and Princes degree Juſtice:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.21.</note> And <hi>Daniel</hi> who was wiſer then all the Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and Magitians, taught <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> this leſſon, Thou O King art King of Kings; for the Lord of Heaven hath given thee a Kingdom, power, ſtrength,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.21. <hi>Apology fetcht out of Allen.</hi>
               </note> and glory; and that he changeth the times and ſeaſons; he remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth Kings, and ſetteth up Kings, which none will deny, but he that ſaith in his heart there is no God, but nature; to which purpoſe ſpeaks ſome of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:94414:10"/>the Papiſts and Jeſuits, and eſpecially <hi>Bellarmine;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bellarm. de conc. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 19.</note> 
               <hi>In regnis hominum pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtas Regis eſt à populo,</hi> &amp;c. In the Kingdom of men the power of the King is from the people; which power is immediately in the multitude as in the Subject; and <hi>Suares</hi> ſecond to none in ſubrility, ſays that God is ſaid to give this power to the Prince, becauſe he hath immediately given it to the people, who transferres it to the Prince; and this ſaith he, is <hi>modus maxime connaturalis, &amp; optimus qui intra latitudinem naturalis rationis cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taripoteſt;</hi> the moſt connatural, and beſt meanes,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reſp. ad Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo. Jur. fidel. F.</hi> 127.</note> which can be thought or found within the Latitude and extent of natural reaſon.</p>
            <p>Which to confirme, he produceth Scripture, that whereas St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, there is no power but of God; he doth not ſay that every Prince is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted of God; for his ſaying is not of any Prince, but of the power; and ſo as he ſaid before, the power being immediately in the people from God, is immediately by them conveyed to the Prince; yet will he not allow the power to be immediately in the people; <hi>Ex peculiari inſtitutione &amp; dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione divina;</hi> from the peculiar inſtitution and Divine gift; <hi>ſed per natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralem conſequutionem ex vi primae creationis;</hi> but by natural conſequence from the force of his firſt creation; in which they ſeem to aſcribe more to natural reaſon and production, then to Divine pateſaction. But St. <hi>Paul</hi> is his own Interpreter; for after his general Doctrine of obedience to the power, he expoundeth it in the ſingular, and applyeth it to the Prince in particular, as he is the Miniſter of God to thee; and then again, that he beareth not the Sword for nought; and leaſt they ſhould forget it he reite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rateth it, for he is a Miniſter of God, &amp;c. But it is objected that though St. <hi>Peter</hi> makes the King Supreame, yet he tells us the King is an humane Ordinance, or creature of the people; for the words are, Submit your ſelves to every Ordinance of man, for the Lords ſake: but it is anſwered,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.11.</note> Kings may be called an humane Ordinance, for being made of one of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and not by the people; and are humane in regard of their material cauſe, though not of their efficient; and if <hi>Peter</hi> had meant that Kings had been made by the people, he muſt alſo have meant that the Governors had been made by the people; for he ſaith, they are ſent by him, not by them, for the puniſhment of evil Doers, ſo as the Governors are ſent by the King, not by the people.</p>
            <p>This needs no application, were it not for this Impoſtors exprobations; for who but ſuch a blind Bayard will queſtion who made his <hi>Highneſs</hi> a Prince and Judge over us, and cannot ſee what wondrous works the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate hand of God hath wrought by him, who as <hi>Moſes</hi> delivered this captive Nation from the bondage and Tyranny they groaned under; and though not ſent by particular nomination as <hi>Moſes</hi> was; yet queſtionleſſe by the immediate deſignation of the Almighty above ordinary providence; for if we obſerve his various and marvelous progreſſions in his military im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, who from a common Commander within a few Summers for his ſtupendious Victories was made Commander in chief; and from that dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity above his own ambition, or humane calculation, <hi>Reſque fide major,</hi> was advanced to the Supreame power of theſe three Nations; how can we but acknowledge that it is the Lords doing; and that it is marvellous
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:94414:11"/>in our eyes, who raiſeth the poor out of the duſt, and lifteth up the needy out of the dunghil,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 113.7.</note> that he may fit with Princes, even the Princes of the people?</p>
            <p>The ſecond way by which the juſt power of Government is gained, is <hi>bello &amp; Victoria;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chyl. rud. Fo.</hi> 16.</note> by Warre and Victory; for as Maſter <hi>Hobbs</hi> ſaith, it is a <hi>Corollarie</hi> in the natural ſtate of man, that a ſure and unreſiſtable power conferres the Right of Dominion and ruling over thoſe who cannot reſiſt, of which before ſufficient hath been ſaid.</p>
            <p>A Title alſo to which his <hi>Highneſs</hi> may juſtly lay claim, for after the Victorious and invincible Army under the Command of Sir <hi>Thomas Fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fax</hi> and his <hi>Highneſs,</hi> had layed the Royal part in the duſt, and trampled it under foot, the Enemy which was vanquiſhed in the Field, had recourſe to ſubtile practiſes to corrupt the Parliament, and City of <hi>London,</hi> upon the ſpecious pretences that there was no Enemy in the Field; and therefore no more need of any Army to continue the heavy and unneceſſary charge upon the people: by ſuch Arguments as this the faction prevailed to vote the diſbanding of the Army, and vaſt Summes of the Commonwealths Treaſure were waſted in raiſing Forces, and entertaining of Reformadoes to beat the Army, and thereby to make way for the readmitting of the then King, to the reexerciſing that power which had produced ſuch bloody and fatal effects, and that without any juſt ſatisfaction given for the ſame to the people, or reaſonable proviſion for thoſe had Faithfully engaged, in the maintenance of them;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See the Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Parliament of England, dated</hi> 24. <hi>of Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</hi> 1649.</note> inſomuch that the Army preſaging what dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous and bloody conſequences might enſue to the reinſlaving of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and to make void and irrite all their former and glorious Victories; and that the Commanders and Officers of the Army might become a prey to the Royal party; and the Enemy whom they had with great difficulty, and much effuſion of blood ſubdued; and that their own honor and ſafety was now in diſpute; they of neceſſity were juſtly inſtigated by the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of nature, and ſelf defence, to oppoſe their bloody, inhumane and ungrateful deſignes, in attempting to ſupplant, and cut off thoſe had been the Patriots and Champions of their Lives, Liberties and Fortunes, and by the power of the Sword, to force them to Victorious conditions; which having obtained by the Right of Warre, the Supreame power divolved on them, becauſe they were in an Hoſtile manner unjuſtly invaded and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced to defend themſelves from imminent deſtruction. And that this was a juſt Warre,
<note place="margin">Cic. pro. Milone.</note> let <hi>Cicero</hi> and <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> be Judges; <hi>Illud eſt non ſolum ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum ſed etiam neceſſarium,</hi> ſaith <hi>Cicero, bellum cum vi vis illata defenditur;</hi> that is not onely juſt, but a neceſſary Warre, when inforcing force is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended by force: And <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> to the ſame effect; <hi>injuriam Paſſos oportet pro ſeipſis Arma capere;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ariſt. ad Alex.</note> it is not onely juſt, but it behooveth thoſe who ſuffer injury, to take up Armes for themſelves, or to defend their Kinſmen, Benefactors, or Aſſociates affected with injuries, as the Commanders and Officers of the Army did; neither is the objection of any force that in Civil Warre, where the people is divided into two parts, that part which conquereth the other, cannot challenge conqueſt over it by Right of Warre, becauſe it is one Nation, and a Nation cannot conquer it ſelf; to which
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:94414:11"/>
               <hi>Grotius</hi> gives this ſatisfactory Anſwer,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Grotius</hi> 16. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 18.</note> that in ſuch a divided State <hi>Gens una pro tempo re, quaſi duae Gentes habentur;</hi> One Nation during the time of thoſe civil diviſions, is accounted and eſteemed as two; And therefore one part may claim Title of Conqueſt over the other: as one Nation may do over another. So <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, with one party of this Nation,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heywards Hen.</hi> 4.</note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered <hi>Richard</hi> the Second and his party: after which conqueſt he was made King of <hi>England,</hi> and did not claim that by the Title of Inheritance; for as <hi>Mortimer</hi> ſaid, he was <hi>Haeres Malus:</hi> but firſt by conqueſt, and then by conſent of the people; which commonly follows the conqueſt, <hi>as Praemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Factorum,</hi> a Reward of his Valour, which all men naturally applaud and honor. And ſo <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh, with one of the party of this Nation conquered <hi>Richard</hi> the Third and his party; neither did he lay claim to the Kingdome by proximity of blood, for there were others nearer then himſelf; but the firſt Title he had was in <hi>Boſworth</hi> field, when after the conqueſt of <hi>Richard</hi> the Third,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bacon, and Bakers Hen.</hi> 7.</note> he was by publick acclamations ſaluted King of <hi>England.</hi> And ſuch Conquerors for right of War may as <hi>Alexander</hi> ſaith in <hi>Curtius, Leges Victis dare,</hi> Give Laws and Conditions to the ſubdued party; and as <hi>Arioviſtus</hi> ſaid to <hi>Coeſar, Imperare iis quemadmodum vellent,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caeſar de Bello Gallico.</note> To rule over them as they pleaſe. And ſo did the Commanders and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of the Army: (of whom his <hi>Highneſs</hi> was the Head-piece,) by right of War rule and order the conquered party as they pleaſed; and cauſed the City to deliver up all their Forts together with the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> and all the Magazines and Arms therein. To disband all their Forces, and turn all the Reformados out of the Line, to withdraw all their Guards from the Houſes; and to receive ſuch Guards within the Line, as the Army ſhould appoint to guard the Houſes; to demoliſh their Works; and to ſuffer the whole Army to march in Triumph through the City, as Conquerors; and by the ſame Right did they purge the Parliament of its infected and corrupted Members, which power from that time they conſtantly retained, and upon occaſions continually exerciſed; and were as Curators to the Parliament and Common wealth, to remedy the diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, and rectifie the diſorders which the ambition of ſome, and lucre of others introduced; And in fine, for important Reaſons above ſpecified, diſſolved that long Parliament; and that poor men under their arbitrary power were driven like flocks of Sheep, by forty in a morning,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hen.</hi> 4. <hi>See his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs Speech,</hi> 12 <hi>Dec.</hi> 1653.</note> to the Confiſcating of their Goods and Eſtates; without any man to give a reaſon, that any of them had forfeited Forty Shillings; and that no door was open to their grievances.</p>
            <p>By whoſe power afterwards a new Aſſembly &amp; Parliament was conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; &amp; becauſe it ſeemed not to be for the good of the Commonwealth, the Maior part of them thought it requiſite to reſigne, and deliver up the ſaid power unto the Lord General <hi>Cromwell,</hi> which they received from him. So as thereby all Power of Government divolved on the Lord General <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> as Head of the Army; and by right of War deſcended to him as Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral: The Supream Power being then vacant to whom all the acts and honor of the Army is to be aſcribed: Becauſe as <hi>Iphicrates,</hi> the General is the head, without which the body cannot act; and as <hi>Curtius, militarem
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:94414:12"/>ſine duce turbam eſſe corpus ſine ſpiritu,</hi> A Military Company with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a General is as a body without a ſpirit, and cannot be ranck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and retained in its right poſtures without it; for as the Comoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>hi ſummus Imperator non adeſt ad exercitum,
<note place="margin">Plaut. Amph.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Citius quod non facto eſt uſus fit, quam quod</l>
                  <l>Facto eſt opus.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And to ſpeak truth without dawbing, he was the Life, ſpirit and head of the Army; And in all his Battails led them on encountring the Enemy in the front.</p>
            <q>Hoſtibus haud tergo, ſed forti pectore notus.</q>
            <p>And as Fortunate as valiant, who by the amplitude of his Victories overcame the envy of his Enemies, for which as <hi>Romulus</hi> by the right of War, upon the requeſt and approbation of the Army, he took upon him the ſupream dignity.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Ipſius certe Ducis hocque referre videtur,
<note place="margin">Juvenal.</note>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t qui fortis erit, fit feliciſſimus idem.</l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>This certes reflecteth on a Generals aim,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That he who valerous is, thrice happy raign.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>And as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſaith <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ariſt. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Polit. cap.</hi> 22.</note> it is juſt that ſuch a Valourous Prince be Lord of all, and King alone.</p>
            <p>And this right and title alſo floweth from the Ocean of the Divine power; for the Lord is a man of War, and he in War overcometh ever; it was he that girded his loins with ſtrength, and made his way perfect; he taught his hands to war, and his fingers to fight; his gentleneſs hath made him great, he hath given him the necks of his Enemies that he might deſtroy him that hates him; he hath delivered him from the ſtrivings of the Enemy, and made him the head of his brethren. And as his Motto and Word in battail was <hi>The LORD of Hoſts:</hi> So hath his Highneſs perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually and piouſly aſcribed and conſecrated all his victories to the LORD of hoſts.</p>
            <p>The third baſis upon which the juſt power of Government is founded, is the election or conſent of the people; and to this title alſo may his High<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſs juſtly lay claim, who to bar up the way againſt thoſe manifold incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences, which have been felt under many other fleeting forms of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, &amp; to reduce us as neer as may be to our antient way of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by ſupream Magiſtrates &amp; Parliaments, did at the requeſt &amp; intreaty of divers perſons of honor &amp; quality, &amp; of many of the chief Officers of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my for the good of the Commonwealth, under the name &amp; title of the Lord Protector, take upon him the ſupream Government, and was by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and in the preſence of the Commiſſioners of the great Seal, the Judges, the Lord Mayor and Aldermen for the City of <hi>London,</hi> the Souldiers, divers Gentlemen Citizens, and many other people and perſons of quality, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in the ſame, with whom being accompanied to <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall,</hi> he did promiſe in the preſence of God, to the beſt of his underſtanding, to govern theſe Nations according to their Laws, Statutes, and Cuſtomes; ſeeking their peace, and cauſing Juſtice and Law to be equally adminiſtred;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:94414:12"/>whereupon the Commiſſioners and Judges received their commiſſions from him, by vertue of which they have ever ſince acted; and as all the Juſtices of Peace did alſo act by his Commiſſions, ſo did all the Sheriffs according to his Commands and Precepts; and all which came in by proceſs, iſſued out by the Sheriffs, conſented to it, and all the Juſtice in this Nation hath been adminiſtred by this autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; beſides, his Highneſs had the approbation of the Army in <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> by Remonſtrances, and under ſignature; the Souldiers at that time being a very conſiderable part of the three Nations; beſides he had the Congratulation of the great City of <hi>London</hi> by way of invite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which was very great, high and publike; and by a numerous body of thoſe who are known by the names of ſeveral Corporations and Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in that City; as alſo the greateſt County in <hi>England,</hi> the County of <hi>York,</hi> with many other Cities and Burroughs, and many other Counties aſſembled in the publique and general Aſſizes, gave him thanks for the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking of that Burden.</p>
            <p>Theſe and many more were the preſentary and explicite Teſtimonies of the peoples general approbations, &amp; congratulations, manifeſted to his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs upon his gratious acceptance of this Government. And which of late hath been more amply &amp; indiciouſly remonſtrated, &amp; declared in Parliament by the Knights, Citizens, &amp; Burgeſſes, &amp; confirmed, ratified, and eſtabliſhed by an Act, that upon publication of the premiſſes, all and every perſon and perſons of what quality ſoever are ſtrictly charged, and commanded to take notice of the ſame, and to conform and ſubmit themſelves to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment eſtabliſhed; which Proclamation, being publiſhed at the magnificent and glorious inauguration of his Highneſs in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall,</hi> with great ſolemnity in the preſence of the Lord Embaſſador extraordinary of <hi>France,</hi> and the States General of the United Provinces, and divers other noble and honorable perſonages, the people made great ſeveral acclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions with loude ſhouts: <hi>God ſave the Lord Protector;</hi> and the like congra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulations and acclamations, with the expreſſions of their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>tions, wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Highneſs long life, were made by the people <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> City of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> and ſo did all the Cities of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> upon the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Publication of the ſaid Proclamation. With what brazen brow can the Impoſtor now deny but any that his Highneſs may alſo lay claim to this Title? if this be not a viſible, publike, and general approbation, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the people, then was never publiſht any in <hi>Poland, Scotland, Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark,</hi> or any other Dominion or Territory of the Univerſe; and if there be any refractory, or repugnant to the ſame, they are ſuch as this Impoſtor and his Accomplices, malignant men of Belial.</p>
            <p>And this alſo is the Lords doings, who prepared the hearts of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and touched them to appear and follow their Prince and Protector, as he did the Band of men that went with <hi>Saul,</hi> after the Lord had choſen him: ſo as his Highneſs Councel, <hi>or Parliament as he vainly vaunts, nor any one elſe ſhall not be much troubled to anſwer his Interrogations and Queſtions,</hi> which appear ſo frivolous and nugatory.</p>
            <p>But here this Impoſtors malice ceaſeth not; for though he confidently
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:94414:13"/>concludeth his Highneſs to be a Tyrant <hi>in titulo,</hi> as he falſely ſuppoſeth; yet will <hi>he have him alſo a Tyrant in exercitio, and as compleat a Tyrant as ever had been ſince the firſt Societies of men;</hi> for ſo he brazeth it but as he faileth in the firſt, ſo doth he falter in the latter; and doth but labour and blot paper in vain, though he daubs it on with artificial cunning to make the deluſion the ſtronger; for thus he cunningly argues: Is it <hi>not Tyranny to change the Government without the peoples conſent, to diſſolve their repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative by force; and to diſannul their</hi> Acts, <hi>to give the names of the peoples Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praeſentative to confederates of his own; to eſtabliſh iniquity by Law; to take away mens Lives out of all courſe of Law, by certain Murderers of his own, whom he names an High Court of Juſtice, to decimate mens Eſtates; and by his own power to impoſe upon the people what taxes he pleaſeth; and to maintain all this by force of Arms?</hi> Which criminations, as they are by him expreſſed, are malicious and contumelious; for he did not diſſolve their Repreſentatives by force, or diſannul their Acts, but upon neceſſary grounds, and urgent occaſions; neither did he give the name of the peoples Repreſentative to confederates of his own, to eſtabliſh iniquity by a Law; but he purged the Parliament of its unfound and putrified members, and ſetled in it ſincere and ſound perſons who might act nothing but what was agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to Law, and equity, as is in the premiſſes expreſly proved; neither did he take away Mens Lives by certain Murderers of his own, but did make Commiſſioners, &amp; erect an High Court of Juſtice, to take away the Lives of ſuch Rebellious &amp; murdering perſons as this Impoſtor &amp; his Accomplices are, who would have taken away the life of their Prince and Protector, which he juſtly might do; neither did he decimate Mens Eſtates, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe upon the people what taxes he pleaſed by his own power: but he by the power was given him by the Army, with the conſent of many hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable people aſwell as others, at his inſtallation at <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall,</hi> and in other places, by whom he was created Lord Protector; did by advice of his Councel for the maintenance of the Army and Navy, and defraying of other neceſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> charges which concerned the honor and ſafety of the Commonw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ecimate mens Eſtates; &amp; impoſe upon the people neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary taxes. All which as he truly ſaith, he maintained by force of Arms out of all courſe of Law, as by right of War and his ſecond Title he might, as hath been fully debated,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ploy. f.</hi> 19. <hi>Tholoſan. Syn. l. c.</hi> 18. <hi>and</hi> 28.</note> and decided. Beſides, though upon acceptance of this Government, with the conſent and approbation of the people, his Highneſs hath promiſed to govern theſe Nations, according to the Laws, Statutes and Cuſtomes; yet is it a Rule in the Divine, Civil, Canon, and the Common Laws, that neceſſity hath no Law, and that <hi>Neceſſitas facit licitum quod alioquin fuerit illicitum;</hi> and that neceſſity maketh that lawful, which otherwiſe ſhould not be lawful; and Princes ſtrained with imminent and urgent neceſſity for the dignity and ſafety of the Commonwealth, no eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed Law providing for a preſent remedy, may juſtly do thoſe Acts which otherwiſe by the courſe of Law were unlawful, as to decimate Mens Eſtates, and by his power with the advice of his Councel to impoſe ſuch Taxes as are convenient and neceſſary.</p>
            <p>And as the learned Legiſt.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Davis Rep. fol.</hi> 12.</note> Sir <hi>John Davis</hi> ſaith, The King by his Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:94414:13"/>Royal to ſupport the neceſſary charges of the Crown, may decree Impoſts and Impoſitions payable upon Marchandizes; and ſo have Princes heretofore by their Prerogatives to encounter ſuddain dangers and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs, which would not endure ſo much delay as the aſſembling of the great Councel of the Commonwealth, uſed their Edicts and Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which Mr. <hi>Pym</hi> a grave and prudent Senator of this State ſtileth the moſt eminent power of a Prince, and the moſt glorious beams of Majeſty,
<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Pym his Speech in Parl.</hi> 1642. <hi>fo.</hi> 31.</note> in commanding Obedience and Subjection, which he calleth <hi>Leges Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum;</hi> and onely diſallowes them for the abuſes in being exerciſed for the maintaining &amp; enjoying of ſundry monopolies, and other graunts, exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing burthenſome and prejudicial to the people. And therefore, how can this Impoſtor anſwer his Highneſs Queſtion in this point, Whether the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhould prefer the having of their wills, though it be their deſtruction, rather then to comply with things of neceſſity? which as he truly Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, he ſhould wrong his Native Countrey to ſuppoſe: unleſs he will ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the neceſſity to be faigned, &amp; imaginary,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs Speech</hi> 22 <hi>Jan.</hi> 1654. <hi>See his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs Speech the</hi> 12 <hi>of Sept.</hi> 1654.</note> which his Highneſs acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth to be the greateſt couſenage, that men can put upon the Providence of God, and which his Princely and Paternal care abhorreth. Beſides, his Highneſs acted nothing in this Kind, but by the advice of his Councel, who are the Truſtees of the Commonwealth in all Intervals of Parliament, and hath an abſolute negative upon the Supream Power in the ſaid Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals, as the Parliament hath in the ſitting; ſo as it is not his own, but a mixt Act by the advice of his Councel, who in all probability would not adviſe him to any thing but what is neceſſary and expedient; and if they ſhould, the offence would lie at their door. And thus are the preterit Ordinances of his Highneſs fully cleared from the unjuſt aſperſion of this Impoſtor in giving him the title <hi>of the Violation of Laws, and Exerciſe of Tyranny and Robberies.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See the humble Pet. and advice of the Parl.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>the</hi> 17 of <hi>Sept.</hi> 1646.</note> And for the future to prevent all enſing miſtakes and ſuſpitions of the neceſſity of impoſing Taxes on the people, upon provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion made for the ſupport of the Government and Safety of theſe Nations; It is declared and enacted, that no charge be layed, nor no perſon be compelled to contribute to any gift or loan, benevolence, tax, tallage, ayde, or other like charge, without common conſent by Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>But to proceed in the canvaſing of this Impoſtors Calumniations; and whereas he ſaith, <hi>That notwithſtanding his Highneſs hath done all theſe things, yet for his preſervation the people muſt pray,</hi> as if it were impiety in the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to pray for him. Our Saviour Chriſt was of another mind,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.45.</note> whoſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel is, to pray for them who deſpitefully uſe or perſecute you; And ſo was his ſelected Apoſtles, who exhorteth that firſt of all prayers, ſupplications, interceſſions and giving of thanks be made for all men, for the King, and thoſe that be in Authority. And who had rule over them at that time, but <hi>Nero?</hi> a reputed Tyrant;
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1. <hi>Swarez reſponſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad Apolog. p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Jur. fidel.</hi>
               </note> and for perſecuting Chriſtians ſuppoſed to be An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt; wherein by the fruits we may perceive of what ſpirit this Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor is; for he hath not the fruits of the Spirit of our Saviour Chriſt, the Prince of Peace; to wit Love, Joy, Peace, &amp;c. but he hath the fruits of the ſpirit of his father the Devil, to wit, envy, curſing, lying, and all manner of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:94414:14"/>reviling; So if his father, the Prince of darkneſs ſhould be depoſed, by right of inheritance, the ſucceſſion may properly deſcend to him as the Devil Incarnate; who is the worſer, and moſt dangerous Devil.</p>
            <p>And now in every reſpect are the reaſons of this Impoſtor, by which he fortifieth his firſt Queſtion, utterly quaſhed, notwithſtanding his vain-glorious triumphing before Victory, that <hi>it is a Queſtion no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But before he comes to the <hi>Second Queſtion, ſeeing things are more</hi> eaſily perceived <hi>by the Deſcription of Exteriour Accidents and Qualities;</hi> he thought it <hi>not amiſs</hi> to ſee <hi>whether his Highneſs hath the outward marks and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters by which a</hi> Tyrant is <hi>known, aſwel as he hath their</hi> nature and eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial properties, which, as he ſaith do ſo <hi>naturally</hi> correſpond <hi>to his</hi> Highneſs <hi>that it cannot be</hi> doubted, <hi>whether his</hi> Highneſs be the <hi>Original or the Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, or whether he hath in drawing the</hi> Tyrant <hi>repreſented him, or in repreſenting him expreſſed a</hi> Tyrant. But here alſo will his fair and glorious pretences prove but ſhadows and ſick mens dreams; for as it hath been exactly proved, that the nature, and eſſential properties of a Tyrant are not to be found in his <hi>Highneſs,</hi> no more cannot the exterior accidents and quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties be inherent in him; for if the nature and eſſential properties be not in him, the external accidents and qualities alſo cannot; for as <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ariſt. Categ. c.</hi> 2</note> 
               <hi>Accidens non poteſt eſſe ſine eo in quo eſt;</hi> and therefore cannot the Characters be aptly and properly applied to his <hi>Highneſs,</hi> though they be not of his own <hi>ſtamping, as he ſaith: but ſuch as be found in</hi> Plato, Ariſtotle, Tacitus, <hi>and his</hi> Highneſs <hi>own Evangeliſt Machiavel;</hi> who indeed is his one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Evangeliſt: for he ſeemeth better verſed in him then in the Goſpel; having cited more Texts and Paſſages out of him, then out of that, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as his <hi>Highneſs</hi> in his Writings never mentioneth him, nor ever had him in his mouth; as this Impoſtor every where hath who ſuppoſeth his Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxes authentique, whereas neither his Highneſs, nor any Pious Prince will adhere to his authority, and therefore in vain cited by him.</p>
            <p>Howſoever, if we examine his Characters, Marks, and Scutchion of a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, which he would faſten on his <hi>Highneſs</hi> ſleeve, we ſhall find them ſleeveleſs, and altogether impertinent.</p>
            <p>The firſt Charrcter is, That all Tyrants have been firſt Captains and Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals of the people, for which he quoteth <hi>Ariſtotle;</hi> but his words are, all Tyrants have been made <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, of Leaders of the people, and ſo have all Kings &amp; Princes; for without a party of the people, how can an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my be raiſed? and without Armies how can there be Leaders? So <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bactes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ariſt. Pol. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 10.</note> and <hi>Cyrus</hi> Leaders of the People were made Kings, the one of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> and the other of <hi>Medea data libertate,</hi> for giving and gainings the <hi>Peoples Liberty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo was his <hi>Highneſs</hi> alſo made <hi>Protector</hi> of theſe Nations,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble advice of Parl.</hi> 1656.</note> for deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering us from Bondage and Tyranny, and reſtoring us to Peace and Tranquillity, as is declared by our Repreſentative in the laſt Act. But to conſtrue it according to his own mind and meaning, which is incongru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly pacht out of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> and <hi>Tacitus,</hi> That <hi>his Highneſs</hi> being made a <hi>Leader for the people,</hi> under pretences of vindicating and defending <hi>their
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:94414:14"/>Liberties did</hi> ſubvert <hi>the preſent Governement,</hi> which <hi>being done, he invaded that Liberty himſelf.</hi> And ſo indeed his <hi>Highneſs</hi> was made a Leader for the people, and did vindicate and defend their Liberties; and vanquiſhed their Tyrannical Enemy: but when ſome of the Corrupters of the people (contrary to the Law of Nature and Reaſon) in an hoſtile manner would have compelled their Leaders by force of Arms to have ſubjected them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the power of the Tyrant, whom they before had conquered, then according the Law of Nature were they inforced to repel ſuch ingrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and deſtructive inuries &amp; <hi>aperto Marte,</hi> to force them to ſubmiſſion and ſubjection, whence by the Law of War their Command, Rule and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment was transferred on them which they afterwards always exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed over them, as hath been before argued and determined; yet did not their Leaders leave them, but perſevered to maintain and defend their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties againſt the ſaid Tyrants abetters, and never ceaſed till they had wholly and perfectly routed and ſubdued them, for which not onely by the Law of War, but by the Conſent of People, and Act of Parliament, the Supream Power was placed and ſetled on his <hi>Highneſs,</hi> by whom we enjoy our Liberty more fully then before we did in our new modelled Democracy; for as <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> Tyranny is a confuſed and mixt of Timocracy and Democracy, of the principalities of a few, and the power of the people,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ariſt. Pol. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 10.</note> and hath the vices of them both; for the vicious end of the one, as his accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Expoſitor <hi>Camerarius</hi> obſerveth, is to be an Enemy to the noble and rich men, and them either to deſtroy or exile, of which we have had ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible experience, and the vicious end of the other is through diffidence to afflict the people, to baniſh ſome, and diſſipate others into ſeveral places, which alſo hath been formerly practiſed among us: but by Monarchs and the Government of one theſe Vices are rejected, and remedied. For as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſaith, by it the nobles and rich are defended from the injury of the multitude, and the people are protected from the oppreſſions of the Nobles and Rich: So as there is no greater Liberty then in Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, by which the Tyrannical vices are expunged and expelled; and the Nobleſs are according to their virtues worthily preferred and defended, and the People according to their deſerts advanced. And this is his <hi>Highneſs</hi> caſes far different from that of <hi>Panoetius, Pyſiſtratus</hi> and <hi>Dionyſius,</hi> whom <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> produceth as examples of Tyranny. And now I am of the Impoſtors mind, this needs <hi>no further application.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond Character is, That Tyrants <hi>accompliſh their ends much</hi> more by fraud <hi>then force; neither virtue nor force are ſo neceſſary</hi> to that purpoſe, as <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>na aſtutia fortunata, A lucky craft which without force hath</hi> been <hi>found ſufficient, but never force without that:</hi> wherein he miſtaketh his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>Machiavel,</hi> as if in that place he ſhould denote a crafty Tyrant; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as he intimateth a prudent Prince, as if his Prince were all one with a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant. For though all his Precepts collectively taken are not authentick, or allowable, yet ſome parts of his policy are neceſſary and uſeful, for the gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and preſerving a Princes State; as Guards, Garriſons, Fortreſſes, Vigilan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of Councellors, diligence of Spyes, and Intelligencers;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Arcanis Imperii, f.</hi> 207.</note> for which reaſon acute <hi>Clapmare</hi> in diſpraiſing commendeth him <hi>pro politico magni acuminis
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:94414:15"/>ſed minus ſanae &amp; piae mentis,</hi> for a Politian of great wit, though not of a ſound and pious mind; and if we read him with a Chymical Judgement, and refine him by Religious Policy, we ſhal find many conditions in him worthy our obſervation and practice, whereof this is one, that Virtue and Fortune availe not ſo much in obtaining a principality as a lucky craft; for as the <hi>Civilians</hi> diſtinguiſh, there is <hi>dolus bonus,</hi> a good craft; if it be as <hi>Plautus</hi> ſaith, <hi>ſine omni malitia,</hi> without any malice; and is called <hi>ſolertia,</hi> a cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning craft; which is not diſallowable, but laudable, eſpecially in a General or Prince, as it was in <hi>Hanibal;</hi> in which the nature of the Lion and Fox did concurre;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Juſt. l.</hi> 1.</note> and in <hi>Darius Hidaſpes,</hi> who by the cunning craft to make his Horſe neigh, gained the Kingdom of <hi>Perſia;</hi> and in <hi>Servius Tullus,</hi> the Son of a Captive, who being ſubſtituted in the place of a King, by <hi>Tanaquil</hi> his Queen,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>For l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 6.</note> 
               <hi>Regnum dolo partum ſic egit induſtria ut Jure adeptus videatur,</hi> did ſo Rule the Kingdom gotten by craft, that he ſeemed to have gained it by Right, and obtained that by craft they could not have gotten by force; for as <hi>Tacitus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tacit. Ann.</hi> 2. <hi>Mach diſcourſ. l.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>plura conſilio quam vi geruntur;</hi> and as <hi>Machiavel,</hi> fraude without force hath been ſufficient, but never force without that; and though he ſaith that it is praiſe-worthy in a Prince to deal plainly, truely, and really; yet is there Serpentine prudence to be uſed in his Dovelike plainneſſe, and ought to be participate of the fraude of the Fox as well as the force of the Lion; and as this Impoſtor Phraſeth it, to have <hi>the Tail of the Fox as well as the Skin of the Lion;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mach. Princ.</hi> 18.</note> 
               <hi>thereby</hi> as he ſaith, <hi>aggregare I cerve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li de gli huomini con aſtutia, to wind himſelf into the braines of men with craft, and by plauſible pretences to feel the pulſe of their affections, or to diſcover their ſiniſter intentions, that in the end he may Maſter thoſe had ſo little wit as not to rely on his Faith and integrity;</hi> of whom I believe this Impoſtor to be one by his little wit in that point; neither is ſuch diſſimulation unlawful, as a Pious Politician averreth, but Lawful and commendable, yea, and ſometimes neceſſary;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Artyl. Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Policy. c.</hi> 31.</note> eſpecially in Princes, who ought to cover their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions with more care and circumſpection then other men, ſo as it may well and truely be ſaid, <hi>qui neſcit diſſimulare, neſcit regnare;</hi> he that knoweth not how to diſſemble, that is to ſay, diſcreetly to Cloak and cover his Intentions, when occaſion requireth, knoweth not how to Raign; ſo Pious <hi>Aeneas</hi> concealed and diſſembled his departure from <hi>Dido,</hi> for which ſhe Taxed him in the ſame Termes,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Virg. Aeni.</hi> 4.</note>
               <q>
                  <l>Diſſimulare etiam ſperaſti perfide tantum</l>
                  <l>Poſſe nefas, tacituſque mea diſcedere terra:</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But wherefore doth this Impoſtor flowre his <hi>Highneſs</hi> for his fluency in teares? <hi>Eliſha</hi> wept fot the evils would ſall on the <hi>Iſraelites;</hi> and our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour bitterly, to foreſee the deſtruction of <hi>Hieruſalem;</hi> and why ſhould not his <hi>Highneſs</hi> weep to ſee the evils did afflicts his Countrey? who by his prayers and teares did prevail more with God, and worke more in the hearts of the people of great prudence &amp; piety, though this Impoſtor ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully defileth his own neſt, <hi>(in ſtiling them a people of great Faith, and little wit)</hi> more then his courage and the reſt of his moral virtues with the help of his Commilitons, which he ſcoffingly calls his Janiſaries; leaving the <hi>eloquence in execratious and contumelious opprobries</hi> to himſelf, who wil never leave them till the halter hath him.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:94414:15"/>
            <p>The third Character is that <hi>they abuſe all excellent perſons, and ridde out of the way all thoſe have noble mindes; &amp; terrae Filios extollunt, advance Sons of the Earth, which he thus applies,</hi> that his <hi>Highneſs purged both Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament and Army, till he left few or none there that had either honor or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, either wit, intereſt or courage to oppoſe his deſignes,</hi> which before hath been effectually anſwered, to which he referreth the Reader; neither were there any excellent perſons abuſed, or rid out of the way; but ſuch as this Impoſtor is, who were diſturbers of the quiet and peace of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, as they juſtly deſerved; neither were there any advanced but for their Valour and Virtue, which is <hi>Vera nobilitas;</hi> for we are all <hi>terrae Filii;</hi> and it is not birth, but worth puts the difference between us.</p>
            <p>The fourth Character is, they dare not ſuffer aſſemblies, not ſo much as <hi>Horſeraces;</hi> but to uſe <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> words, they ſtrictly forbid Feaſts and Companies, and take away Schooles of Learning; all which his <hi>Highneſs</hi> approves, and hath honoured the Schooles of Learning as their Head and Chancelour; but Horſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> were prohibited three years ago, when miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous plots were for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> acting in the State, and that but for a time to prevent new troubles might be raiſed in ſuch a great concourſe of people by ill diſpoſed perſons.</p>
            <p>The fifth Character is, that in all places they have their ſpies and dilators,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apol. Pol. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 11.</note> which though he borroweth of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> yet may we without reprehenſion decede from our Maſter in this, becauſe experience, which was his Maſter, and that practice of Princes teacheth us, that Spies and Intelligences are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Members of a State; and as <hi>Bodin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bodin. de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pub. l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 11.</note> 
               <hi>Neceſſariae ſunt quidem magnis principibus largitiones ad hoſtium conſilia, copias &amp; opes evertendas, nec potest ullum magnum Imperium ſpeculatoribus carere;</hi> Stipends are neceſſary to a great Princes, neither can any great Empire want Intelligencers to fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate and overthrow the Counſels, Forces, and Eſtates of the Enemies: But how impertinently and impudently doth he apply this? beſides <hi>many innumerable ſpies,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>they have their Fleetwoods, Braghals, and St.</hi> Johns <hi>to ſeem diſcontented, and not to ſide with them, that under that deſign they may yet truſt, and make diſcoveries.</hi> The poiſon of <hi>Aſpes</hi> is under his lips, and his venemous tongue ſpares none comes within his reach.</p>
            <q>Quaelibet in quemvis opprobria figere ſaevus.
<note place="margin">Horac.</note>
            </q>
            <p>But how ſhould this Impoſtor know theſe things, unleſſe he hath more Spies then his <hi>Highneſs,</hi> which ſurely he hath, ſuch as frequent Tavernes, Alehouſes, and Barbers Shops, who ſtamp news by the Print of their own phanſies, and will ſeem to know thoſe things which never were done, or never will be, of whom the <hi>Comaedian</hi> wittily,
<q>
                  <l>Qui res alienas curant opere maximo,
<note place="margin">Plaut. truo.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Qui omnia ſimulant ſcire, nec quicquid ſciunt,</l>
                  <l>Quae neque futura, neque ſunt facta ſciunt.</l>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <l>Who into others Acts do dive with curious eyes,</l>
                  <l>And all things do pretend to ſee, yet nothing Spies,</l>
                  <l>And ſeem to know what never was, or will be done.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But why ſhould theſe honourable perſons weigh his Fables, which are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove Poetical fiction, and which none will believe but Fools and Mad men,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:94414:16"/>his onely Paraſites and Patrons? his <hi>Highneſs alſo,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>hath his Emiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries to ſend with forged Letters;</hi> if any one doubt this, let him ſend to Major General <hi>Brown,</hi> who will ſatisfy him; and what ſaith Maſter <hi>Brown?</hi> he cannot juſtify any Letters to be forged; onely he ſuſpecteth that one who brought him Letters from <hi>Charles Steward,</hi> received not condign punniſhment: But though his <hi>Highneſs</hi> is clear of this calumnie; yet hath that been Judged <hi>arcanum imperii,</hi> a ſecret of Government in Princes and Generals,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plutarch. vita Eumenis.</hi> A <hi>Gell. l.</hi> 15. <hi>c.</hi> 22.</note> to forge Letters, thereby to fiſh out the affections of thoſe they doubted to be diſaffected, or for other Politick ends, as <hi>Eumenes</hi> and <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torius</hi> did, which in ſuch caſes is not unlawful, according to the practice of the Emperor <hi>Frederick</hi> the firſt, and <hi>Lewis</hi> the eleventh King of <hi>France,</hi> whoſe proverb was, <hi>qui neſcit diſſimulare, neſcit imperare;</hi> and which leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the ſaid <hi>Lewis</hi> would onely have his Son to learn, as before hath been intimated.</p>
            <p>The ſixt Article is, <hi>They ſtir not without their Guarde, nor his Highneſs without his Life-Guarde,</hi> as if it were Tyranny in a King or Prince to have a Guarde; which is not onely uſeful, but neceſſary to defend himſelf from the ambitious and ſeditious; without which no Majeſty is ſafe, or ſecure; for as <hi>Pontanus, amor incedit inermis, Armatus dormit;</hi> love walkes unarm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ariſt. l.</hi> 3. <hi>Pol. c.</hi> 11.</note> but the Armed man may ſleep: and truely <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> being a witneſſe, the uſe of ſuch Guardes is neceſſary as well in a quiet and peaceable Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth as in a turbulent and ſeditious; for how, ſaith he, can a King exerciſe his power, unleſſe he hath about him Force and Armed men, to reſiſt thoſe oppoſe it? But he ſaith, his <hi>Highneſs</hi> hath a Life-guarde, and ſo had <hi>Romulus</hi> three hundred Horſe-men, <hi>tam pace quam bello;</hi> as well in peace as Warre for his Royal body. And for the ſame cauſe <hi>Antoninus</hi> had <hi>German</hi> Horſe-men;
<note place="margin">Liv.</note> but this Impoſtor would fain have him to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>card his Life-guarde, that his Bravos may the ſooner ſlay him.</p>
            <p>The ſeventh Character is, <hi>They impoveriſh the people that they may want the power, if they had the will to attempt any thing againſt him. His</hi> Highneſs <hi>way,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>is by Taxes, Exciſe and Decimations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let us remember what the Impoſtor ſaid to his Reader, that he ſhould not want Proofs, if he wants not memory, whereas herein his own memory faileth him; for he might have called to memory that the like Taxes. Exciſe, and Decimations were impoſed by the Parliament; for which in all his paſſages he pleadeth whileſt that poſſeſſed the ſole Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; <hi>&amp; ubi eſt eadem ratio, ibi eſt eadem lex;</hi> and where there is the ſame reaſon, there is the ſame Law; and if ſuch Taxes were Lawful then, and did not impoveriſh the people, how can they for that reaſon be unlawful now? But if his <hi>Highneſs</hi> ſhould have impoſed ſuch intolerable Taxes on the people,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ariſt. Pol. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 11.</note> as <hi>Dionyſius</hi> did on the <hi>Syracuſans,</hi> having by them within five years ſpace exhauſted the wealth of <hi>Syracuſe,</hi> for which <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle</hi> in the ſame place, from which he extracteth this Character, branded him with Tyranny; or if he ſhould have laid ſuch Impoſts on them, as the Duke of <hi>Alva</hi> did on the <hi>Netherlanders;</hi> who, as <hi>Bodin</hi> ſaith, exacted the tenth part of their Vendible goods; by which device within a ſhort time he almoſt ſwallowed up all the Merchants Eſtates (they uſing to tell the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:94414:16"/>ſame ten times over) then might he have had juſt cauſe to charge his <hi>Highneſs</hi> with the impoveriſhment of the people; but ſince he hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes impoſed moderate and neceſſary Taxes, according to the publicke occurrences and occaſions, and now onely ſuch as are ratified and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by the laſt Parliament, this Impoſtor may put up his Pipes, and ſet down by weeping Croſſe.</p>
            <p>The eighth Character is, <hi>that they make Warre to divert and buiſy the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; and beſides to have a pretence to raiſe money, and to make new Levies if they miſtruſt their own Forces, or think them not ſufficient:</hi> But the words of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> are, they make Warre leaſt the people ſhould be idle,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ariſt. Pol.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 11.</note> and that they may have need of a General; and varyeth nor a little from his alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Authority, to intrude his own Inventions; but herein alſo muſt we ſhake hands with our Maſter, being taught by experience, that as <hi>Bodin, ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil eſt utilius quam externis bellis implicari;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bodin. de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pub. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> there is nothing more profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble then to make Warre with Forrainers.</p>
            <p>And firſt to invert <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> reaſon, that idleneſs in people may be taken away; for idleneſs is the Mother of all vices, and begetteth vicious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in a Commonwealth, which unleſs they be expunged, the body will be vitiated and corrupted. Therefore it is neceſſary to make Warre; whereby ſuch nefarious and facinerous perſons may be exonerated,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tholoſan. Synt. l.</hi> 41. <hi>&amp;</hi> 22.</note> and thoſe which remain imbettered; and more glorious for them Valiantly to hazzard their Lives for the honor of their Countrey abroad, then ignomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſly to endanger themſelves by looſe living at home. An other reaſon is drawn from <hi>Annibal,</hi> that ancient circumſpect and couragious Captain, that Warre is to be made with Forrainers, to prevent inteſtine ſeditions, which was his State Aphoriſme; <hi>Nulla magna civitas diu conſiſtere poteſt;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Livii.</note> 
               <hi>ſi foris hoſtem non habet domi invenit:</hi> No great City can long continue; if it have not an Enemy abroad, it will find one at home, as prevalid bodies are ſecure from external hurts, yet are they burdned and laden with their own ſtrength, which was the principal cauſe that <hi>Scipio Africanus</hi> the younger would not deſtroy <hi>Carthage,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bodin. de rep. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 10.</note> leaſt if there were no Warre againſt the Enemy, it would begin at home; and therefore to avoid ſome Warre at home, or ſome eminent and ſuppoſed Warre abroad, a Prince may well ſupport a juſt quarrel in any ſuch Countrey by way of prevention; ſo as it is no Tyranny, but preventing Policy, to make Warre with an ambitious Enemy; <hi>Non cuivis homini contingit;</hi> and this Impoſtor is uncapable of this imperial myſtery.</p>
            <p>But mark his malitious inference, <hi>The Warre with Spain ſerves his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to this purpoſe, and upon no other Juſtice was it begun at firſt, or is ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued;</hi> what Pander can be more impudent, as it may be he is to the Whore of <hi>Babylon,</hi> who ſavors much of her Conclave, to deny the juſtneſs of the undertaking that Warre, which is ſo plainly and evidently demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Declaration of his <hi>Highneſs,</hi> in the year 1655. that the prudent and Proteſtant Princes of Chriſtendom embrace and believe it; and ſo do all others who are not ſimply ignorant, or wilfully blinded: but let us hear the Advice of Maſter <hi>Pymm,</hi> that provident Member of this State to the late King <hi>Charles</hi> in Parliament, and the reaſons by which he would have mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:94414:17"/>him to the ſame Warre: The <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Colonies, ſaith he, in the <hi>Indies</hi> were weak, diſtracted, and diſcontented; and that there were ſixty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Perſons of this Nation in thoſe parts, whoſe bodies were ſeaſoned to that Climate, which at a very ſmall charge might be ſet down in ſome ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious part of thoſe pleaſant Rich and Fruitful Countreys, and eaſily make him Maſter of all that Treaſury,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Maſter Pymms Speech</hi> 1642.</note> which not onely foments the Warre, but is the ſupport of Popery in all parts of Chriſtendom: what will this Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtor now ſay? He cannot ſay it was his <hi>Highneſs</hi> Plot, but Maſtes <hi>Pymms,</hi> againſt whom, if he open his Jawes, they will inſtantly be Metamorphoſed into the Jawe bones of an Aſſe, by Vote of Parliament; and whereas he makes this Warre his <hi>Highneſs</hi> pretence to raiſe monies to repleniſh his va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant cohorts: What did Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> the <hi>Semiramis</hi> and <hi>Sheba</hi> of this Nation? She was the <hi>Spaniards</hi> Potent Antagoniſt, and never encountred him but ſhe Conquered him; for which ſhe received this boon and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nevolence for her Victorious attempts againſt him; as Maſter <hi>Pymm</hi> affirmeth, that the greateſt part of that charge was made upon the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects Purſes,
<note place="margin">Vid. Pym. ibid.</note> and not upon the Queens; though the honor and profit of the ſame did moſt accrue to her; this certainly will cloſe this Impoſtors lips from bawling againſt the Taxes, and that Sacred and hopeful Warre.</p>
            <p>The ninth Character is, <hi>They will ſeem to favour and provide for good men:</hi> But herein this Impoſtor miſtakes <hi>Ariſtotle;</hi> for he doth not propound this as a Character of a Tyrant, but of a King, to wit, to favour and preferre good men; and ſheweth that by this meanes a Tyrant may lengthen his power, if he ſquare his Rule by the patterne and ſimilitude of the Royal power.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ariſt. Pol.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 11.</note> And makes as abſurd an Application: That is, ſaith he, <hi>If the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters will be Orthodox and flatter; if they will wreſt and torture the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, to prove the Government Lawful, he then likewiſe will be content to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand Scripture in their favour, and furniſh them with Tithes:</hi> For his <hi>Highneſs</hi> before the acceptance of this Princely dignity, when the fifth Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy men in Parliament would have deprived the Clergy of their bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices and Tithes, his <hi>Highneſs</hi> preſerved and confirmed them, according to the Laws of the Land; neither need the Miniſters wreſt and torture the Scriptures to prove his Government; for they are generally plain in that point, as before hath been demonſtrated.</p>
            <p>The tenth Character is, <hi>That things which are odious and diſtaſtful, they make others Executioners of, and when the people are diſcontented, they appeaſe them with Sacrificing thoſe Miniſters they employ, and do grateful things themſelves;</hi> and ſimply inferreth that he will leave it to his <hi>Highneſs</hi> Major Generals to ruminate a little on that point; for Princes make others Surrogates, and Executioners of their Judicial Acts; becauſe as <hi>Jethro</hi> ſaid to <hi>Moſes,</hi> they are too heavy for them, and not able to performe them themſelves alone; not that they be diſtaſtful,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.</note> but expedient it ſo ſhould be; yet whatſoever they do, or Act, is in the Princes name, and by their Authority; and in this reſpect is his own Acts: So did his <hi>Highneſs</hi> by the advice of his Councel imploy the Major Generals upon urgent and neceſſary occaſions, to prevent ſeditions, preſerve Peace in the Commonwealth, which are particularly expreſſed in his <hi>Highneſs</hi> Declaration, Dated <hi>October</hi> 1655. which in that regard was his
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:94414:17"/>
               <hi>Highneſs</hi> own Act; and though it did prove diſtaſtful to the people, yet was it not therefore unjuſt and inconvenient; for <hi>Moſes</hi> a moſt juſt Prince did enjoin, and prohibit almoſt all things contrary to the mind, and will of the people; neither were the Major Generals that Action Sacrificed to the cenſure of the Parliament, nor thereby incurred any penalty, though the Parliament was not pleaſed for ſome weighty reaſons, to confirme their Authority in the ſame mode they deſired, yet ſtand they in the ſame fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour with his <hi>Highneſs,</hi> and without any diſparagement in the Parliament; and whereas the deaf <hi>Adder</hi> ſaith, he never heard of any good his <hi>Highneſs</hi> hath done himſelf, it ſeemeth he never frequenteth our Churches; who up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Thanks-giving days from the Pulpit might have heard Commemorations of his marvellous Victories; and every day might have heard from the Parliament the thankfulneſſe they have acknowledged to God, for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving his <hi>Highneſs</hi> in many Battailes, and to make him an Inſtrument for reſtoring and preſerving our peace; and if he had not loſt all his Sences,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See the Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Advice,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>holden at Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</hi> 1656.</note> he could not but ſee, hear, taſte, ſmell, and feel, the many gracious bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings which God hath conferred on us ſince his <hi>Highneſs</hi> acceptance of the Empire: For what greater bleſſings can accrue to a Commonwealth then peace and plenty? which through Gods bleſſings we enjoy quietly and abundantly: that we may ſay with the Poet,
<q>
                  <l>— Non eſt quod copia Major</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Jove</hi> donari poſſit.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Hor. l.</hi> 2. <hi>Ser.</hi> 2.</note>
                  </l>
               </q> Or as it is ſaid of <hi>Auguſtus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Strabo. l.</hi> 17.</note> 
               <hi>Nunquam pacis facultas tanta<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> omnium bonorum copia affluxit, quantum ſuppeditavit,</hi> &amp;c. Never ſo much Liberty of peace and plenty of all good things did abound, as he hath ſufficiently Miniſtred ſince he took upon him the Reines of the Empire, inſomuh as it we compare the ſtore and cheapneſſe of our preſent Commodities, with the Scarceneſſe and dearneſſe of the preterit times, we ſhall conceive them to overpoiſe ours to the value of our Taxes. And as he hath loſt all his Senſes, if he had loſt his Tongue too, he had been rid of his worſt member.</p>
            <p>The tenth Character is, In all things <hi>they pretend to be wonderful careful of the publick, to give general accompts of the monies they receive, which they pretend to be levyed for the maintenance of the State, and the proſecuting of the Warre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But in this alſo he miſconſtrues <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> who doth not deliver this as a Symptome of a Tyrant; but inſinuateth that by practiſing thoſe Precepts are proper to a Prince, his power may endure the longer; and for that he ſaith, his <hi>Highneſs</hi> made an excellent Commentary on the ſame in his Speech to this Parliament, which if he did, his <hi>Highneſs</hi> therein did per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the part of a debonaire Prince, to give an account to the repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of the people of his charges, &amp; diſburſements for the Commonwealth.</p>
            <p>The twelfth Character is,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ariſt. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c</hi> 11.</note> 
               <hi>All things ſet aſide for Religions uſes they ſet to ſale, that whileſt theſe things laſt, they may expect the leſſe of the people;</hi> the Cavalier ſaith, he would interpret this of the <hi>Deanes</hi> and Chapters Lands, as if he were not a Cavalier; and if he be not, he is worſe: for many Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valliers have ſubmitted to Gods providence, and this civil Government: but this is <hi>nihil ad rhombum;</hi> for his <hi>Highneſs</hi> ſince his power hath main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:94414:18"/>the Eſtate of the Church, and advanced Learning; though it may be not in that Superſtitious kind, this Impoſtor would have him.</p>
            <p>The thirtenth Character is, <hi>They pretend inſpirations from God, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponſes from Oracles to Authorize what they do;</hi> but how doth he apply this? His <hi>Highneſs,</hi> ſaith he, hath ever been an <hi>Enthuſiaſt,</hi> as if it were <hi>Enthuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſme</hi> for him to believe and avouch his power to be of God, and of Chriſt himſelf; upon whoſe Shoulders the Government is layed, and not to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute the contrivance and Production of this mighty Work to himſelf, or any other perſon; and not to judge of Gods Revolutions as the products of mens Inventions; and if this be Enthuſiaſm, then all our precedent Kings and Princes have been Enthuſiaſt's; who by their Title <hi>Dei gratia</hi> profeſſe to have received and held their Scepter of none but God; and that their power dimaned immediately from him as the firſt cauſe, and mediately by ſecond cauſes from him alſo, as before hath been aſſerted: or that if were Enthuſiaſm to pray and beleeve, and to receive returns from God, or to be ſpoken unto by the Spirit of God, who though he ſpeaks with the written word ſometimes, yet according to that of <hi>Job,</hi> God ſpeaketh once, yea twice; for though God doth not ſpeak to men in theſe dayes by Revelations, or by the voice of a Prophet, yet ſpeaketh he by the ſecret operation of the Spirit, though it doth not viſibly appear to us; as it is ſaid in the ſame place of <hi>Job,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 33.14.</note> God ſpeaketh once yea twice, yet man per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth it not; and that by prayer we may obtain the returns, and comfort of the Spirit, is clear by the ſimile of our Saviour. If ye then, ſaith he, being evil, know how to give good gifts to your Children, how much more ſhall your Heavenly Father give the Holy Spirit to them that aſk him? whoſoever therefore doth exclude the Spirit,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 11.13.</note> without whoſe concurrence or teaching all ordinances are ineffectual, is like to the Diſciples of <hi>John,</hi> who had not ſo much as heard whether there was an Holy Spirit; by which as the Apoſtle ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 19.2. 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 12.13.</note> we are all baptized into one Spirit, and made to drink into the ſame Spirit, and have one and the ſame Spirit, with the Apoſtles, though in a different meaſure.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Lingua quo vadit?</hi> his tongue runs at randome, and idely blurteth a nonſenſical ſimile. And as ſaith he, <hi>Hugh Capet in taking</hi> the Crown, <hi>pretended to be admoniſhed to it in a dream by the</hi> Inſtigation <hi>of St. Vallery,</hi> and <hi>St. Richard; ſo I</hi> believe his Highneſs will <hi>do the ſame at the Inſtigation of St. Henry, and St. Richard his two ſonnes;</hi> A meer bull, &amp; a nominal conceit without ſenſe or reaſon; for what correſpondence hath my Lord <hi>Richard</hi> with St. <hi>Richard,</hi> or my Lord <hi>Henry</hi> with St. <hi>Vallery?</hi> they being no ſuch ſuperſtitions Saints and dreaming Spirits. But what if his <hi>Highneſs</hi> at the Inſtigation of my Lord <hi>Henry,</hi> and my Lord <hi>Richard,</hi> ſhould have taken the Crown, which this Impoſtor did but dream of? he had taken no more then he hath merited; and he were worſe then an Infidel, if he ſhould not provide for his own, and eſpecially for theſe of his own houſhold. And my Lord <hi>Henry,</hi> and my Lord <hi>Richard</hi> may be St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Saints, that is, Holy men, if they follow his Doctrine by Faith in Chriſt, and works of Salvation.</p>
            <p>The fourteenth Character is,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ariſt. Pol.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 11.</note> they <hi>love God and Religion;</hi> and in this doth he alſo rack <hi>Ariſtotles words</hi> from the ſenſe; for his meaning is that, if a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:94414:18"/>will prolong his power, he moſt imitate a good pious Prince, which he prepoſterouſly calleth <hi>Artem Tyrannorum potiſſimam,</hi> the beſt Art of Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants; for piety and juſtice are the two pillars of a principality; otherwiſe by this Character, <hi>David</hi> a man after Gods own heart might be a Tyrant, and <hi>Numa Pompilius</hi> alſo, who was the Founder of Religion among the Romans, and for his piety advanced to that Royalty, as his <hi>Highneſs</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe partly was to this ſupream Magiſtracy: for protecting and cleanſing true Religion of its ſuperſtitions.</p>
            <p>And indeed, as he ſaith, His <hi>Arms were Pious</hi> Arms; and conquered moſt by thoſe of the <hi>Church,</hi> Prayers and Tears; for his Prayers and Tears pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed more with God, then his Arms and Force with Men; and that as he alſo ſaith, Godlineſs <hi>hath bin great</hi> gain to him, for which the Lord hath honoured him with a Temporal principality, as in all probability he will with his Heavenly Kingdom. Thus are this Impoſtors prophane Scoffs againſt his <hi>Highneſs,</hi> piouſly inverted to his honor, who not onely as he <hi>like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſaith Romanlike,</hi> but Brittainlike, being a Prince and Prieſt (for by our Law alſo <hi>Rex eſt perſona mixta cum Sacerdote</hi>) hath and doth as a Prince protect our Temporal Eſtates; And as a Prieſt preſerve the Tythes-offrings, &amp; duties of the Church, and <hi>not coſt us all as</hi> he maliciouſly ſlandereth him.</p>
            <p>No other marks of a Tyrant can be found in <hi>Ariſtotle, Plato,</hi> and his familiar <hi>Machiavel,</hi> ſaith He, which are ſuitable to his Highneſs but thoſe two, as he conceiveth: The firſt to uſe <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> own words (which he commonly changeth and wreſteth to his own conce it,) is that he would not have him impulſt with anger, to fight and ſtrike; for as <hi>Heraclitus,</hi> it is a difficult matter to reſiſt anger which may coſt ones life;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ariſt. Pol. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 16.</note> which is alſo a precept for a Prince, by the practice of which a Tyrant may the longer ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt; For as St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith, <hi>Dum juſto amplius iraſcimur, &amp; volumus aliena corrigere peccata graviora committimus,</hi> when we are angry above meaſure, and would reſtraine and repreſſe offences,
<note place="margin">Ambroſ. de Sancto Joſepho.</note> wee commit greater. And therefore <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> after the furious ſlaughter of the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> ordained that Sentences of Princes ſhould be deferred for thirty dayes from execution: yet <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſaith in another place,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ariſt.</hi> 9. <hi>c.</hi> 8.</note> Anger is a virtue in a Valiant man, and ſpurs him on to dangerous attempts, <hi>Vires injicit ira,</hi> and by conſequence in a General and Prince; And therefore as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, We ought not to provoke a King to anger, becauſe the anger of a King is like the roaring of a Lyon.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore as this Impoſtor ſaith, ſeeing <hi>his Highneſs is naturally cholerick, and will call men Rogues, and go to Cuffs,</hi> let him beware he falls not into his <hi>Highneſs</hi> clutches, leaſt he handle him like a Rogue; and ſerve gim as <hi>Agamemnon</hi> did <hi>Therſites</hi> a bawling Captain of the Grecians, who for his impudent railing ſlew him with a cuff of his fiſt.</p>
            <p>And the laſt is, that a Tyrant ſhould not be really good, nor abſolutely bad, but half one, and half toother; but herein alſo he falfieth <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ariſt.</hi> 15. <hi>c</hi> 11.</note> whoſe words are, that he ſo faſhion himſelf <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that he either have a good minde to virtue, or elſe that he be half good, and not altogether vicious; and doth not ſay that he would have him really good, but that he would have him like a Prince, be as good as poſſibly may
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:94414:19"/>be. And whereas he ſaith that this half good is too great a <hi>proportion for his Highneſs and more then his temper will</hi> bear; It is onely his ſaying, as if his <hi>Ipſe dixit</hi> like the Pope his Holy Fathers Sentence were definitive, and to be reſted in;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble advice of Parl.</hi> 1656.</note> though the contrary be humbly acknowledged by the Parliament, which is of more authority then his <hi>finxit</hi> or the Popes <hi>dixit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In concluſion he ſuppoſeth, <hi>That if his Highneſs be not a Tyrant,</hi> then <hi>there is no deſcription of a Tyrant.</hi> And becauſe he hath put an <hi>if</hi> to it, he hath invited me to ſhew him that ſome have affirmed,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Kings</hi> 1.11. 1. <hi>Juſtin. l.</hi> 1. <hi>Eſay</hi> 45.1.</note> there are no Tyrants <hi>in Titulo,</hi> and others no Tyrants in <hi>Exercitio,</hi> and divers no Tyrants at all; according to his Hypotheſis. And for that there are no Tyrants <hi>in Titulo,</hi> ſome alleadge the example of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> who invaded the right of <hi>Rehobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an;</hi> yet was he by Holy Writ neither reputed an Uſurper or Tyrant: but on the contrary, that the ten Tribes were given him by God. And ſo ſay they, <hi>Cyrus</hi> invaded the Kingdome of <hi>Harpagus,</hi> to which he had no Title though the Sonne of his Daughter; and did beat him out of his Kingdome, yet is he by the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> called the Lords an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ointed.</p>
            <p>Others to prove there are no Tyrants in <hi>Exercitio,</hi> produce the example of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> whoſe cruelty and Tyranny in Sacred Writ is general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expreſſed, but in eſpecial for erecting his golden Image, and command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that they who reſuſed to worſhip it, ſhould be caſt into a fiery Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 15.9.24.17. <hi>Baruch</hi> 1.</note> by which he would have enforced and compelled the conſciences of men to his prophane ſuperſtitions, which is the moſt execrable Tyranny, <hi>&amp; Carnificina Animorum,</hi> a Torture and Torment of mens Souls, yet God calleth him his Servant, and the Prophet <hi>Jeremy</hi> and <hi>Baruch</hi> did write to the Jews to pray for the life of him, and <hi>Baltazar</hi> his Son; And further ſay that God ſtirreth up the ſpirits of wicked Princes to do his will, and that if they abuſe their authority, they are to be judged by God onely, who is onely their Superiour: yet ſay they, God reſerveth them to the ſoreſt Tryal; Horribly and ſuddenly will the Lord appear unto them, and an hard Judgement ſhall they have.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>In Gen.</hi> 10.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And thoſe who maintaine there are no Tyrants at all, argue from the name of a Tyrant, which as <hi>Muſculus</hi> ſaith, ſignifieth nothing but as a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch, a Prince, and a King, though of late it hath been taken in the worſer ſenſe;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act,</hi> 19. <hi>&amp;</hi> 19.</note> which though it be frequent in every mans mouth, and our old Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Tranſlation uſeth ſometimes the word Tyrant, yet the Authors of the New Tranſlation have not once uſed the words, becauſe they find no He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew word in the Scripture to ſignifie a Tyrant. Neither do <hi>Ariſtotle, Bodin,</hi> or Sir <hi>Walter Rawleigh</hi> agree in the diſtinction or deſcription of Tyranny; and therefore queſtion whether any man can deſcribe what a Tyrant is; and then who can tell who was ever a Tyrant according to that deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption?</p>
            <p>Pardon me for this digreſſion; for my intention is not to aſſert any of theſe opinions, but onely to give this Impoſtor a glance, and a touch for his <hi>if;</hi> who will be of any opinions which may ſerve his turn. But now, this Impoſtor ſhall give me leave to rowl up the concluſion, which things
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:94414:19"/>ſeeing they are ſo, It is <hi>certo certius</hi> and not lyable to exception, that according to his diſtinction and deſcription of a Tyrant, His <hi>Highneſs</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out queſtion is no Tyrant, <hi>in Titulo</hi> nor <hi>in Exertio,</hi> neither in Title nor in Practice; and that he is a Lawful and Legitimate Prince, ordained by God, warranted by the Sword, and approved by the People; And <hi>triplex nodus non facile eſt ſolvendus,</hi> A triple wreath is not eaſily looſened. And this is the prime and peremptory queſtion upon which the other two depend, which being defunct, the other two dye with it. For to refricate your memories, The firſt Queſtion was whether his <hi>Highneſs</hi> was a Tyrant or no? upon which it is reſolved upon the Votes of the Scripture, Reaſon and Parliament, that he is no Tyrant. The ſecond Queſtion is, If he be a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, whether it be lawful for any private perſon to kill him? Thirdly, If it be lawful, whether it is likely to prove profitable or noxious to the Commonwealth? So as it is as cleer as the Day-ſtar, that the firſt queſtion, which is the Foundation of the other, being reſolved againſt him, the other two which are built upon it, will of themſelves fall to the ground; for <hi>Sublato Fundamento corruit Opus,</hi> The Foundationing failing the Work falleth.</p>
            <p>And now me thinks I hear my <hi>Genius</hi> calling on me, <hi>Heus tu,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cic. Epiſt. ad Att.</note> 
               <hi>manum de tabula,</hi> Hark, Sir, Stay your Hand, and ſpare your Pen, leaſt it may ſeem over-long and troubleſome. And ſo I would, were it not to be feared that ſome of the Impoſtors ſwearing <hi>Auditors</hi> will be made by his En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantements <hi>Jurare in verba Magiſtri,</hi> to ſwear what he ſaith, or through ſimplicity, or prejudice will not, or cannot conceive, or weigh the premiſſes in the golden Scales of true Judgement, and diſtinguiſh real Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from gliſtring probalities: Whereby they may be ſeduced to imagine his Highneſs to be one of his Tyrants, and his Ears to be Horns, and his Juſtice Tyranny: And conſequently, to be lawful for every perſon, to do Juſtice upon him without ſolemnity, as he ſaith, that is to kill him, according to his ſeditious inference. For what reverence and obedience will be given to a Prince (without which what is his power?) when the people are perſwaded, that under pretences and colour of Tyranny every private Subject may vindicate his own quarrel, and be a Judge and Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioner of his Right and Actions? Which prepoſterous inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to prevent, I thought it neceſſary to continue this diſcourſe, and further to proceed in the refutation of his ſtrange abſurdites; and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to my deſign of brevity, will ſuccinctly conſider his material paſſages, omitting his ſuperfluous Tautologies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt</hi> Therefore he propoſeth, that <hi>Supream Magiſtrates who degenerate into Tyrants, are not be cenſured by private perſons; and that none of ſober ſenſe do make them Judges of their actions: But he findes none have been ſuch great enemies to Comon Juſtice, or to the Liberty of mankind to give any kind of indem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper, who can pretend no title, but that of being the ſtronger; nor to have the peoples obedience upon any other Obligation then that of neceſſity, or fear.</hi> Wherin, by the way, I cannot ſuperſede Sir <hi>Edward Coke's</hi> Rule of State:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cooks Com. p.</hi> 392.</note> 
               <hi>Sunt quos ducit amo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; plures ſunt tamen quos corrigit timor,</hi> Some are drawn to be obedience by the cords of love, but more are forced to it by the ſcourge of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:94414:20"/>fear; which the Magiſtrate could not do, unleſs he were the ſtronger, and had the power of the Sword. But how unfitly do theſe expreſſions correſpond with his Highneſs Title, which hath been before diſcuſſed and reſolved?</p>
            <q>Sambucam citius caloni aptaverit alto.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Perſeus Sat.</hi> 4.</note>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>A Fidle you ſhall ſooner ſit to a Souldiers ſide.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>But to examine his Reaſons, why a Tyrants <hi>caſe is particular; and why, in that every man hath that vengeance given him, which in other caſes is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to God and the Magiſtrate;</hi> which he <hi>ſaith, cannot be obſcure,</hi> if we rightly conſider what a <hi>Tyrant is, what his crimes are, and in what ſtate he ſtandeth</hi> with the <hi>Commonwealth, and with every member of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And firſt, he aſſumeth that <hi>Laws are the Nerves or Sinewes of a Society,</hi> or Commonwealth, without <hi>which they muſt neceſſarily diſſolve, and fall</hi> aſunder. Thoſe <hi>therefore that ſubmit not to the Laws, but make their Will and Luſt a Law,</hi> and ſecure <hi>themſelves againſt the ordinary courſe of Juſtice</hi> as Tyrants do, are not to be <hi>reputed in the Society of mankind,</hi> nor to <hi>have benefit from Humane</hi> Society, nor <hi>protection from Law;</hi> wherein he ſeemeth, as he pretended, to argue from the definition of a Tyrant, which is, as he ſuppoſeth, that he that ſubmitteth himſelf to no Law, but ſecureth himſelf againſt the ordinary courſe of Juſtice, is a Tyrant; which is an imperfect definition: For in the beginning of Societies, there were no written Laws; but Princes being advanced to the hight of Majeſty for their Valour and Wiſdome,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Juſt. l.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp; l.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>Arbitria Principum pro Legibus erant,</hi> The Decrees of Princes ſtood for Laws, as <hi>Juſtine</hi> ſaith of the Aſſyrians, and of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenians; <hi>Libido Regum pro Legibus erant,</hi> the Will and Luſt of Princes were for Law. If then all Princes were Tyrants, which ſubmit themſelves to no Law, but made their Will a Law, all the Grecian Princes before the Laws of <hi>Draco,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ariſt. Polit. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 12.</note> 
               <hi>Solon,</hi> and <hi>Lycurgus;</hi> and all the Roman Kings before the Laws of <hi>Tullius Hoſtilius,</hi> were Tyrants; and ſo alſo was <hi>Moſes,</hi> whoſe <hi>licet</hi> was a Law before the Law was given him by God on the Mount: His definition therefore is defective, becauſe not <hi>adaequate</hi> to the thing defined, and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally the <hi>Nonſubmiſſion</hi> to written Laws, which he ſpeaks of, doth not make a Tyrant; For a good Prince without Laws may Rule the People aſwel as with Laws. And <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> makes it dubitable, and diſputable, whether it is better to be Ruled by a good Law,
<note place="margin">Ariſt ibidem.</note> or a good Man? And whereas he maketh <hi>Ariſtotle to ſay that Tyranny is</hi> againſt <hi>the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture:</hi> he doth not mean, <hi>contrary to the Law of Humane</hi> Society, <hi>by which Humane Nature is preſerved,</hi> as the Impoſtor conſtrueth it; for Humane Nature hath, and may be preſerved without the Law of Humane Society, and that by the Law of Nature: According to which as Sir <hi>John Davis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In the Preface to his Reports.</note> If we all lived of Nature, we ſhould need few Laws, and fewer Lawyers, which Princes, as Gods Subjects, are bound to obſerve, aſwell as their Subjects them; and which as <hi>Bodin,</hi> is, <hi>Regina utriſque Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bod. Poc.</note> A Queen commanding them both: And a Leſbian Rule flexible eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way, according to the various contingencies and viciſſitude of things: Which therefore by ſome is preferted before written Laws, becauſe the inconſtancy of the people, and change of things do often require new
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:94414:20"/>Laws, which the Law-givers cannot foreſee, or provide for, which Defects are ſupplied by the Law of Nature in a good Prince. Therefore ſuch Princes as do not guide themſelves, and rule their Subjects according to the Law of Nature, as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſaith, are Tyrants,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ariſt. Eth. l.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 10.</note> becauſe they rule con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Law of Nature; And as in another place, <hi>Rex ſi vitioſus ſit, Tyrannus efficitur,</hi> A King, if he be vitious, becomes a Tyrant; for vices are contrarie to the Law of Nature, and right Reaſon: Such vitious Princes were <hi>Sardanapalus,</hi> and <hi>Aſtyages:</hi> And therefore for their vices by <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bactes</hi> and <hi>Cyrus</hi> expulſed their Kingdomes. But grant his Major, <hi>that thoſe</hi> Rulers who ſubject themſelves <hi>to no Humane Law but their will, and</hi> his luſt is a Law, by which he <hi>governeth himſelf and others, are no Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates,</hi> but Tyrants: How doth this reflect on his Highneſs, who hath ſubmitted himſelf to the Laws of this Nation, and hath a principal care to put them in Execution? <hi>Juſtiſſimus <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nus.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Qui fuit ex Anglis, Et ſervantiſſimus aequi,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Virgil. Aene.</hi> 2</note>
            </q>
            <p>As before hath been ſhewen: Beſides in caſes of preſent importunity, or imminent neceſſity, he exerciſeth not an abſolute power, but is guided by his Councel, who have as abſolute a negative voice in the Intervals of Parliament, as the Parliament had whileſt it was ſitting. Then he falls fowl on the <hi>crimes and effects of Tyranny: A Commonwealth,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>falling into a Tyranny abſolutely, loſeth that name.</hi> For <hi>Servorum nulla eſt Civitas,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> and <hi>Grotius, Sed magna familia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ariſt. Pol. c.</hi> 8. <hi>Grotius de Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 8. <hi>ſ.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>Where all are Slaves,</hi> it is not a City: for as he ſaith, there is one Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the utility of the Ruler, and another for the commodity of the Ruled; this hath place among the free people, the other between Lords and Servants, and where the people is bridled by ſuch a Government, is not a City, but a great Family; And he inferres there is no longer King and People, Parliament and People, but theſe <hi>names are changed</hi> (at leaſt <hi>their natures into Maſters and Servants,</hi> Lords and Slaves. But certainly this Impoſtor hath learned the Art of Forgetfulneſs, not to forget injuries, as <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> and <hi>Caeſar</hi> did, but benefits and good turns as <hi>Brutus,</hi> whom though <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſaved at the Pharſalian battail,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs Speech.</hi> 12 <hi>of Septemb.</hi> 1654.</note> yet was he the chiefeſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirator againſt him; Even ſo doth he brand his Highneſs, with the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaving others, who freed him from ſlavery; and aims more at the utility of the Commonwealth then his own, and will not remember the gentle and gratious proteſtation his Highneſs publikely and ſolemnely made in Parliament, that he did not aſſume to himſelf dominion over them, but reſolved to be a Fellow-ſervant with them: And ſo indeed he is; for in his Protection he ſerveth us, and we in our obedience ſerve him: unleſſe he wil make obedience ſlavery, which is <hi>Regis &amp; Legis eſſentia,</hi> the being &amp; eſſence of a Prince and Law. And of the two, his ſervice and burden is the greater; and as <hi>Tiberius</hi> ſaid, <hi>Oneroſior ſervitus,</hi> The heavier ſervice. But obſerve his ſottiſh inference: And in <hi>truth, ſaith he, we are all members of Whitehal, and when our Maſter pleaſeth, he may ſend for us thither, and there bore through our ears at the Dore-poſts; For for whom</hi> did his Higneſs ſend for thither, but for ſuch refractory and turbulent ſpirits as his is, and there by godly and moral inſtructions did labour to bore them through their
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:94414:21"/>conſciences and reclaim them, or otherwiſe, by cuſtody, to ſecure them to prevent future combuſtions in the Commonwealth? And let this Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtor take heed that his Highneſs find not his hole wherein he lurketh, and ſend for him to <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall,</hi> and there cauſe him to be mounted on the top of a pillory, and his ears and tongue too to be bored through, and his forehead ſtigmatized for his impudent and eminent ſcandals. Next he ſheweth the condition wherein a Tyrant ſtandeth with the Commonwealth: <hi>to wit, that</hi> a Tyrant <hi>is no part of the City, nor member of the Commonwealth,</hi> and therefore in all reaſon to be reckoned <hi>in the number of thoſe ſavage beaſts that fall not within any other harde, that have no other defence then their own ſtrength, making a prey of all that is weaker, and by the ſame reaſon being a prey to all, are</hi> ſtronger then himſelf: But if we grant that a Tyrant is no part or Member of a Commonwealth (which I can neither finde in <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> or <hi>Grotius,</hi> whom he quoteth in his margent,) yet is he not for that reaſon a Tyrant; for injury ſhould be offered to a Prince, ſaith <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>L.</hi> 1. <hi>Pol. c.</hi> 9.</note> who excelleth others in virtue and valour, to eſteem him apart of the City &amp; Commonwealth, ſeeing there is <hi>Impar in eis virtus,</hi> Une<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual virtue in them; for ſuch a man ought to be eſteemed a God among men; And ſo alſo is there in Tyrants, who as he alſo ſaith, for their Virtue and Valour were at the firſt made Tribunes, or Leaders of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Regis Juſt.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 5.</note> And though they be Eccentricque and above the other Sphaere and Orbe, yet do they like <hi>Primum Mobile,</hi> Rowl about, and ſway all the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour Orbes with their Motion and rule. And therefore the compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Tyrants with wild beaſts, which he borrowed of his Maſter <hi>Mariana</hi> is incongruous and abſurd, becauſe there is not the ſame Reaſon of both, <hi>&amp; parium eadem eſt ratio;</hi> for among wild beaſts there is no rule, or goverment,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Hiſt.</hi>
               </note> but promiſcuous confuſion and dilaniation, whereas in Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny there is a Form of Rule and Government, though not ſo juſt and equal as it ought to be:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Kek. Pol. fol.</hi> 21</note> And for that Reaſon, ſaith <hi>Tacitus, Praeſtat eſſe ſub malo Principe, quam ſub nullo,</hi> It is to be better under an evil Prince then none, and a Tyranny is better then an Anarchy; for where there is no Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at all, men like brute beaſts indeed by wounds and ſlaughters, ſnatch and catch what they can to themſelves. And for the ſame infirm Reaſon,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 9.</note> he in the enſuing page aſſevereth, that no Society <hi>and no Faith is to be kept wit Tyrants, nor no Religion of Oath to be obſerved, becauſe as</hi> Seneca <hi>ſaith, that whatſoever was of Mutual Obligation between us, his deſtroying the</hi> Lawes of Humane <hi>Society hath diſſolved; but I wonder much</hi> that he who ſeemes ſo well verſed in <hi>Grotius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Grotius lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. <hi>L.</hi> 5. <hi>Tuſcan.</hi>
               </note> ſhould not obſerve that he utterly rejecteth that opinion of <hi>Seneca,</hi> and alſo of <hi>Cicero</hi>'s, which in that Place he alſo citeth, <hi>Nulla nobis Societas cum Tyrannis, ſed ſumma potius diſtractio,</hi> That no Society is to be had by us, but rather extream diſtraction. For ſaith he, Tyrants have had Society with the people, and by compacts and agreements with them, eſtabliſhed their power, by granting them Liberty: And which is more to be admired, the Impoſtor ſeemeth to countenance the Error of <hi>Michael Epheſus,</hi> which as <hi>Grotius</hi> ſaith, proceeded from that Fountain, <hi>That Adultery is not committed with a Tyrants Wife,</hi> and graceth it it with a jeer, if ſhe have no <hi>other guard for her chaſtity, but age and deformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty:</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:94414:21"/>But he will finde, that if his Wife have not the guard for her chaſtity of age and deformity, a Tyrant may with leſſe offence, and danger commit Adultery with his Wife, if he have any.</p>
            <p>In the next place he produceth another argument of the <hi>ſame nature; that a Tyrant making</hi> himſelf <hi>above all Law, and defending his injuſtice by a ſtrength which no power of Magiſtrates is able to oppoſe, becomes above all other puniſhments, above all other Juſtice, then</hi> that <hi>he receives from the ſtroak of ſome generous hand. And by the Law of Nature, where</hi> no <hi>Juſtice is to be had, every one may be his own Magiſtrate, and do juſtice for himſelf:</hi> which he learned of his Maſter <hi>Suarez,</hi> who giveth the ſame reaſon for the lawfulneſs of every private mans authority in ſuch a caſe. <hi>Quia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Suarez Reſp. ad Apologiam pro Jur. fidel. Fol.</hi> 415.</note> ſaith he, <hi>per Naturalem Legem Deus dedit unicuique poteſtatem defendendi ſe.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God by the Law of Nature, hath given power to every man to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend himſelf, where no remedy is to be had againſt him from their Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior.</p>
            <p>But herein is this Impoſtor catched in his own ginne, by falling from his firſt principle, which was that it is Lawful <hi>for every private perſon to kill <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpers or Tyrants in Titulo; but not ſupream. Magiſtrates who degenerate into Tyrants, and be Tyrants in exercitio;</hi> whereas by this reaſon every pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate perſon may as well kill the one as the other; for a Tyrant in <hi>exercitio</hi> is alſo above Law, and defendeth his injuſtice by a ſtrength which no power of inferiour Magiſtrates is able to oppoſe; and by his ſucceſſive Title becomes more potent and irreſiſtible in his Acts of Injuſtice; for no Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice can be had againſt him alſo for his Compulſory, Contributions, Loanes, Benevolences, Aſſeſſements, Taxes, or other the like Impoſitions; and may as well be ſtiled <hi>magna Latrocinia,</hi> great Robberies as well as the other. In which Argument this Impoſtor ſeemeth to have loſt his ſober ſenſes; for he ſaith, None of ſober ſenſe makes private perſons Judges of the Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of thoſe that degenerate into Tyrants, which by this Argument he doth.</p>
            <p>And further in this caſe the Impoſt or ſaith, <hi>that every one may be his own Judge, and do Juſtice for himſelf;</hi> for the queſtion is not whether a private man may take upon him to be his own Judge, whether a Magiſtrate doth him wrong or not; for that is denied of <hi>Grotius</hi> and <hi>Bodin.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Grotius l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>Ne occaſio ſit majoris tumultus faciendi;</hi> leaſt it ſhould be an occaſion of greater tumults: And therefore <hi>Cicero</hi> compares ſuch reſiſters of Magiſtrates to the <hi>Titans, Qui ut illi Caeleſtibus, adverſantur Magiſtratibus;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cic. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de Legibus.</hi>
               </note> who oppoſe Magiſtrates as they did the gods. But the queſtion is, <hi>Whether every private perſon may take upon him to be his Judge, in puniſhing an uſurper that hath no juſt Title to Magiſtracy,</hi> which this Impoſtor reſolveth in the affirmative. In which he decedeth from the Inſtitutions of his Maſters, <hi>Mariana</hi> and <hi>Suarez:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Suarez reſp. ad Apolog. pro Jur. fid.</note> The one averring, that if the Tyranny be doubtful and not Manifeſt, no man ought to offer him force; &amp; how this doubt ſhall be reſolved the other ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <hi>Neque enim inprivato cujuſquam arbitrio ponimus,</hi> &amp;c. We place it not in the Judgement of every private perſon nor mamy,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Regis Inſt. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 5.</note> unleſſe the publick voice of the people be aſſenting, and learned and grave men be called to Councel, leaſt, ſaith he, any one ſhould conſpire againſt the life of the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:94414:22"/>Prince, as if he were a Tyrant: And ſo alſo ſaith <hi>Grotius, maxime autem in re controverſa judicium ſibi privatum ſumere non debet:</hi> In this caſe above all other, a private man ought not to take to himſelf Judgement.</p>
            <p>And yet this Impoſtor would Father that opinion on <hi>Grotius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Grotius lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 4.</note> which his grave Fathers <hi>Mariana</hi> and <hi>Suarez</hi> rejected, and make him like the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyre</hi> in <hi>Aeſop, iiſdem buccis calorem &amp; frigus efflare;</hi> breath contraries, to ſupply his purpoſe; for <hi>Grotius</hi> doth not ſay, where no Juſtice is to be had, every one may be his own Magiſtrate, and do Juſtice for himſelf; for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſaid the contrary,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Molin. de In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. Fo.</hi> 1. <hi>diſp.</hi> 100. <hi>Grotius de ſol. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note> and ſo doth <hi>Molina</hi> whom <hi>Grotius</hi> cited in that place, to wit, that no private man ought to take vengeance for an injury offered him, <hi>eo quid unuſquiſque poſſit facile occoecari ſua in cauſa,</hi> becauſe every one may be eaſily bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nded in his own caſe: And therefore it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, Vengeance is mine; that is, God's, and his Magiſtrates; whom (though we ſuppoſe them to do us injuſtice) we ought not to reſiſt. And in that <hi>Grotius</hi> ſaith, <hi>ubi ceſſet judicium,</hi> where Juſtice ceaſeth, the Law of nature ſomtimes now hath place. He doth not ſpeak of injuſtice done by Magiſtrates in their place of Juſtice to private perſons, but of injuries and wronges that happen between private perſons, which appeareth by his ſubſequent diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; for Juſtice ſaith he, doth ceaſe <hi>momentanè,</hi> for the preſent mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, where Juſtice cannot be executed without certain danger and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage: In which ſence that of this Impoſtor is to be taken, that the Law of God permitteth every man to kill a thief, if he take him breaking open his Houſe in the night, becauſe he cannot bring him to Juſtice without cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain peril or loſſe: Or elſe ſaith <hi>Grotius,</hi> Juſtice doth ceaſe <hi>continuè,</hi> conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually; which is either by Right, as in Wilderneſſes and Iſlands, where there is no City and Government; or by Fact if the Subjects will not hearken to the Judge, as Pirates, Robbers, Moſſe-troopers, or ſuch noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Malefactors, who are no part of a City, but contemn Government; and therefore as <hi>Grotius</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Grotius l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 19. <hi>Molin. ibidem.</hi>
               </note> may be puniſhed by every man, if we reſpect the Law of nature; or elſe ſaith he, When the Judge doth refuſe to do Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice; as if ſaith <hi>Molin,</hi> in one Kingdom one City aſſaulteth another, and doth grievous injury to it; and the King (being requeſted) neglecteth, or dareth not to vindicate the offered injuries. In this caſe that City may not onely deſend it ſelf, but alſo make Warre with the other, and put the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactors to the Sword: But cautiouſly addeth, <hi>Non tamen auderem facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem hanc multum extendere;</hi> yet I dare not much extend this power no further then between City and City; and not to give private perſons the power of Magiſtracy; and that where no Juſtice is to be had, to do Juſtice for themſelves; no, not between themſelves, unleſſe in the cauſes above mentioned; and therefore <hi>à fortiori</hi> not againſt a Magiſtrate, as this Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor conceiveth; which opinion both <hi>Molin</hi> and <hi>Grotius</hi> utterly reject.</p>
            <p>And in that he ſaith, <hi>That it is contrary to the Law of nature, that when the Law can have no place, men ſhall be forbidden to repel force by force: but to be left without all defence and remedy againſt injury: God left not the Slave without a Remedy againſt the cruel Maſter, and permitted every man to kill a Thief breaking upon his Houſe in the night, becauſe it may be ſuppoſed he could not otherwiſe bring him to Juſtice; and ſhall a Free People have no redreſſe
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:94414:22"/>againſt an Imperious Maſter, nor an oppreſſing Tyrant?</hi> Wherein this Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor hath forgot the old Wiſe Leſſon,
<q>
                  <l>— Fuit haec ſapientia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quondam</l>
                  <l>Publica privatis ſecernere, ſacra profanis.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>To diſtinguiſh between publike and private things, Sacred and Profane; for private perſons, upon any pretence of Injuſtice, may not be their own Judges, and make reſiſtance againſt the publike Magiſtrate, or the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame power, for they are publike and Sacred perſons, Sanctified by the Ordinance of God: Yea, though they be unjuſt and wicked, yet is there power and Authority the Ordinance of God; and therefore Chriſt told <hi>Pilate,</hi> that the power he had was given him from above;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 9.11.</note> and as <hi>Jehoſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phat</hi> ſaid to his Rulers, They execute not the Judgement of man, but of the Lord.</p>
            <p>The ſame anſwer may be returned to that he ſaith, What can be more ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd in nature, and contrary to all common ſence to call him Thief, and kill him that comes alone, or with a few to rob me, or to call him <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor,</hi> and obey him who robs me with Regiments and Troopes, as if to rove with two or three Ships were to be a Pirate, but with fifty an Admiral; as if the number of Adherents onely, not the the cauſe, did make the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between a Robber and a <hi>Protector:</hi> But it is not the number of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents puts the difference between them, but the cauſe; for the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor</hi> as the publike and Supreame Magiſtrate, by the Advice of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel, or Parliament, for the good of the publike may impoſe Aſſeſſements and Taxes on the people whom as Gods Vice-gerent, we are all obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to obey: but the others in contempt of publike Authority, as private perſons Robbe, Pillage, and Plunder their Brothers and Neighbours: Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the Pirates anſwer to <hi>Alexander</hi> had been pertinent, who being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of him by what Right they did infeſt the Sea, and ſpoil Paſſengers; ſaid, by the ſame Right that he with many did Robbe the whole World. Whereas the Legal and publike Authority of the one did make the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Right and Robbery between them. And as concerning the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the people to Taxes, either made expreſſely by themſelves, or vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually in Parliament, ſatisfaction therein hath before abundantly been given. And if this Impoſtor will have other Remedy and ſatisfaction, let him hearken to <hi>Grotius,</hi> who will further Inſtruct him, and tell him that Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates Judge private men; Princes Magiſtrates, and God Princes,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Grotius l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note> of whom he hath a peculiar care, who will vindicate their offences, if he Judge i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> needful, or bear with them <hi>in poenam &amp; explorationem populi;</hi> for the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment or Trial of the people; or elſe as others ſay, they may be queſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of the Superior Magiſtrates, by the Supreame Law of the peoples ſafety. And every private mans defence; as he would have it is altogether in this cauſe reſtrained by the Law of God and man, ſince Magiſtrates and publike Courts of Juſtice have been conſtituted.</p>
            <p>Theſe are his reaſons; in which he ſaith, He ſhould be much leſſe confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, unleſſe they were ſeconded by the Examples that are left us by the greateſt and moſt Virtuous, and the opinions of the greateſt and Wiſeſt Men, by whom, ſaith he, if I am deceived, I ſhall however have the excuſe
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:94414:23"/>to have been drawn into that error by them: So that notwithſtanding his former Thraſonical vaunts; he begins now to doubt that he is deceived, and drawn into an error: <hi>Et habemus poenè confitentem reum;</hi> and not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe; for Examples and Authorities, as the Logicians ſay, are the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt Weapons brandiſhed in our humane Academy who give it for a Rule,
<note place="margin">Boeth. Hial.</note> 
               <hi>Locus ab Authoritate eſt infirmiſſimus:</hi> An Argument from Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is the weakeſt: And eſpecially his which are either wreſted, or for the moſt part miſconſtrued. But to examine them in order; in the front he placeth <hi>Grotius</hi> as his chiefeſt Champion, whom he miſtaketh and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membreth as he did before. For <hi>Grotius,</hi> ſaith he, ſaith, That an Uſurper that onely by force poſſeſſeth himſelf of Government, and by force onely keeps it, is yet in the State of Warre with every man; and therefore every thing is Lawful againſt him, is Lawful againſt an open Enemy, whom eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry private man hath Right to kill.</p>
            <p>Whereas <hi>Grotius</hi> ſaith, If by an unjuſt Warre any one by force ſuatcheth unto himſelf the Empire, and no agreement and conſent followeth, nor longe Poſſeſſion, but by force retaineth it, the Law of Warre ſeemes to remain; and that what is Lawful againſt an Enemy, is Lawful againſt him, who by Right may be killed of every private man; and omitteth the Limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatious (to wit) an unjuſt Warre, conſent of the people, and poſſeſſion, as not conducent to his deſign, becauſe they jointly concurre to the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of his <hi>Highneſs</hi> juſt Title; for as hath before been declared, his <hi>Highneſs</hi> may lay clame to this Government by the juſt Title of Warre, and alſo by the conſent of the people; the onely queſtion may be, is concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the poſſeſſion, which as I conceive, is rightly determined by Learned Maſter <hi>Aſhkam.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fol.</hi> 99.</note> That place, ſaith he, is Judged to be in full poſſeſſion, when it is ſo held, that another power as great as that that holds it, cannot approach it without great danger; or that there is no probable hope to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover it, which is ſufficient ſaith he, to challenge our obedience; &amp; which as <hi>Grotius</hi> ſaith, Every private man ought to follow, as our Saviour Chriſt did; who though he was the King of Kings, yet becauſe he had undertaken the condition of a private perſon, did willingly pay Tribute to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> becauſe the monies bore his image and Superſcription, that is, becauſe he was in poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Empire.</p>
            <p>All his other Authorities were deduced from the Laws and practiſes of thoſe Citiſens, who lived and Ruled in meer Commonwealths, to whom the Government of one was alwayes odious:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ariſt. Plut. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note> And as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, moſt people are evil Judges in their own af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires; and as this Impoſtor, who like the Devil ſometimes ſpeaks truth; it is contrary to the Laws of God and nature,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fo.</hi> 8.</note> that men who are partial to themſelves ſhould be their own Judges: And therefore <hi>Xenophon, Solon, Plato,</hi> and <hi>Cicero</hi> are not competent Judges in this caſe, becauſe it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned the continuance of their own State and dignity. And though in their Commonwealth they erected ſtatues in their Temples to Tyrannicides, and Deified thoſe private perſons who murthered Tyrants; yet in Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chical Governments, none ſuch eſcaped Capital cenſure, whoſe Examples becauſe they are divulged in moſt Hiſtories, I willingly ſuperſede, and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:94414:23"/>will onely name two, which ſeem more rare and memorable: As that of <hi>David,</hi> who cauſed the Meſſenger to be ſlain, that upon Requeſt &amp; for pitty had lent his hand to help forward the voluntary death of <hi>Saul;</hi> and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Domitian,</hi> who did put to death <hi>Epaphroditus, Neros Libertine,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he helped <hi>Nero</hi> in love to kill him; which may ſeem to be <hi>ſummum Jus,</hi> and in equity conſiderable, as void of a malicious Intention, which is the forme of Murder, and partly excuſeth or mitigateth ordinary homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cides but that the parricide of Supream Magiſtrates is of higher conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, and abominable by the Law of God and Law of man, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſhall brew his hands in their bloud, though by conſent and voide of malice, ſhall in <hi>Publicum Exemplum</hi> without hope of mercy receive the higheſt puniſhment.</p>
            <p>From his authorities, he deſcendeth to the examples of ſuch lawleſſe Murderers, which as his Maſter <hi>Mariana,</hi> are not numerous <hi>Ex tanto numero Tyrannorum</hi> ſaith he, <hi>qui anti quis temporibus extiterunt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Juſt. Reg. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 6.</note> 
               <hi>paucos quoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam numerare licet ferro ſuorum periiſſe,</hi> Out of the great company of Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants have been in antient times, few can be numbred who periſhed by the ſword of their own people.</p>
            <p>And as in <hi>Spain,</hi> he ſaith but two, ſo may we ſay of <hi>England,</hi> ſo faithful and loyal commonly have the people been to their Supreme Magiſtrate. And this Impoſtor inſtanceth but in one, which in his judgement ſeems <hi>inſtar omnium,</hi> though indeed little <hi>ad Rhombum:</hi> to wit the ſlaughter of <hi>Coeſar, which his Pater Patriae Cicero</hi> extols <hi>as an act moſt</hi> generous, and worthy of <hi>aeternal memorie.</hi> But <hi>Tacitus,</hi> more truly, <hi>cum occiſus fuit Caeſar, aliis turpiſſimum, aliis pulcherrimum facinus videretur:</hi> when <hi>Caeſar</hi> was ſlain, it ſeemed to ſome a moſt fowl, to others a moſt glorious act.</p>
            <q>Scinditur incertum Stadia in contrari vulgus.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Li.</hi> 1. <hi>Ann.</hi>
               </note>
            </q>
            <p>For if we conſider that according to the judgement of the ſager ſort, it will appear a barbarous murder and obnoxious to the ſtate of <hi>Rome</hi> as then it ſtood, and that by the judgement of <hi>Tacitus</hi> himſelf; <hi>Quia,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Nullum aliud diſcordantis Patriae remedium fuit.</hi> Becauſe there was no other remedy to cure and unite that diſcordant Nation, then by the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of one. And for that reaſon as <hi>Plutarch</hi> relateth,
<note place="margin">Plut. Vit. Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar.</note> was <hi>Caeſar</hi> created <hi>Perpetuus Dictator,</hi> by the Senate and People, hoping thereby ſaith he, <hi>Ab inteſtinis Diſcordiis reſpirare,</hi> To breath and reſt from their Inetſtine Diſcords, ſo as in the regard of the neceſſity and utility (which as they were the cauſe of our conſociation, ſo are they of our preſervation) <hi>Ceſar</hi>'s acceptance of the Empire was a neceſſary and a commodious Act: which <hi>Cicero</hi> himſelf, who fouly trampled on <hi>Caeſars</hi> aſhes,
<note place="margin">Li. de Nat. Deo.</note> did upon mature de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberation acknowledge. <hi>Quod is eſſet ſtatus Reipublicae, quod eam unius Conſilio &amp; cura gubernari neceſſe eſt,</hi> That ſuch was the State of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, that that of neceſſity muſt be governed by the Councel and eare of one; And <hi>Neceſſitas eſt Lex temporis,</hi> Neceſſity is the Law of the times, which we are forced to obey, and againſt which as one ſaith, <hi>Ne dii quidem pugnare poſſint.</hi>
               <note place="margin">App. Alexand. de Bello Civilis</note> And therefore the Senate and People of <hi>Rome</hi> after the Conqueſt of <hi>Pompey as Appian</hi> ſaith, did not onely create <hi>Caeſar</hi> perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:94414:24"/>Dictator, but with the Dictatorſhip gave him the perpetual Conſulſhip, to the Conſulſhip the Title of Emperour, and the ſirname of <hi>Pater Patriae,</hi> whereof <hi>Cicero</hi> was one. Neither could the Senate plead any excuſe for <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s murder, whom they themſelves acknowledged Supreme: But con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned it as an horrid parricide. Onely the prevaricator <hi>Cicero</hi> who (as this Impoſtor ſaith) if he was not conſcious of that deſign, yet he affected the honour to be thought ſo, as appeareth by his Philippick and invective Orations, for which he juſtly paid the mult of his head which forged them, and his hands which preſſed them, and were both faſtned to the <hi>Roſtrum</hi> wherin he made them: which may be the Impoſtors penalty in the end for his prevaricative and invective pamphlet, and that <hi>jure,</hi> who is as faithleſs and calumnious as the other: Inſomuch as if <hi>Caeſar</hi> was an Invador, as this Impoſtor conceiveth: yet was he rightly fixed and ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>led in the Majeſty of the Empire by the Decree of the Senate, and conſent of the people; who were ſo enraged at his death that they unanimouſly flocked to the houſes of the Parricides to puniſh and tear them in pieces.
<note place="margin">Plut. Vit. Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaris.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But I will conclude this Queſtion with the determination of <hi>Tholoſanus; Exempla Tyrannicidarum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Syntag. l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 20.</note> ſaith he, <hi>non hic ſunt ſequenda.</hi> The Examples of Tyrannicides are not here to be followed, which happened in a free Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth which had no King, nor did not ſubject themſelves to him, or that thoſe things which were done raſhly be meaſured by the ſucceſs: which this Impoſtor ſeems to acknowledge in that, he ſaith, <hi>That now he will conclude with authorities are much more authentick, and Examples we may much more ſafely imitate, as if it were not</hi> very ſafe to imitate the former. And now <hi>Ventum eſt ad triarios,</hi> He is driven to his laſt refuge: The ranks of his many battails are broken, and his humane arguments routed and forced to his laſt reſerve, and to bring up his triaries and divine authorities into the field, on which he chiefly relies; but they like a ſtaff of reed will fail him, and though <hi>primo impetu,</hi> at the firſt diſpute they ſeem more then men, yet at the ſecond they will prove <hi>Minus Faeminarum,</hi> Weaker then Women, and ſoon overcome: But to encounter them in the ſame order they are ranked.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. <hi>Ch.</hi> 12. <hi>Ver.</hi>
               </note> The firſt is drawn from the Law of God, <hi>which decreeth certain death to that man that doth not hearken, as he ſaith, or ſubmit himſelf to the Judge, or</hi> the Deciſion of <hi>Juſtice, and thence inferreth, that neither that, nor any other Law is in force, if there</hi> were <hi>no way to put it in execution, and againſt a Tyrant proceſſe, and citation</hi> have no place, <hi>neither have any formal remedies againſt him, and therefore</hi> includes that every man may kill him.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joan. Sarisb. de nug. Cur. l.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 20.</note> But he rowls the ſame ſtone he did before, and the ſame an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer will ſatisfie both. That a Tyrant is the Miniſter of God, whom any private man ought not to reſiſt, but is to be left to the Judgement of the Lord, who will either take vengeance on him, or permit him for our puniſhment or trial to remain.</p>
            <l>
               <hi>Regum timendorum in proprios greges,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Horat.</note>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Reges in ipſos Imperium eſt Jovis.</hi>
            </l>
            <p>The next is taken from the example of <hi>Moſes; every Engliſh man,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>hath more cauſe, and as much call as</hi> Moſes <hi>had to ſlay the Aegyptian.</hi> But as he hath no cauſe, as hath been manifeſted, ſo hath he no ſuch call; for
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:94414:24"/>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> from the inſpiration of God, obtained his authority, who moved him to this ſlaughter, that he might begin to ſhew himſelf an avenger of his people, and to kill the publick Enemy, which is the interpretation of the beſt Commentators according to the harmony of the Scriptures. For <hi>Stephen</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Moſes</hi> ſeeing one of his Brethren ſuffring wrong,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 7 <hi>Chapt.</hi> 24, 25. <hi>Ver.</hi>
               </note> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended him and ſmote the Egyptian who oppreſſed him, ſuppoſing his Brethren would have underſtood that God by his hand would have deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered them, but they underſtood not; Though <hi>Moſes</hi> did know that he was ordained a Captain from God to vindicate the Hebrews, and that he ſhould prepare himſelf by this ſlaughter to that charge; And though he did fly out of Egypt; yet as the Apoſtle ſaith, by Faith <hi>Moſes</hi> forſook Egypt,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.27.</note> and feared not the feirceneſs of the King, for he endured as he that ſaw him which is inviſible, that is, he did it not for fear, but believed in his time to deliver <hi>Iſrael.</hi> What imprudence or impudence is it therefore in this Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtor to aver that <hi>Moſes</hi> had no other call we read of, but the neceſſity his Brother ſtood in of his help, when the contrary is cleared by the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, that he had his call in this action, immediately from God, who by the ſmiting of the Egyptian was prepared and animated to the deliverance of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The example of <hi>Ehud</hi> followeth which both his Maſters <hi>Mariana</hi> and <hi>Suarez</hi> principally urge,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Suarez in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pol. pro Jur. fidel. Mor. de Rege Inſt. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 6. <hi>Grotius, l.</hi> 1. <hi>c,</hi> 4.</note> that he as a private perſon killed <hi>Eglon</hi> the King of the Moabites, to free the Iſraelites from his Tyranny. But as <hi>Grotius</hi> ſaith, Sacred authority doth plainly juſtifie that he was raiſed by God, and by his ſpecial command to avenge the Tyranny of the Iſraelites: And that God alſo by what Miniſters he pleaſed, did execute his Judgements againſt other Kings, as he did by <hi>Jebu</hi> againſt <hi>Joram:</hi> neither doth it appear, ſaith he, that the King of the Moabites had no right to rule by compact, which ſeemeth probable by the whole eighteen years time he ruled them, that ſome conſent might paſſe between them.</p>
            <p>And w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ereas he ſaith, <hi>That a Tyrant is not a Devil to be caſt out by prayer and Faſting but by a Dagger of a cubit long; yet was it the onely and pious meanes the people of God uſed to free themſelves from the Tyranny and Slavery of</hi> Nebuchadnezzar <hi>and other Princes,</hi> which at the laſt they obtained without the helpe of a Dagger; but he had rather run to the Devil for a Dagger to execute his revenge, then fly to God by prayer for his deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Judg.</hi> 10.</note> This ſame anſwer alſo may be given to his Example of <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fon:</hi> for it is perſpicuous by his miraculous acts that he was raiſed by God, to begin to deliver <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of the hands of the Philiſtines, and that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he acted was by the Spirit of God. Beſides as <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">In eundem lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</note> he was a publick Magiſtrate conſtituted of God, and that as a Magiſtrate he did puniſh and plague the Philiſtines; and therefore ſtiled their Enemy. And ſo is it ſaid, ver. 20. That <hi>he judged Iſrael in the dayes of the Philiſtines twenty years.</hi> For as the ſame Author, <hi>Nemini privato licet ad hunc modum injurias proſequi,</hi> It is not lawful for a private man in this manner to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute injuries; and not as a private man to do unto them as they did unto him, as this Impoſtor ſaith, and conceiveth. And in that the Text ſaith, that the men of <hi>Judah</hi> ſhould ſay, Knoweſt thou not that the Philiſtines
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:94414:25"/>are Rulers over us: It is anſwered by the Gloſſe on that place, that it was their groſſe ignorance that they judged Gods great benefits to be a plague unto them, which they underſtood not, though he did, and therefore ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred he them to bind him, becauſe he knew that God would deliver him. And therefore this Impoſtor for his ignorant collection in this place, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riteth to have his brains brayed in a Morter with <hi>Sampſon</hi>'s Jawbone of an Aſſe, that he may be cured of his ſooliſhneſs. And if his Friends and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations daily receive capital puniſhment as he ſaith, it is becauſe they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to the fooliſh dictates of ſuch a frenetick Impoſtor, by which they are blinded and bewitched to foment ſuch mortal and peſtilent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy againſt their Prince and the State, And therefore juſtly ſuffer: The ſame Reſponſe may alſo be returned to his Example of <hi>Samnel:</hi> That nothing was acted by him on <hi>Agag,</hi> but by the ſpecial command of God. Which,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.3.</note> becauſe it was neglected of <hi>Saul, Samuel</hi> according to the Voice of God, hewed him in pieces before the Lord in <hi>Gilgal.</hi> Neither was this <hi>Agag</hi> a Tyrant, as this Impoſtor ſaith, or an Uſurper, or had any rule or command over the People of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and therefore <hi>extra oleas fertur,</hi> he is carried beyond the limits of the queſtion, and idly argueth not <hi>ad idem.</hi> He concludes with the Example of <hi>Jehojada</hi> the high Prieſt, who ſaith he, Six years hid <hi>the right Heir</hi> of the Crown in the Houſe of <hi>the Lord, and without doubt was all that while contriving</hi> the deſtruction of that Tyrant <hi>Athaliah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 45. <hi>Godw. Ant. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 45. <hi>Martyr. Con. In</hi> 2 <hi>Kings.</hi> 11. <hi>In</hi> 2 <hi>Cron.</hi> 23.</note> who aſpired to the <hi>Crown by the</hi> deſtruction of thoſe had right to it, but though he pretended no immediate command from God as <hi>Jehu</hi> did, or immediate by <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rim &amp; Thummim,</hi> which ſignified his Prophetical Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, &amp; by which he anſwered as from an Oracle; yet as <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> ſaith, he enterpriſed that Act <hi>Fiducia praeclara auxilii Divini,</hi> By the clear and manifeſt conſidence of the Divine aſſiſtance, or as <hi>Wolfinus Tigurinus, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſu Spiritus Sancti,</hi> By the Impulſe and Inſpiration of the Divine Spirit; And therefore doth this Impoſtor improperly aſcribe this action to the ſole contrivement and invention of man; and that <hi>Jebojada</hi> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to authorize this action, but the equity and Juſtice of the Act it ſelf, which was Gods Act in him, and wrought by the Impulſe of his Spirit; who though as <hi>Lavater</hi> alſo ſaith,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 23.</note> Whatſoever he did was done by the Incitement of the Holy Spirit, yet doth he uſe the ordinary means of pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and diligence, and military forces: Becauſe humane helps, when they be offred ought not to be deſpiſed, no more then they were by <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Jehu</hi> in the like caſe. And whereas he ſaith, that <hi>any man might have done what</hi> Jehojada <hi>did as lawfully,</hi> that could <hi>have done it is as effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually</hi> as he: <hi>Jehojada</hi> did not do it, as <hi>Jehojada</hi> or a private perſon, but as the Princes Tutor and Guardian, which appertained to him, as the next of kinne, having married the Princes Aunt, who in that reſpect, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented the perſon of the Prince; and by virtue of that Relation was not onely obliged to hide and defend his perſon, but to have a care of his right to the Crown, and reſtore him to the Kingdom of <hi>Juda,</hi> which he law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully did, and onely might do, and not any other private perſon. And therefore for that Royal Act was he honoured as a King, and buried a among the Kings. Beſides, as <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> ſaith, <hi>Non erat homo privatus,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:94414:25"/>ſed Reipublicae ſumn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us Pontifex,</hi> he was not a private man,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 23. <hi>In Eundem Locum.</hi>
               </note> but the High Prieſt of the Commonwealth, to whom it appertained to judge in all Civil as well as Eccleſiaſtical cauſes; and by that authority as a Judge ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the decree and promiſe of God, that the Scepter ſhould not depart from <hi>Judah</hi> till <hi>Shiloh</hi> come; and that his Houſe and Kingdome ſhould be eſtabliſhed for ever; and according to the Law in <hi>Deuteronomy,</hi> that the Kingdome ſhould not reſide in Strangers; he did lawfully and juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly do execution on <hi>Athaliah,</hi> whereby the ſeizin and poſſeſſion of that Kingdome was made, and delivered to the right Heir of the Houſe of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah;</hi> and did not do it as a private perſon with his Dagger, but as a publick Magiſtrate with the aſſiſtance of the Nobles, and the approbation of the People; and therefore as the Text ſaith, All the People of the Land re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyced, and the City was quiet after they had ſlain <hi>Athaliah</hi> with the Sword.</p>
            <p>But mark this Impoſtors prepoſterous alluſion; They ſlew, ſaith he, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaliah <hi>at the horſe-gate, and by the Kings houſe, the very Whitehall wherein ſhe had cauſed the blood royal to be ſpilt, and which ſhe had ſo long unjuſtly</hi> poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed, and <hi>there, by providence did ſhe receive her puniſhment,</hi> alluding to the late Kings execution before <hi>Whitehall.</hi> A compariſon as abſurde as odious, and no more like then <hi>Cicero</hi> and his Son: for the one was acted by the authority of a publick Act of Parliament, the Repreſentative of the People; and the other by the malicious and revengeful hand of a Cruel Woman, with the deteſtation of all the people.</p>
            <p>Wherein this Impoſtor diſcovereth his reſerved intention, in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he did pretend to ſtand ſolely for the Parliament, but here he covert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wheeleth about to the King, and which in the next <hi>page</hi> he plainely pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſeth, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tinam,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Te potius</hi> Carole, <hi>retinuiſſemus quam hunc ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buiſſemus,</hi> We wiſh we had rather retained thee O <hi>Charles,</hi> then had this man. Who preſaging that he ſhall not by adviſing the Parliament draw the Army to his miſchievous deſign, endeavoureth by coqueſing the King to invire the Royalliſts to effect it, and careth not how it be done ſo it be done, reſolving with that deſperate malecontent.</p>
            <q>Flectere ſi nequeo ſuperos Achavontamovebo.
<note place="margin">Virgil.</note>
            </q>
            <p>If the Heavens will not help him, the Devil ſhall. But what will the Devil help him to but ſhame and confuſion? and will ſerve him as he doth the Witches, leave him when he cometh to the gallows; which will be the end and portion alſo of his accomplices, that unleſs as he ſaith, in the contrary ſenſe <hi>they repent, they ſhall alſo</hi> periſh as their precedent Aſſaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates have, and juſtly ſuffer in the ſame place where they ſhall act ſuch an high offence, and therefore admoniſh them with the Poet by others dangers to be wiſely cantious;
<q>
                  <l>Vos ego nunc moneo, faelix quicunque dolore
<note place="margin">Tibull.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Alterius, diſces poſſe carere tuo.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Yet will he not conclude this Story <hi>of Athaliah without obſerving that Jehojada</hi> commanded, <hi>that whoſoever followed her ſhould be put to death,</hi> and generally applies it to all are confederates with his Highneſs, but <hi>more eſpecially</hi> to his Chaplines, <hi>and Tryers, who,</hi> as he ſaith, will <hi>admit none to the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:94414:26"/>miniſtery that preach liberty with the Goſpel,</hi> though indeed they admit all that will preach not onely civil Peace and Liberty, but alſo Chriſtian Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and Liberty of Conſcience; and onely bar thoſe who will preach uncivil ſedition, and tyranny of conſcience: And <hi>yet doth he compare them with</hi> Baal's <hi>prieſts,</hi> becauſe as he ſaith, <hi>they do ſacrifice to our Idol of a</hi> Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, <hi>and preach for</hi> Tyrants, when as they preach nothing but ſound Doctrine, according to the Scriptures in defence of the Supream Power: and yet would have them hanged before their Pulpits as <hi>Matten Baal</hi>'s prieſt fell before the Altar; but it he is a Jeſuit, as he ſhoweth himſelf to be, he is one of <hi>Baal</hi>'s Prieſts.</p>
            <q>Et ſaepe in Magiſtrum ſceler a redierunt ſua.</q>
            <p>And what he deſignes to others may fall on himſelf, who with his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Prieſts and Jeſuits, for preaching continually like <hi>Baal</hi>'s Prieſts, Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and practiſing it in their Maſſes, &amp; principally for ſowing the Cockle of Sedition among his <hi>Highneſs</hi> Leige People, as <hi>Baal</hi>'s Prieſts did, wil certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as then heretofore have been, we hanged, drawn, and uarteted at <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burn,</hi> if once diſcovered, which they alſo may be pleaſed to take notice of, and to uſe his own phraſe, that unleſs they alſo repent, they ſhall all like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe periſh.</p>
            <q>Sed tandem amoto quaeramus ſeria ludo.</q>
            <p>And now he begins ſeriouſly to conſider what he above hath ſaid, and hath found out two Objections which he hath made ſtronger then he is able to anſwer. The firſt is, <hi>That thoſe Examples out of the Scriptures, are of men that were inſpired of God; and that therefore they had that call, or au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority for their actions, which we cannot pretend to: And ſo that it would be unſafe to us to draw their actions into Examples, unleſs we had likewiſe their juſtifications to alledge;</hi> to which he anſwereth, That if God <hi>commandeth theſe things, it is a ſign they were lawful and commendable;</hi> But if he had anſwered, that theſe were lawful and commendable in them whom the Lord had commanded to do them,
<note place="margin">Non Apollonis magis verum, quam hec ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nſum.</note> 
               <hi>Apollo's</hi> anſwer had not been more true. But to ſay, they are commendable and generally lawful, and to be drawn into Example as a General precept by every one, is more incertain then a Paradox, and abſonant from the harmony of the Scriptures; and are no more ſet down for our imitation then <hi>Jehu</hi>'s ſlaughter of <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram,</hi> which was done by the expreſſe Oracle and Revelation of God: For otherwiſe every private perſon may by that Example ſlay his true Prince, ſuch as <hi>Joram,</hi> and <hi>Ahaziah</hi> were, if they degenerate into Tyrants, which this Impoſtor himſelf ſaith, none of ſober ſene will averre. Thus is the Bee drowned in his own honey, and intangled in his own words, and his own mouth hath condemned him, yea, his own lips teſtifie againſt him.</p>
            <p>What ſhall I ſay of the Iſraelites robbing of the Egyptians, or <hi>Sampſon</hi>'s ſelf murther, or <hi>Jonas</hi> caſting himſelf into the Sea, or any other Propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal precedents, or priviledged commandments, of which fort there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny recorded in Holy Writ: but that they were otherwiſe heynous offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces by the Law of God, and out of the general, precept, and therefore un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful for us ordinarily to follow, unleſs that, as he ſaith, we had their ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifications to alledges.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:94414:26"/>
            <p>The other Objection is, That there <hi>being no oppoſition made to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of his</hi> Highneſs, <hi>the people following their callings and traffique at home,</hi> making <hi>uſe of the Laws, and appealing to his</hi> Highneſs <hi>Court of Juſtice,</hi> that <hi>all this argues the peoples tacite conſent to the Government.</hi> But this Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection is not rightly ſtated, and ſomething he hath not fully expreſſed; as to ſtile that a tacite which is more then a tacite, and implicite conſent; for it is more then a tacite and implicite conſent: for the Judges and Juſtice; of Peace to take their Commiſſions from his <hi>Highneſs,</hi> and the Sheriffs to act by his Proceſſe, and the people to come in upon the Proceſſe iſſued out by the Sheriffs, and appealing to his Court of Juſtice; For there are two main Pillars of Government, <hi>Imperare &amp; Obedire,</hi> to Rule, &amp; to Obey, which are Relatives and cannot be ſevered; And there can be no Rule without Obedience, nor no Obedience without Rule. <hi>Sint quibus Imperat.</hi> And when ſubordinate Magiſtrates are created for the <hi>Meum &amp; Tuum</hi> of the whole Land, to which the people actually ſubmit an active obedience, it is more then a tacit and implicite conſent.</p>
            <p>And in the ſtating of the Objection ſomething he hath omitted; for he ſhould have premiſed that in that his <hi>Highneſs</hi> at the requeſt of divers perſons of honour and quality, and many of the chief Officers of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, did take upon him the Supream Government, which afterward was ſeconded by the general conſent of the people, and by them created the Supream Magiſtrate of theſe Nations, as before hath been acknowledged, and demonſtrated; The people therein have openly and explicity declared their actual and real conſent to the Government of his <hi>Highneſs,</hi> which would have made the Objection ſtronger, and altogether unanſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.</p>
            <p>But now to examine his Anſwer, which <hi>is that if commerce and pleading</hi> were <hi>enough to argue the Peoples conſent, and give Tyrants the</hi> name of <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments,</hi> there was <hi>never yet any Tyranny of any long ſtanding in this world, which in his ſence may be true,</hi> ſpeaking of a Tyrant <hi>in Titulo,</hi> who ſo ſoon as he hath gained the peoples conſent without any preſcription of time, is no longer a Tyrant, even by the judgement of Learned <hi>Grotius,</hi> as he not unworthily ſtileth him; whereof commerce, pleadings, and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to him and his Magiſtrates is one clear argument which the general concurrence of the peoples conſent makes invincible And therefore im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinently doth he produce the Examples of <hi>Nero</hi> and <hi>Caligula,</hi> who were not Tyrants <hi>in Titulo,</hi> but <hi>Exercitio;</hi> who if they had been Tyrants <hi>in Titulo,</hi> the conſent of the Senate and People had cleared them of that odions name.</p>
            <p>And as to the Example of <hi>Eglon,</hi> whom the Iſraelites, as he ſaith, ſerved eighteen years, no queſtion but he by his ſo long continuance of time, and the conſent of the people might have challenged the Right of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, aſwell as by conqueſt; neither can time corroborate a principality where the antient of dayes will change it? And to the Example of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaliah</hi> who reigned ſix years, it may be anſwered, that though traffick, pleadings, and all publick Acts of Juſtice were exerciſed by and under her for the ſame time, yet wanted ſhe the complete conſent of the people,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:94414:27"/>all the people generally diſaffecting and diſliking her Government, which was apparent by their publike rejoycing at her death.</p>
            <p>Beſides <hi>Jehoiada</hi> by the impulſe of God, as a publike Magiſtrate and Tutor of the Prince, to whom by the decree of God, the Kingdom of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah</hi> did remain, which was irrepealerable, might lawfully Act what he did againſt <hi>Athaliah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Got. de Jur. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 4.</note> though her Raign had been of longer continuance, as <hi>Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> ſeemeth to intimate.</p>
            <p>To the third queſtion, <hi>Whether the removing of a Tyrant is like to prove of advantage to the Commonwealth, or not; he can ſcarce perſwade himſelf to ſay any thing, becauſe he thinks that needleſs, and all one to enquire whether it is better the man dye, or the impoſtume be launched, or the Gangreen Limbe be cut off: yet be there ſome,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>whoſe cowardice and avarice furniſh them with ſome Arguments to the contrary, and would feign make the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that to be baſe and degenerate, is to be cautious and prudent; and what indeed is a ſervile fear, they baſely call a Chriſtian patience;</hi> and that with continuance in ſlavery they have loſt their courage, and with their cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage their Fortu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>And thus would he perſwade his Auditors to precipitate themſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mortal dangers, upon the rumination of his precepts, as <hi>Cleombrotus</hi> vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly did on <hi>Plato's,</hi> without any prudential circumſpection or caution.</p>
            <p>But he might have Learned a more wary Leſſon of his Maſter <hi>Mariana,</hi> who though he Fathers his impious principles,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>De regnis Inſt. J.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 6.</note> yet adviſeth he every man to be cautious how he enterpriſeth ſuch a dangerous attempt. <hi>Artentè</hi> ſaith he, <hi>cogit andum eſt;</hi> we ought ſeriouſly to conſider what moderation and reaſon is to be obſerved in expelling a Tyrannical Prince; leaſt one evil be heaped on another, and one impiety avenged by another; and the ſafeſt and expediteſt way is, if a publike aſſembly may be called to deliberate by common conſent, what is to be determined: And eſpecially the Prince is to be admoniſhed, to be recalled to health; who if he obey and ſatisfy the Commonwealth, I think it fitting to deſiſt, and not uſe bitter and ſharp Remedies. But his Maſter <hi>Mariana's</hi> provident Inſtructions are too dila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory for this Monſters heady Reſolution, who will rather hearken to the Counſel of his prime Apoſtle <hi>Machiavel, That men deceive themſelves,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>to mollify arrogancy with humility; a Tyrant is never modeſt but when he is weak, 'tis in the Winter of his fortune when the Serpent bites not; we muſt not therefore expect cure from our patience, and ſuffer our ſelves to be cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſened with hopes of amendement;</hi> though our Saviours Counſel is, that if our Brother treſpaſſe againſt us,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 18.15.</note> we ſhould firſt tell him of his fault private<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and if he hear us not, to tell him of it before witneſſes; and if he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe them, to tell it to the Church: but if he refuſe the Church alſo, let him be as an Heathen and Publicane. Theſe are the degrees of charity every Chriſtian is to obſerve in admoniſhing his Brother, before he exerciſeth the ſeverity and extremity of Juſtice; becauſe as our Saviour ſaith, by that means we may win our Brother; and he is little leſs then an Infidel &amp; Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licane that reſuſeth ſo to do. Nay, God himſelf never ſtrikes but he denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth his admonitions that they might repent; as he did by <hi>Eliah</hi> to <hi>Ahab,</hi> by <hi>Jado</hi> to <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> by <hi>Jeremiah</hi> to <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> and by <hi>Daniel</hi> to <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzar:</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:94414:27"/>and in civil affaires admonition ought to precede Proceſſe; <hi>Non autem de neceſſitate, ſed de urbanitate, &amp; honeſtate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tholoſ. Synt. l.</hi> 32. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note> not for neceſſitie ſake, but for civility, and honeſty; ſo as this Impoſtor ſeems in this ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain fit to be void of all Piety, Civility, and Honeſty; and like a Brain-ſick Mountebanck will cut off the Limbe, before it appeares to be a Gangrene or immedicable, and lance the Impoſtume, which with Soveraign Salves may be cured, and Judge that a Gangrene and Impoſtume which is none. Yet this Impoſtor ſaith, <hi>Nemo unquam impertum flagitiis quaeſitum bonis arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus exercuit;</hi> never did any man Mannage the Government with Juſtice that got it by wicked meanes: The longer a Tyrant lives, the more the Tyrannical humor encreaſeth in himſelf.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tac. l.</hi> 1. <hi>Hiſt.</hi>
               </note> But this is part of <hi>Piſos</hi> ſpeech againſt <hi>Othe,</hi> who was a competitor with him for the Empire; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the leſſe authentical: And if <hi>Flagitiis</hi> is underſtood by force and might, as this Impoſtor in this pamphlet ſeemes to take it, then this poſition is not generally true; for <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> who gained the Empire by force, and is ſtiled by <hi>Victor Invaſor,</hi> was as he ſaith, <hi>tam pacis bellique artibus clarus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vict. vita Caeſ.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primis clementia longe clariſſimus,</hi> moſt famous in Peace and Warre; and eſpecially in clemency moſt famous:
<note place="margin">Ib. vita Aug.</note> And though <hi>Auguſtus</hi> was <hi>Dominandi ſupra modum avidiſſimus,</hi> and by might obtained the Empire; yet for his candid Demeanor and civil Juſtice was he ſo beloved, and honored after his deceaſe by the people, that they wiſhed <hi>ut non naſceretur, aut non more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur,</hi> that he had not been born, or had not died: beſides <hi>Grotius</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Grot. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 14.</note> 
               <hi>Tyranni interdum libertatem reddiderunt;</hi> Tyrants ſometimes have reſtored Liberty; &amp; <hi>Tacitus</hi> himſelf in the ſame ſenſe, <hi>Vitia erunt donec homines,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hiſt. l.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>ſed nec haec continua, ſed interventu meliorum penſantur;</hi> there will be Vices as long as there be men; but theſe are not continual, but are recompenſed by the intervening and ſupply of better things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But what,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>would ſucceed, if a Tyrant ſhould be removed?</hi> I will tell him, that <hi>cura pejor ſit morbo;</hi> the cure may be more dangerous then the diſeaſe. And as his Maſter <hi>Mariana</hi> ſaith, one evil may be heaped on another; and one Impiety avenged by another: and all Hiſtorians will ſhew him the lamentable events of ſuch prepoſierous and precipitated mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, which many times beget effuſion of blood, ruines, and ſacking of Cities, and ſometimes the deſtruction of Cities and Kingdoms. But I will rather inſtance in ſome ancient Examples then Novel, which as yet adhere in the minds and mouthes of men: It is not unknown to thoſe who are verſed in Annals, that of all the <hi>Grecians</hi> none were more renowned then the <hi>Spartans,</hi> either for the glory of Military, or ſeverity of Civil diſcipline: but they when they could not endure the Dominion of <hi>Agis</hi> becauſe it ſeemed to be a Tyranny; conſpired againſt him, and openly ſlew him: But what were the Fruits of this unhappy Slaughter,
<note place="margin">Cic. Tull. Offic.</note> 
               <hi>Tully</hi> doth ſhew us; <hi>Ex eo tempore,</hi> from that time, ſaith he, the ſtrength of the <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> did fall into divers Stormes and Tempeſts of adverſities; and did ſuffer all the calamities of a miſerable ſtate. And what ſucceeded the Barbarous ſlaughter of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> but moſt dangerous and mortal Diviſions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the chief, who being inflamed with the hope of obtaining the Empire did by their Diſſentions tear the Bowels of the Commonwealth in pieces?
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:94414:28"/>Inſomuch that the people complained, as <hi>Tacitus</hi> relateth, <hi>prope everſum orbem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hiſtor.</note> 
               <hi>etiam cum de principatu certaretur;</hi> That by the Diſſentions of men, concerning the principality, the whole world was turned upſide down: Which <hi>Caeſar</hi> himſelf preſaged, who being informed of ſome Nocturnal conjurations, and meetings of ſome Malevolent perſons, did checke and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend them ſaying and Prophecying of himſelf, <hi>Non tam ſua quam Rei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publicae intereſſe ut ſalvus fieret,</hi> That it reflected not ſo much upon his own good, as the welfare of the Commonwealth, that he ſhould be ſafe; and that for himſelf he had got abundance of glory: but the Commonwealth, if any ſuch thing ſhould happen, would not be quiet and peaceable, but in a worſe condition then before.</p>
            <p>And therefore is the ſafety of a Tyrant more to be deſired then his Slaughter,
<note place="margin">In Plut. in Bruto.</note> becauſe commonly civil Warres thereupon enſue: for as <hi>Favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinus,</hi> A civil Warre is worſe then an unlawful Dominion; which <hi>Cicero,</hi> who could beſt judge of the beſt State of a Commonwealth, in his Epiſtle to <hi>Pomponius Atticus,</hi> in the time of the civil Warres writing of them, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged, <hi>Ego autem uſque co enercatus ſum, ut malim</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>quam cum optima ſpe dimicare;</hi> But I, ſaith he, am ſo out of heart and caſt down that I had rather live under a Tyrant, then fight with the beſt of hopes. And therefore after the civil Warres were ended, and the Empire placed on <hi>Auguſtus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Ann.</hi>
               </note> the people wiſely, as <hi>Tacitus</hi> writes, <hi>novis rebus aucti tuta, &amp; praeſentia quam vetera &amp; periculoſa mallent:</hi> being augmented and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by their new Government, did deſire rather thoſe preſent times which were ſafe, then thoſe preterite which were dangerous. This needs no ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication to the condition of our State: <hi>Res ipſa loquitur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides it is obſerved,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Golden Grove. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> that according to the <hi>French</hi> Proverb, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n mal traine un auter,</hi> one evil draws on another; and commonly that one Tyrants head being cut off, three more may ariſe in their roome; ſo the people of <hi>Rome</hi> by the avoiding the <hi>Scilla</hi> of one Tyrant, to wit <hi>Silla</hi> fel headlong in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Charybdis</hi> of many Tyrants, which more perplexed them. To which purpoſe <hi>Valerius Maximus</hi> reporteth a pretty Story of a certain old Woman,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note> who, when the <hi>Syracuſians</hi> did ſervently deſire the end and expiration of <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the Tyrant, did poure forth her Prayers for his health; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing demanded of the Tyrant (wondring at her undeſerved reverence to him) for what good turn ſhe did ſo: anſwered, that ſhe being a Maid, and living under a grievous Tyrant, deſired to be rid of him, who being ſlain, a more cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>el Tyrant poſſeſſed the Caſtle, and that ſhe alſo wiſhed a period to his Dominion, which alſo was effected, and that then a more outragious Tyrant ſucceeded him: And therefore ſaith ſhe, fearing that you being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away, a worſe might poſſeſſe your place, ſhe did devote her Prayers, for his ſafety: A grave though a Foeminine anſwer, which deſerves to be placed among the famous Apothegmes; for it is generally obſerved, which alſo is verified in the ſucceſſion of the firſt <hi>Roman Emperor,</hi> that the latter commonly is worſe then the former.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tiberius,</hi> as <hi>Dion.</hi> ſaith, was cruel, and a diſſembler; and was ſublated by poiſon, whom <hi>Caligula</hi> ſucceeded, an inceſtuous, Prodigal, and Luxuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Tyrant, and inceſtuous with his Siſters, whom <hi>Cheraea</hi> murdered.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:94414:28"/>
               <hi>Claudius</hi> ſucceeded him, who was a Slave to <hi>Meſſalina</hi> and his Servants, and was poiſoned with a Muſhroome; whom <hi>Galba</hi> ſucceeded, who was <hi>inexplebilis pecuniae,</hi> a Slave to his Coffers; which is a moſt abominable vice in a Prince, who above all others ought to be magnificent; for which vileneſſe he was ſlain by his Souldiers. <hi>Nero</hi> ſucceeded him, who was a deteſtable Monſter, defiled his Mother, and after murdered her; he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by the <hi>Senate;</hi> and for ſear of ſhame executed the office of Hangman upon himſelf. Not long after <hi>Vitellius</hi> took upon him the Empire, who was nothing elſe but drunkeneſſe and gluttony, and of al the reſt died moſt ſhamefully and miſerably; <hi>Aetas parentum pej<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r avis,</hi> and ſeldome comes a better. Onely <hi>Veſpaſian,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tacitus, in melius mutatus erat,</hi> was chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into the better. I could Load you with Examples of this nature, but my Intention is not to be tedious and burthenſome: But let us per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend what this Impoſtor ſaith to it: <hi>It is phrenſy,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>and ridiculous policy, to ſuffer a certain miſery for a contingent one, and let the diſeaſe kill us becauſe there is danger by the cure, and ne moriare mori, and not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fire a change, when we are certain we cannot be worſe: Cujus contrarium ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum eſt;</hi> &amp; in this caſe the contrary is true; for we ſuffer not a certain miſery; and if we change, we may be worſe; for we now poſſeſſe plenty and peace, which are <hi>optima rerum,</hi> the beſt of things; and upon the change may probably fall into civil diſſentions, and have a worſe Government, which is <hi>peſſima rerum,</hi> the worſt of things: and therefore as <hi>Cicero</hi> in the ſame caſe affirmeth, <hi>omnis pax bello civili utilior videtur:</hi> Any peace ſeemes more commodious then a civil Warre. And whoſoever ſhould attempt ſuch an infernal Act, is ſure to undergo a certain, not a contingent miſery, and no leſſe then capital cenſure, and loſſe of Life; unleſſe with this Impoſtors brave <hi>Syndercombe</hi> he prevents it with a <hi>nè moriare mori;</hi> for diſcovery, vengeance lies at there door; and the Lord doth never, or rarely permit ſuch Impoſtors to eſcape Divine Juſtice:
<note place="margin">Vita Auguſti.</note> 
               <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> as <hi>Suetonius</hi> Hiſtoriſeth it, <hi>non ultimae quidem ſortis hominum conſpiratione &amp; periculo caruit,</hi> wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not the dangerous conſpiracies of the meaner ſort of men; yet were they diſcovered or ſuppreſſed, <hi>priuſquam invaleſcerent,</hi> before they were of any validity, and incurred the fatal ſtroke of the Sword of Juſtice: And to come nearer the ſtate of thequeſtion, <hi>Leonagillus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Golden Grove. l.</hi> 9. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>Ann. Dem.</hi> 568.</note> an ancient King of the <hi>Gothes</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> both a Tyrant and a <hi>Arrian,</hi> purſued the true Chriſtians, and exiled his own Son, becauſe he was of the true Religion; where upon this young Prince being moved at the perſecution of the Chriſtians, did twice raiſe Armes againſt his Lord and Father: At the firſt he was taken captive and baniſhed, and at the ſecond he was put to death on Eaſter day. So <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> being a Tyrant and Perſecutor of the <hi>Jews,</hi> who were then Gods people, yet becauſe <hi>Zedekiah</hi> rebelled againſt him, who was then his Soveraign, was he put to flight, and he and his Sons taken Priſoners, who were ſlain before his eyes, and himſelf bound in chaines, caſt into Priſon, and both his eyes put out, where he remained till the day of death. Two notable Examples of the effects of Gods Judgements againſt two Princes for rebelling againſt their Soveraign. More precedents to this purpoſe are recorded in the Volumes of preterit Stories, <hi>quam
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:94414:29"/>muſcarum cum caletur maximè,</hi> then flies in the heat of Summer: but I Study Brevity, eſpecially in ſo a clear caſe; how ſoever it is reſolved in this Impoſtors Junto, that his <hi>Highneſs</hi> is <hi>to be killed; but he onely queſtions the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner how; ſome,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>are of a ſtrange opinion, that it were a generous and noble Act to kill his Highneſs in the Field, but that pleaſeth not his Spirit,</hi> knowing well that he is <hi>impar congreſſus Achilli,</hi> and that he is ſtronger in the Field then in the Court; and doth not like the hazard, blood and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion that thereupon might enſue: but he would have him catched in a Ginne,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 9.</note> and ſlain by a Stratagem; for, ſaith he, <hi>The moſt Lawful way to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy him, is the readyeſt; no matter whether by force or fraude.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And by conſequent,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Regis Inſt. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 7.</note> ſaith <hi>Mariana,</hi> no matter, if by poiſon, eſpecially, ſaith he, the ſaculty of Acting by fraude being granted. And for this reaſon, becauſe ſaith this Impoſtor, it may be ſo effected with leſſe hazard, blood, and confuſion, which makes no difference between open force, and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate fraude; for though hebe not removed by a precedent bloody War, yet a ſubſequent Warre may happen as dangerous and as bloody as it, as it did upon <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and <hi>Richard</hi> the ſeconds Slaughter; which was the cauſe of the greateſt conſuſion and effuſion of blood between the Houſes of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> that ever embroyled this Nation, wherein four ſcore of the Blood-Royal periſhed. As alſo of the loſſe of <hi>France,</hi> which as <hi>Philip Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaeus,</hi> Secretary to <hi>Lewis</hi> the eleventh King of <hi>France,</hi> averreth, we might have retained, had not thoſe diviſions intervened and impeded us; ſuch are the fatal effects of the murder of Supream Magiſtrates, though ſuppoſed Tyrants.</p>
            <p>And though it is more generous and more noble to kill the Enemy in the Field,
<note place="margin">Ariſtorle.</note> then by fraude; and that a magnanimous man loves to ſpeak freely and truely; and a generous mind knows not by ſtealth to conquer his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy; as <hi>Alexander,</hi> though he were Adviſed by <hi>Parmenio,</hi> to conquer his mighty Enemy <hi>Darius</hi> by circumvention, refuſed ſo to do, holding it more glorious, <hi>Aperto Marte,</hi> by dint of Sword to gain the Victory, becauſe thereby the mind of the Enemy is perpetually conquered, and forced to confeſſe the Victory, as <hi>Claudian,</hi>
               <q>Confeſſos animo quoque ſubjugat hoſtes.</q> And which generally alſo was the practice of the <hi>Romans,</hi> unto the end of the ſecond <hi>Punique</hi> Warre; yet is fraude by the ſtouteſt and ſageſt Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains ranked in equal poſture with ſtrength and might, as <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes,</hi>
               <q>— Dolus an virtus,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Virg. Aen.</hi> 2.</note> quis in hoſte requirat.</q> And as by <hi>Fabius Maximus,</hi>
               <q>Et in virtuti placuit dolus.
<note place="margin">Silius Ital.</note>
               </q> And according to the vulgar Verſe:
<q>Nil refert armis contingat palma, dolove.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And as <hi>Auſtin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> 10. <hi>ſuper Joſ.</hi>
               </note> it appertaineth not to the Juſtice of Warre, whether it be Acted by ſorce or fraude.</p>
            <p>And to give the Devil his due, ſuch prudent fraude and craft is to be preſerred in Martial enterpriſes,
<note place="margin">De re Militar.</note> before force and might of hand, becauſe as <hi>Vegetius, aperto Marte commune eſt periculum:</hi> In open fight the danger is common and equal; but <hi>Ex occulto,</hi> by a cloſe and ſuddain fight, the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:94414:29"/>may be either vanquiſhed or put to flight with little loſſe and leſſe dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; which was the cauſe of the Ceremony of the <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> (who of all the <hi>Grecians</hi> were the beſt warriours) that they (when they over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the Enemy by Stratageme) did ſacrifice an Oxe to <hi>Mars;</hi> but when by open ſtrength, a Cock; preferring the utility of the firſt before the mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimity of the latter:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chryſoſtome l.</hi> 1. <hi>de ſacerdotio.</hi>
               </note> And therefore <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> chiefly commended thoſe Emperors, who by fraude obtained Victories. But what doth all this avail to this Impoſtors drift? for though ſuch Stratagemes are approved be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Prince and Prince, Captain and Captain; yet are not ſuch violent fraudes allowable between private perſons in a peaceable Commonwealth, much leſſe to Subjects againſt their Magiſtrates, who are to obey Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, and to be ſubject to Principalities and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; for that were <hi>coelum cum terra miſcere,</hi> to confound Heaven with Earth, and make a <hi>Chaos</hi> or confuſion in the Commonwealth, and therefore by all Princes condemned as Capital.</p>
            <p>And though Empoiſoning is leſſe turbulent, becauſe more occult; yet is it more execrable and deteſtable, and exploded by the Law of Nations, even in military affaires. Which <hi>Tiberius</hi> (ſubtil enough to do miſchief) refuſed to Act on his terrible Enemy <hi>Arminius,</hi> of which <hi>Grotius</hi> gives the reaſons; becauſe the perils of Warre (which were frequent) ſhould be too much extended.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Grotius de Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 4.</note> And that Princes (whoſe lives before others are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended by Armes) are leſſe ſafe then others from poiſon: Yet <hi>Mariana</hi> (this Impoſtors Tutor) who approves the killing of Princes by poiſon, whom he calls Tyrants, if they do not pleaſe the Pope;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Regis Inſt. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 7.</note> yet alwayes with this modification, That it is better to poiſon a Tyrant in his chair, or in his habit, in imitation of the Moores, then to poiſon his drink, for fear the Tyrant may be guilty of killing himſelf, and that it may prejudice his Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
            <p>Certainly a great Example of charity ſaith <hi>Pierre du Mouline</hi> Ironically,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bourbier de la foy. Fo.</hi> 730.</note> that thoſe Fathers ſhould have a cure of the Soul, when they cauſe the Body to be flain; and yet extols the Murder of <hi>Jacobim</hi> the Monk, for killing with a poiſoned Knife <hi>Henry</hi> the third King of <hi>France,</hi> ſaying, <hi>caeſo Rege,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Regis Inſt. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 6. <hi>Pet. Mol. b.d. f.</hi> 129.</note> 
               <hi>ingens ſibi nomen fecit,</hi> That he got himſelf a great and excellent name by kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him; for which the Pope gave thank to God in a full Conſiſtory, without any charitable reſpect to the Soul of <hi>Henry</hi> the third: Such chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Fathers hath this Impoſtor.</p>
            <p>And though the <hi>Gothes,</hi> and the <hi>Parthians,</hi> and the <hi>Moores,</hi> did infect their Weapons with poiſon, and double the cauſes of death; yet hath it alwayes been abhorred of moſt Chriſtians, and eſpecially of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>Brittains,</hi> as <hi>Johannes Sarisburienſis</hi> (the Diſciple of <hi>Thomas Becket</hi>) writeth, <hi>Quod Britannia veneno abhorruit, &amp; in principes non novit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Nugis Cur. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 9.</note> 
               <hi>ſed pro ſuis principibus invictos gladios exercere:</hi> That <hi>Brittany</hi> abhorred from poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and did not know to exerciſe their invincible Swords againſt their Princes, but for their Princes. And ſuch poiſoning Plots were not heard of in our Nation,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bakers Hiſt Q. Eliz. Reign. F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 553.</note> until ſome <hi>Spaniards</hi> thinking to make Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> away by poiſon, and not daring to truſt any <hi>Engliſh</hi> man in ſuch a buſineſſe, did treat to that purpoſe with <hi>Rodericke Lopus</hi> a Jew, and Phyſitian to the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:94414:30"/>Queen, with <hi>Ferrara Loyſy</hi> and other <hi>Portugals,</hi> who came into <hi>England</hi> at that time in Relation to <hi>Don Antonio,</hi> but were diſcovered by the Intercep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Letters, and were all condemned and executed at <hi>Tyburn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now he begins to rave, and like <hi>Ajax</hi> is angry without fear or wit;
<q>
                  <p>— Calido ſub pectore bilis</p>
                  <p>Intumnit,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Perſeus ſat.</hi> 5.</note> quam non extinxerat <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rna cicutae.</p>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>He preſageth, and <hi>truely that his ſenceleſs projects will not prevail with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious Auditors;</hi> and that he doth
<q>— Ventis perfundere verba,</q> Vent his mind to the wind; and therefore gives over his ſeducing exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and vomits out the Venone of his rancour and bitterneſſe againſt every one. <hi>What have we of the Nobility</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>but the name? The Luxury and the Vices of them. Poor Wretches, thoſe that now carry the Title, are ſo far from any of their Virtues that ſhould grace them, and indeed give them the Titles, that they have not ſo much as their generous Vices, Indignation, and Ambition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And wherefore all this, but that the Nobles are ſo virtuous and pious, as to ſubmit to the good pleaſure of the Almighty, and not madly (as he doth) to kick againſt the Prick.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What have the Miniſters,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>or what indeed deſire they of their cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, but their Titles? how do they racke the Scriptures for flatteries, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudently apply them to his Highneſs?</hi> And why this alſo? but that they derive his <hi>Highneſs</hi> Authority from the power of the Scriptures, and Miniſter the ſincere Milk of the word, and in plain evidence of the Spirit and power, and not by the enticing Speech of mans wiſdom, as he doth the contrary.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the City,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>but a great tame Beaſt that eates, and carries, and cares not who rides it?</hi> And this too, becauſe they prudently and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly affect peace and tranquillity, and will not be rid by ſuch a miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous <hi>Baboon,</hi> nor driven through his inſtigations to ruſh into the Battail, like the Horſe and Mule that have no underſtanding. <hi>And what,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>will not the Army fight for? what will they not fight againſt? what are they but Janiſaries and Slaves themſelves, and making all others ſo?</hi> But it is an old ſaying, that one Fool may propound more queſtions then twenty wiſe men are able to anſwer; but he hath here propounded many queſtions any Fool may anſwer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What will not the Army fight for?</hi> ſaith he: Who knows not but they will not fight for ſuch ſeditious, and turbulent Traitors as he? and who knows not what they will not fight againſt? not againſt their couragious and Victorious General; and their magnificent, and courteous Lord and <hi>Protector;</hi> and who knows not that they are not <hi>Janiſaries,</hi> but their Generals Commilitons and fellow Souldiers; not Slaves, but Commanders, and have freed us from Slavery; and as it is ſaid in, the peoples late Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentative, reſtored us to peace and tranquillity?</p>
            <p>At the laſt ſaith he, <hi>What are the people in general, but Knaves, Fools, and Cowards, principled for eaſe, vice, and Slavery?</hi> But who knows not that their honoſty and fidelity exceedeth that of other Nations, and that in that reſpect <hi>Anglorum fides,</hi> among Chriſtians may paſſe for a Proverb; as an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:94414:30"/>
               <hi>Artica fides</hi> did among the Grecians? And he hath forgotten what his holy Father Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> called them, <hi>Angli, quaſi Angeli,</hi> for their fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and honeſty; and fools they are not, becauſe they will not ſwallow this Impoſtors principles of knavery, which none but fools and gudgeons will? And who dares call them ſo, whoſe renowned valour is ecchoed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſounded within the circumference of <hi>France, Spain,</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> and are not principled in eaſe, vice, and ſlavery as he ſaith, but employed in noble and virtuous actions, for the glory of their Countrey?</p>
            <p>And as for Slaves, that Tenure hath been long ſince exiled <hi>England, Et nunquam Libertas gratior extat,</hi> We never enjoyed more gratious Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; And thoſe Epithites do more properly appertain to himſelf. For doth not he play the knave and fool too with the Nobles, Miniſters, Citizens, Parliament, People, and with the Councel? yea, the <hi>Protector</hi> himſelf al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt in every paſſage of this pamphlet?</p>
            <p>And who will not judge him a Fool, whoſe peeviſh conceits end in his own deſtruction, which queſtionleſs will fall on his petulant noddle? <hi>Et Sapiens incipit a fine,</hi> And a Wiſe man begins from the end. And a Coward certainly he is, and dares not appear in the open field, though a profeſſed Souldier,
<q>
                  <l>—Et larga eſt illi copia fandi</l>
                  <l>Tunc eum bella manus poſcunt.
<note place="margin">Virgil. Aeneid.</note>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And is bragging and prating when he ſhould be fighting.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Syndercombe</hi> is the onely Patriot, he deems worthy of his Elogies, who he ſaith, <hi>hath ſhewed as great amind, as any Old</hi> Rome <hi>could boaſt of; and had he lived there, his name had been regiſtred with</hi> Brutus <hi>and</hi> Caſſius, and had had his ſtatue aſwell as they; and ſo he might; for <hi>Brutus</hi> and <hi>Caſſius</hi> had no ſtatues erected to them in <hi>Rome;</hi> And if they had not fled from <hi>Rome,</hi> the people had ſerved them as they did <hi>Caeſar,</hi> ſo much they abhorred his barbarous murder; But on the contrary, beſides ſtatues, the people erected a Columne of the pureſt ſtone, almoſt of twenty foot long to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and placed it in the Market-place, in which was engraven <hi>Pater Patriae.</hi> And alſo erected a Temple to him in common with the Goddeſſe of <hi>Clemency,</hi> and conferred many Divine honors on him. But all the honour that <hi>Brutus</hi> and <hi>Caſſius</hi> gained, was their miſerable ſelf-mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and rather for the ſame merited a ſtake knocked in their graves, then ſtatue in the temple, with his deſperate <hi>Syndercomb,</hi> who inſtead of taking away his ſtake from his grave (which this Impoſtor would have) deſerveth to have his head faſtned to the top of a long pole, and ſet on the top of <hi>Newgate,</hi> according to the Engliſh cuſtome, as an enſign of his traite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous intention, and ſpectacle of infamy, which is the onely ſtatue or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument this Impoſtor muſt expect for him. Yet do I not much wonder why he is ſo profuſe and exceſſive in his commendations, when I obſerve that he chiefly praiſeth him, for that <hi>neither bribes nor terrors could make him betray his Friends,</hi> whereof he may be ſuppoſed to be one, and that <hi>Mulus Mulum ſcabit,</hi> One Knave clawes another.</p>
            <p>And at the laſt I cannot but obſerve that this Impoſtor in three paſſages of this pamphlet, hath been tampering with the Army to perſwade them-againſt
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:94414:31"/>againſt his <hi>Highneſs,</hi> and hath excogitated an irrefragable reaſon, as he ſuppoſeth, whereby to effect it; 'Tis a Rule ſaith he, that Tyrants ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve when <hi>they are in power, never to make uſe of</hi> them that help them to it. <hi>And indeed,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>it is their intereſt and ſecurity not to do it: for thoſe that have been the Authors of their greatneſs, being conſcious of their many me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, they are bold with the Tyrant, and leſſe induſtri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us to pleaſe him; They think all they can do for them is their due, and ſtill they expect more; and when they fail in their expectations, as it is impoſſible to ſatisfie them, their</hi> diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointments make them diſcontented, and their diſcontents dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous.</p>
            <p>His Rule is experimentally falſe; for Princes whom he ſtiles Tyrants, when they are in power make uſe of thoſe, and prefer them that helped them to it, until they grow inſolent in their demands, and offenſive in their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents.</p>
            <p>But true it is, that it is a moſt difficult thing to pleaſe and ſatisfie thoſe that advanced him,
<note place="margin">Victor Vita. Nervae.</note> and ſecure them from diſcontent, which made <hi>Nerva</hi> to complain, after he had taken upon him the Empire, that he was not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſubject to many vexations, and perils, but to the cenſure not onely of his Enemies, but of his Friends: <hi>Qui cum merere omnia praeſumum, ſi quicquam non extorſerint, atrociores ſunt ipſis quoque hoſtibus,</hi> Who when they preſume to merit all things, if they cannot extort what they deſire, are more bitter and dangerous then their Enemies themſelves</p>
            <p>And therefore is every Prince and Emperour between <hi>Scylla</hi> and <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribdis,</hi> two dangerous Rocks, to wit, their enemies and their Friends. And though by their Friends aſſiſtance they keep their Enemies in aw; yet many times their deſerts make them to forget themſelves, and in a moſt dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous manner to oppoſe their Princes, if they correſpond not with their peremprory vores, which hath Moved Princes ſometimes to leſſen their power, and other times ſeverely to puniſh them According to the degree of the contempt; of which a rare Example we have in the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civil deportment of Sir <hi>William St<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anley</hi> towards <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh, who at the Battail of <hi>Boſworth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bak. Hen.</hi> 7.</note> came in to reſcue him, when he was in danger to be ſlain by <hi>Richard</hi> the Third, and afterwards did ſet the Crown on his head, which was found among the ſpoils; for which Noble Act he promoted him to be one of the Privy Councel, &amp; Lord Chamberlain of his Houſhold, and gave him the Ample Spoils of the Victory, and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe abundantly rewarded him, inſomuch as at his death were found in his Caſtle in ready money Forty thouſand Marks beſides Plate and Jewels: Yet becauſe <hi>Henry</hi> the Seveth refuſed to grant him one inconvenient boon (to wit) to be Earl of <hi>Cheſter</hi> (which was an Appennage to the Principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of <hi>Wales,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bacon. Hen.</hi> 7.</note> and an honour appropriate onely to the Kings Son) he fell into a miſchievous diſcontent, and began to incline to <hi>Perkins,</hi> and as ſome ſay, to aid him with mony; but certainly to prefer the Title of <hi>York</hi> before that of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> which appeared by his own confeſſion, in ſaying that if he certainly knew that <hi>Perkins</hi> was the ſon of <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bak. Hen.</hi> 7.</note> he would never fight, nor bear arms againſt him, for which words he was arraigned, condemned, and beheaded; and all his former merits buried in the grave
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:94414:31"/>of this conditional treaſon: and in this ſenſe, is that true that the Impoſtor ſaith, that a Prince will never truſt thoſe he hath provoked, and fears, and will be ſure to keep him down, leaſt he ſhould pluck him down.</p>
            <p>And in ſuch caſes a Prince is not at liberty to ſhew mercy as a private man may; for a Prince, as Sir <hi>Edward Coke,</hi> is <hi>Caput &amp; ſalus Reipublicae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Coke l.</hi> 5. <hi>f.</hi> 124.</note> the head and ſafety of the Commonwealth. And as from the head health is conveyed to every part of the body, ſo from the Prince ſafety is conveyed to every part of the Common-wealth, and every private perſon hath intereſt in the ſafety of the Prince, becauſe his ſafety is their ſafety; and therefore a Prince ought not freely and abſolutely to ſhew mercy to ſuch traiterous malefactours, becauſe the Commonwealth is interceſſed in it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Et pereat unus ne pereant omnes.</hi> It is better that one periſh, then all ſuffer; And a Prince (to uſe that Impoſtors alluſion) may uſe <hi>ſuch friends</hi> (who abuſe their truſt, and conſpire againſt him, and are not onely uſeleſs, but obnoxious to the Common wealth,) as <hi>Dionyſius did, hang them</hi> up like Bottles, and not incurre the title of a Tyrant, but be adjudged a wiſe Prince, as <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh was.</p>
            <p>But now this Impoſtor is acting the laſt Scene of his interlude, and as in a Tragedie, in the beginning or Protafis, he was very pleaſant, ſo now in the Cataſtrophe he is very rigid, and threatens nothing but death. — <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentant omnia mortem.</hi> And verily all his paſſages would better become a Scenical Stage, then a Princely Court, wherein he layes his bloody Scene, and like an impoſthumed ſtomack vomits nothing but blood. <hi>Though brave</hi> Syndercombes <hi>great ſpirit</hi> ſaith he, <hi>be ſuppreſſed, yet there are a great rowl behind even of thoſe, which are in his own muſter-rowls, that are ambitious of the names of Deliverers of their Countrey, and do know what the action is that will purchaſe it.</hi> Which they all know to the contrary,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See the Humble Adviſe fol.</hi> 2.</note> that his Highneſs eminently, and the Officers and Souldiers of the Army ſubordinately, have (under God) been the Deliverers of their Country, and Reſtorers of our Peace and Tranquillity, whoſe ſaithfulneſs to the Commonwealth, the late Parliament gratefully and publikely acknowledged, and that they ſhall put a juſt value thereupon, to their general ſatisfaction. In vain therefore doth this Impoſtor go about to fright his <hi>Highneſs</hi> with a ſuppoſition of their infidelity, whoſe conſtancy as a rock is irremoveable, and with one voice averre.</p>
            <q>Nec feret illa dies ut commutemur in aevo.
<note place="margin">Auſo.</note>
            </q>
            <p>And further with a bug-bear he thinks to fright his <hi>Highneſs</hi> as others do Children: His Bed, his Table ſaith he, is not ſecure: and he ſtands in need of other Guardes to defend him againſt his own. But thoſe are but <hi>Figmenta &amp; terriculamenta puerorum,</hi> Feigned and childiſh ſcarre-crowes, and are above credulity.</p>
            <q>Nec pueri credunt, niſi qui nondum aere lavantur.
<note place="margin">Ju.</note>
            </q>
            <p>For he who hath the wiſedom to win the affections of a potent Army, cannot want the prudence to gain the love of his own Family, which as <hi>Cleobolus,</hi> is the beſt Oeconomy to govern by love, not fear,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Macrob Sat. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 11.</note> as his <hi>Highneſs</hi> doth, who as a greater <hi>Pater familia's</hi> as <hi>Macrobius</hi> adviſeth, uſeth his Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers as Familiars, and not as Servants, but as Fellow-ſervants.</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:94414:32"/>
            <p>And alſo his <hi>Highneſs</hi> Court is by his Virtuous and Religious Example formed and faſhioned into ſuch a pious and civil frame,
<note place="margin">Beiſius de Nat. Ep. ad Max.</note> as the Emperor <hi>Maximilian</hi> was, that no Chriſtian family can be better inſtituted, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed; and therefore his Followers cannot be inſcious, what an abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, and odious crime it is to betray their Lord and Maſter not onely in reſpect of them to whom by mutual relation they are obliged to be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, but in the apprehenſion of others, and even of thoſe who have inſtiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them to commit ſuch a deteſtable fact, and received benefit by it, and yet puniſhing them for it?</p>
            <p>As we read of <hi>Publius Servilius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Patric. de Princip. Tit.</hi> 20.</note> who being with <hi>C. Marius</hi> and <hi>L. Sylla</hi> Condemned as Enemies of the people of <hi>Rome,</hi> hid himſelf in a private Village, but was betrayed by his Servant, and ſo ſlain, whom for his prodition they firſt rewarded, and then as a Proditor precipitated from the Tarpeian ſtone.</p>
            <p>And ſo <hi>Sylla</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Nyſus,</hi> who inflamed with the love of <hi>Minois,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Patric. de Princip. Tit.</hi> 20.</note> upon his promiſe to her of marriage, betrayed her Fathers Palace to him; but in ſtead of ſtanding to his promiſe, he married her to the <hi>Ocean,</hi> and precipitated her to the bottom of the Sea.</p>
            <p>And ſo it is alſo related of <hi>Claudius,</hi> that before he had gotten the Empire, he was aſſured it by <hi>Caſſius, Cheraea,</hi> and <hi>Lapys,</hi> who ſlew <hi>Caligula,</hi> yet after he had poſſeſſed it,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dion. l.</hi> 60.</note> he cauſed them to be puniſhed with death. Becauſe though <hi>Caligula</hi> for his cruelty deſerved to be cut off, yet ought it not to have been done by <hi>Cheraea</hi> his <hi>Tribune</hi> to whom the ſafety of the Prince was committed: for how can a Prince expect that he will be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to him, was perfidious to another?</p>
            <p>And if <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Niceph. l.</hi> 14. c. 16.</note> who above all other Princes approved Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors, will give them a reward, yet did he permit his Souldiers to taunt them, and call a Spade a Spade.</p>
            <p>To which purpoſe <hi>Nicephorus</hi> reported of <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> that when he had conquered <hi>Zadochius</hi> who rebelled againſt him, and put him to flight, and forced him to repair to his familiar Friend <hi>Eudicius</hi> for refuge, who had received many benefits from him, yet in the night ungratefully cut off his head, and in all haſte carried it to <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> who gave him thanks for it, but would not permit him to remain with him, neither did he think the company of a perfidious Friend to be good matter or example to himſelf, or army: Inſomuch as if Proditors ſometimes eſcape capital puniſhment, yet can they never avoid capital hatred.</p>
            <p>By ſuch Patterns and Examples as theſe, which his Highneſſe Gentlemen and Servants have learned in their Academy (for what is his Court but a little Univerſity? ſo ſtudious are they of any erudition) are they ſettled and confirmed in their fidelity and allegeance, that his Highneſs doth not ſtand in need of another Guard to guard them, as this Impoſtor pretendeth: for they are his privy and Cabinet-guard, and nearer to him then his Life-guard, who in all privy and ſecret paſſages are prompt at hand, girded with their Swords to guard and defend his perſon with hazard of their Lives.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pol. Virgil. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 17.</note> As the couragious Servant of <hi>Maurice</hi> Duke of <hi>Saxony,</hi> did, who of late years ſeeing his Maſter ſuddainly aſſaulted by certain Turks that
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:94414:32"/>lay in ambuſh, and caſt from his Horſe, covered him with his own Body, and valiantly repelled the Enemy, until certain Horſe-men came in, and ſaved the Prince, but died himſelf a little while after, being hurt, and wounded in every part of his Body.</p>
            <p>Or as the undaunted and adventurous Eſquire of the Duke of <hi>Guyſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jean de Seres Charry f.</hi> 446.</note> who ſeriouſly ſurveying a Trenche, a certain Souldier levelled a Harquebuſſe at him, which his Squire eſpying as it was firing, ſuddainly caſting himſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them, and with the loſſe of his own Life, guarded his Maſters.</p>
            <p>Or elſe as that affectionate Servant of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbinus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Macrob. Sat. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 11.</note> who being commanded to be ſlain, hid himſelf in a ſecret place, but being betrayed, one of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants changed his apparel with him, and put his Ring on his finger, whom the Souldiers ruſhing into his Bed-chamber, ſuppoſing him to be his Maſter ſuddainly ſlew him, by which meanes his Maſter eſcaped.</p>
            <p>I could furniſh you with many more Examples of ſuch Noble Servants, who have ſacrificed their Lives for their Maſters ſafety; but I haſten to an end; <hi>Pulchrum eſt pro Domino mori,</hi> It is a moſt glorious act to die for a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; for which many Servants have been graced with Noble Elogies, and regiſtred in the Monuments of Eternal Memory.</p>
            <p>At the laſt this Hobgoblin would fright his <hi>Highneſs</hi> with the formida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble judgements of God out of the Scriptures; which he abuſeth as the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil did, when he tempted our Saviour, and have more analogy and propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to this Impoſtor then to his <hi>Highneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For thoſe places of Scripture which he thundreth out of <hi>Job,</hi> againſt him, are judgements generally denounced by the Spirit of God againſt the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for their evil and wicked imaginations, and machinations; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I do truly, and properly applie them to himſelf.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job.</hi> 20.24.</note> 
               <hi>Death and Deſtruction purſues him whereſoever he goes; they follow him everywhere. Darkneſs is hid in his ſecret places. A fire not blown ſhall conſume him: he ſhall flee from the Iron Weapon, and a Bow of Steel ſhall ſtrike him through: The Heavens ſhall reveal</hi> his iniquity, and the Earth ſhall riſe up againſt him.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 27.</note> That the eyes of the wicked ſhall fail, and they ſhall not eſcape, their hope ſhall be at the giving up the ghoſt. And ſo I fear it will be with him,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 10.21.</note> for before the giving up the ghoſt he will never repent, or be good.</p>
            <p>But to his <hi>Highneſs</hi> the antecedent Verſes may juſtly be aſcribed: Thou ſhalt be ſecure, becauſe there is hope, thou ſhalt digge about thee, and thou ſhalt take thy reſt in ſafety. Alſo thou ſhalt lye down, and none ſhall make thee afraid; yea many ſhall make ſuite unto thee.</p>
            <q>
               <l>— Rex eris, ajunt,
<note place="margin">Horat. Ep.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Si rectè facias; hic murus abeneus eſto</l>
               <l>Nil conſcire ſibi, nulla palleſcere culpa.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Thus would this Monopoly of miſchief have frighted his <hi>Highneſs</hi> with pernicious and deadly Threates; who though <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> and <hi>Hanibal</hi> were <hi>ad portas,</hi> yet would he not fear them, no not the principalities and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers that dwell in high places; nor all the crafts and ſubtilities of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, or this Impoſtor himſelf, who is one of his moſt pretious Imps; for the Lord is with him: But on the contrary, his <hi>Highneſs</hi> hath ſtruck him
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:94414:33"/>into ſuch a fright,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Horat l.</hi> 1. <hi>Ep.</hi> 10.</note> — <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t motu ad Lunam trapidabit arundinis umbram.</hi> That he is aſraid that every ſhadow is a Meſſenger: And that he ſhall not eſcape the hand of Juſtice. And though the Monſter lurk in <hi>Cacus cave;</hi> yet not withſtanding his prepoſterous ſteps will be diſcovered; his foot ſhall ſlide in due time, the day of his deſtruction is at hand, and the things that ſhal come upon him make haſt; for the Lord hath forſaken him, becauſe he hath forſaken the Lord, and followed that which is evil, and not that which is good: And this alſo may be ſaid of his confederates and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices, that, becauſe they partake of his villanies, they ſhall participate of his infamy.</p>
            <p>And thus have <hi>William Allens</hi> parturient mountaines produced a pittiful and ridiculous Mouſe; who with it for ſhame were beſt to conceale, and hide their heads in ſome obſcure chincke or corner, and never appear again, either in the light or night, for fear the Dog or the Cat catch them, which night and day watch, and obſerve their peepings.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>A word to his Poſt-ſcript.</head>
            <p>JUdicious Reader, expect two or three Sheets more of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, in refutation of this Impoſtors Jeſuitical Opinion, if in the mean time he eſcape the Halter of the Hang-man, which he himſelf not without juſt cauſe doubteth; and which I preſage will be the Caſtrophe and concluſion of his Tragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal deſign; for though the fugitive Sculk in ſome forrein ſeminary; yet the falſe Spirit may move him to come over into his Native Countrey, to do more miſchief, and to receive Sentence according to his deſerts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vivat</hi> PROTECTOR.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:94414:33"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
